<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>NOVEMBER: Poems in War Time, Electronic Edition</title>
            <author><name type="person" reg="Binns, Henry Bryan">Henry Bryan Binns, 1873-1923</name></author>
         </titleStmt>
	 <publicationStmt>
	   <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic Collections
	   and Services, Emory University</publisher>
	   <pubPlace>Atlanta, GA</pubPlace>
	   <address>
	     <addrLine>540 Asbury Circle</addrLine>
	     <addrLine>Woodruff Library</addrLine>
	     <addrLine>Atlanta, GA 30322</addrLine>
	   </address>
	   <availability><p>&#x00A9;Emory University. Permission is
	   granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce,
	   distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
	   by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
	   provided this header is included in its entirety.  For
	   inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Institute
	   for Jewish Studies, Emory University, Atlanta GA 30322 or
	   the Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic Collections and
	   Services, Woodruff Library, Emory University, Atlanta,
	   Georgia 30322 </p></availability> 
	   <date>2004</date>
	 </publicationStmt>
	 <seriesStmt>
	   <title>The Great War</title>
	 </seriesStmt>
	 <notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
	     <title>NOVEMBER: Poems in War Time</title>
	     <author>Henry Bryan Binns</author>
	     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
	     <publisher>Dodd, Mead &#x0026; Company</publisher>
	     <date>1918</date>
	   </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
	<projectDesc><p>Poetry contemporary to World War I (the Great
	War) has been digitized by OCR or rekeying. The work has been
	done in conjunction with Dr. Harry Rusche of the English
	Department, Emory University</p></projectDesc>
	<tagsDecl>
	  <rendition id="quote">Paragraphs including q or quote
	  elements indicate material that is in a block
	  quote.</rendition>
	  <rendition id="title">Where the title of a work is
	  italicized, it is marked with a title element, both in the
	  text and in footnotes.</rendition>
	  <tagUsage gi="q" render="quote">blockquote</tagUsage>
	  <tagUsage gi="quote" render="quote">blockquote</tagUsage>
	  <tagUsage gi="title" render="title">italic</tagUsage>
	</tagsDecl>
	<refsDecl><p>The page numbers of the volumes are indicated by
	page break elements</p>
	<p></p>
	</refsDecl>
	<classDecl>
	  <taxonomy id="lcsh">
	    <bibl>
	      <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
	    </bibl>
	  </taxonomy>
	</classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
	   <rs type="collection">poetry</rs>
	   <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs>
            <rs type="form">Unedited</rs>
            <rs type="genre">Poetry</rs>
            <rs type="geography">Great Britain</rs>
            <date>1900-1999</date>
         </creation>
	 <textClass>
	   <keywords scheme="lcsh">
	     <list>
	       <item>World War, 1914-1918--Poetry.</item>
	       <item>English poetry--20th Century.</item>
	       <item>War.</item>
	     </list>
	   </keywords>
	 </textClass></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!-- add your information here -->
	<change>
	  <date>2009</date>
	  <respStmt>
	    <name>Shruthi Vissa</name>
	    <resp>Beck Center staff</resp>
	  </respStmt>
	    <item>Proofing, encoding</item>
	</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<pb n="[1]"/>
   <titlePage id="binns300" type="half">
     <docTitle>
       <titlePart type="main">NOVEMBER
       </titlePart>
     </docTitle>
   </titlePage>
<pb entity="[2]"/>
<pb entity="[3]"/>
   <titlePage id="binns301" type="full">
     <docTitle>
       <titlePart type="main">NOVEMBER<lb/> Poems in War Time</titlePart>
     </docTitle>
       <byline> BY<lb/> HENRY BRYAN BINNS</byline>
       <docImprint>
	 <pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
	 <publisher>DODD, MEAD&#x0026;COMPANY</publisher>
	 <docDate>1918</docDate>
       </docImprint>
   </titlePage>
<pb n="[4]"/>

<div id="binns302" type="copyright">
<p>Copyright, 1917,</p>
<p>BY DODD, MEAD AND COMPANY, INC.</p>
</div>


<pb n="5"/>



<hi rend="italic"><l>DRAW into thine own being the circumambient Power,</l>
<l rend="indent">Till wholly invigorated by its divinity.</l>
<l>Thou art become enthusiast in every cell.</l>
<l>Poet throughout thy soul; breathing the fine</l>
<l>The starry breath of that spirit transcendent</l>
<l>Whose body thou may'st be, hast thou faith for it--</l>
<l>To vibrate, radio-active, with the intense</l>
<l>Joy of its immanent music, pain of the wild</l>
<l>Strange passionate intervals of its music.</l>
<l>That is no mere singing of words--pulsation</l>
<l>This, of celestial singing such as, it may be,</l>
<l>Thrills all the ether between the living stars.</l></hi>



<pb n="6"/>


<p>Note. --The Fourth and Fifth Preludes and "A Non-Combatant" first appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Ploughshare</hi>, and "The Hill-top
Wood" in the <hi rend="italic">Poetry Review</hi>. "A Schoolmaster in Picardy" was
suggested by Albert Thierry's <hi rend="italic">Des Conditions de la Paix</hi> (Paris,
<hi rend="italic">L'Union pour la Verit&#x009;</hi>, 1916), partly written in the trenches.
Its author was killed at Aix Noulette, 26 May, 1915.</p>




<pb n="7"/>


<div id="binns303" type="table of contents">
<figure type="binnstc" rend="inline">
<figDesc>Table of contents at front of Binns' "November"</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>



<pb n="[8]"/>

<pb n="[9]"/>

<pb n="[10]"/>
</front>

<body>
<pb n="11"/>

<div id="binns001" type="poem" n="1">
<head rend="center">November<lb/>
<rend type="center">FIVE PRELUDES</rend></head>

<div id="binns100" type="section" n="1">
<lg type="stanza">
<head rend="center">I</head>
<l>UP dripping from the sea</l>
<l rend="indent">Her weeds all watery,</l>
<l>She dashed against the windows as she came</l>
<l>The fringy hem of her wet</l>
<l>Cloak, and set</l>
<l>Me shivering closer to the genial flame.</l>
<l>Bleak was her face, turned westward from the</l>
<l rend="indent">grey</l>
<l>Uncompromising dawn of a grim day,</l>
<l>As though she would not countenance</l>
<l>Even his ungracious greeting!</l>
<l>O, when she turned her back on all romance</l>
<l>And left, so long ago, the East behind her,</l>
<l>Her heart of hope already had stopped beating.</l>
<l>Grey woman, going by my door.</l>
<l>There's nothing can remind her</l>
<l>Of colour any more!</l></lg></div>


<div id="binns101" type="section" n="2">
<lg type="stanza">

<head rend="center">II</head>

<l>O BUT a wood on a November day!--</l>
<l rend="left">Do you know the thing I say?</l>
<l>Do you see the russet bracken</l>
<l>That the sunlight lies among?--</l>


<pb n="NOVEMBER  12"/>



<l>See the shafts of brass among the dreamy grey</l>
<l>Pillars, where the low sun strikes, flashing?</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Above the cold still under-air</l>
<l>In the morning, pale above you,</l>
<l>Can you hear the north-wind passing</l>
<l>Over with his wingy flight?</l>
<l>Can you feel the quiet glee</l>
<l>Of the world's untroubled heart?--</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Summer's dead, the bracken's dead:</l>
<l>In the earth the trees have buried</l>
<l>Safely with their sap their treasure:</l>
<l>All for wrestling, all for mirth,</l>
<l>They stand ready.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Do you see how glad and gay</l>
<l>Is the Earth with all her trees?</l>
<l>How they welcome in the season</l>
<l>Rude and gruff ?   How they give</l>
<l>Themselves to the November</l>
<l>Day, and to the rough</l>
<l>Hands of winter?--</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>They have humour to enjoy</l>
<l>The changing moods of time:</l>
<l>To smile with the cold light and say</l>
<l>"I take you, too, November!"</l></lg></div>



<pb n="NOVEMBER 13"/>

<div id="binns102" type="section" n="3">
<lg type="stanza">
<head rend="center">III</head>

<l>HOW lovelily the larches bear their dead</l>
<l rend="inline">And the young oaks carry their widow-
weeds !</l>
<l>Gladder than Spring it is to see their glory</l>
<l>When the air is cold above the snow.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I say it's a glad thing to see that tall young larch</l>
<l>Standing all maiden-stately in gold apparel</l>
<l>To welcome him who now shall strip her bare.</l>
<l>Or yon, her sister, lovelier in thinner gossamer,</l>
<l>As it were sunny gleaming dew-drops veiling</l>
<l rend="inline">her:</l>
<l>And to know Winter laments naught but hath
his own pure splendour.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Winter!--when you stand here amid the wood,</l>
<l>There's some sublime gladness that summer
could not tell</l>
<l>Comes forth to praise you! Among these comrades</l>
<l>I hear another mightier word of freedom
spoken.</l></lg>

<lg type="Stanza">
<l>They weep, but not corrosive tears.</l>
<l>They let grief go, it also frees them.</l>

<l>13</l>



<pb n="NOVEMBER 14"/>

<l>Stedfast, evading naught, from life they withhold nothing.</l>
<l>Even their grief is presently a toy</l>
<l>For the spirit of young laughter.</l></lg></div>

<div id="binns103" type="essay" n="4">
<head rend="center">IV</head>****wasn't sure whether to format as paragraphs or as stanzas.

<p>WHEN joy escapes me, it is not this sin
or that I have committed, but, longing
after some unattained delight, I have forgotten
my Divine Companion.</p>

<p>Numb to His touch, what can I know of joy?
It is only in His presence that my spirit ventures
forth from its shadowy lair:--only responding
to His touch my spirit ventures.</p>

<p>But I forget, and unaccountably my busy day
is empty: meaningless seem the dear greetings
of my friends.</p>

<p>In His love is my meaning: vainly I seek my
self elsewhere !--I have outgrown my mind and
body. My spirit is no more at home except
in His companionship.</p>

<p>There only, is health for me, purpose and
happiness. But I forget: I recognise Him not:
I am no longer part of His delight, but my own
burden: my body and soul heavy with a forgetfulness that cuts me off from knowing Him at hand: that, looking in His face, is still alone,
and lying in His bosom, desolate.</p></div>

<l>14</l>



<pb n="NOVEMBER 15"/>

<div id="binns104" type="section" n="5">

<head rend="center">V</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>IF we withheld thee not, O thou divine delight,</l>
<l rend="inline">Thou radiance, whom we hide in our un-
happiness,</l>
<l>Our days would shine like gold thread in the
woof of night.</l>
<l>And God would take their labour for his
comely dress.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O thou divine delight, did we withhold thee
never</l>
<l>But dared with every breath to give thee
utterance,</l>
<l>Fear would have lost his foothold on the earth
for ever.</l>
<l>All of it caught again into the starry dance.</l>

<l>Aloof from thee, the oppressor holds himself, a
stranger;</l>
<l>The   unjust   shelters him   from   thee   with
shields of scorn:</l>
<l>Mightest thou but rejoice in these, thou wouldst
endanger</l>
<l>The last withholding thrones that keep thee
yet unborn.</l>

<l>15</l>



<pb n="NOVEMBER 16"/>

<l>Thou art not childish glee, nor gladness only
art thou:</l>
<l>Thou art Creative Power whom we have disobeyed :</l>
<l>Thou art the pulse of God within us here and now:</l>
<l>'Tis not of Death--of thee O life, we are afraid.</l>
</lg></div></div>

<pb n="17"/>


<div id="binnns002" type="poem" n="2">
<head>Freedom's Fellowship</head>

<div id="binns106" type="section" n="1">
<head rend="center">I</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>SEATED in the World's Playhouse, I beheld</l>
<l rend="inline">The Great Piece playing. Often I rebelled</l>
<l>At watching, and was fain to disobey</l>
<l>The Voice that held me at that Passion Play</l>
<l>Of Man's Redemption, a spectator, far</l>
<l>Removed from the actual agonists of a war</l>
<l>Wherein myself was mixed.   Till onlooking,</l>
<l>There woke within me the &#x00E6;onian Thing</l>
<l>Displayed in all that action.   I was 'ware</l>
<l>Of Him whom I beheld: the Actor there</l>
<l>Across the footlights, the Protagonist.</l>
<l>As one who had looked upon a glass and wist</l>
<l>Not that it was a mirror, nor whom he saw--</l>
<l>So gazing, suddenly, I knew with awe</l>
<l>It was no stranger, nor that Piece of Strife</l>
<l>Another than the substance of my life. . . .</l></lg>

<lg type="Stanza">
<l>Often on that Playhouse <sic>I'ld</sic> turn my back</l>
<l>To wander in the woods of Goodly Stack</l>
<l>And squirrel-haunted Squerryes.    There,  the trees</l>
<l>Showed me the sense of the ancient prophecies</l>
<l>That foretell a strange breaking-forth of power</l>
<l>Beautiful as the unfolding of that flower</l>

<l>17</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP 18"/>

<l>Whose bud is this mysterious Earth, that keeps</l>
<l>The glory so enfolded in her deeps</l>
<l>No man, however nimble be his wit,</l>
<l>Guessing at its delight can image it.</l>
</lg></div>



<div id="binns107" type="section" n="2">
<head rend="center">II</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>AS a tall pine, grappling the rock below</l>
<l rend="center">To climb the unsubstantial air, will grow</l>
<l>On a hand's breadth of the hill-shoulder, so</l>
<l>On a mere span of space, therein set firm,</l>
<l>Shall rise that royal spirit that hath its term</l>
<l>In Godhood, will a man but give his whole</l>
<l>Passion and patience to become one sole</l>
<l>Substance for it, that he may stand sublime</l>
<l>Upon a shoulder of the Hill of Time</l>
<l>Witnessing to the Timeless;--may rise up</l>
<l>Erect, to dare the lightning with his top:</l>
<l>Wrestle with wanton tempests, and not break</l>
<l>In any of their capricious clutches: take</l>
<l>The sun's pitiless drouth, out of that fire</l>
<l>Fashioning fibres still to lift up higher</l>
<l>The challenging dark shadow of his crown.</l>
<l>Dizzily up he climbs, but he thrusts down</l>
<l>More than a pine into the secret place</l>
<l>Forbidden to the light, beneath the face</l>
<l>Of Earth that looks on Heaven.   There is the
fount</l>

<l>18</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP 19"/>

<l>Of the ever-urgent impulse that doth mount</l>
<l>Up in the sap and out into the light,</l>
<l>Carrying the secret of that recondite</l>
<l>That enigmatic power, which is the mirth</l>
<l>Vibrant in all the Body of the Earth,</l>
<l>The gladness of Her being, whereof all</l>
<l>Things that are Hers partake. .  .</l>
<l rend="inline">High in the tall</l>
<l>Pine's upper fork, the kestrel hath his seat;</l>
<l>While up and down its shaft with clattering feet</l>
<l>The nut-brown squirrel scrambles: screams the jay:</l>
<l>The mild wood-pigeon all the livelong day</l>
<l>Flutes to his lady.   But the unexpressed</l>
<l>Residue of delight within the breast</l>
<l>Of Mother Earth aches so for utterance</l>
<l>In man as to becloud the pure expanse</l>
<l>Above him, burdening the atmosphere</l>
<l>Wherever he is gathered, with the sheer</l>
<l>Anguish of her unbearable delay</l>
<l>Till he respond to her, and She can say</l>
<l>That without which her joy is yet unspoken,</l>
<l>That   which   without   him   must   remain   but broken</l>
<l>Fragments and enigmatic words. O when</l>
<l>That which already is half awake in men</l>
<l>Bewildering their days with impulses</l>
<l>Mysterious that they know not to appraise</l>

<l>19</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  20"/>

<l>And so seek to evade--when it shall gain</l>
<l>Them wholly, and they serve with might and main</l>
<l>Its divine purpose to bestow on Man</l>
<l>God's meaning, they shall utter, for they can,</l>
<l>That Life on whose appearing Earth attends,</l>
<l>That word of words that changes into friends</l>
<l>The foes that hear it, for before their birth</l>
<l>It cradled them within the heart of the Earth.</l>
<l>Then life's assembled hosts shall hear again</l>
<l>The fiat of creation, spoken plain</l>
<l>Among them all, and they shall understand.</l>
<l>Can you not feel the wonder close at hand!</l>
<l>The Earth is quick with it beneath my feet,</l>
<l>So nearly is the whole of life complete.</l></lg></div>

<div id="binns108" type="section" n="3">
<head rend="center">III</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>A ROOT was I, and burrowed down my way</l>
<l>Year after year through sorry coloured clay;</l>
<l>And it was liker death than life to me</l>
<l>Through all that miry age of misery.</l>
<l>My spirit with enduring patience bore</l>
<l>By some mere pebble to be thwarted, or</l>
<l>To be encouraged by the slimy ooze</l>
<l>To new blind patient toil: my spirit whose</l>
<l>Manhood was made expressly for the wide</l>
<l>Regions of the light, where it would open-eyed</l>

<l>20</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP 21"/>

<l>Enter some little into God's design,</l>
<l>Echo his windy words, and even divine</l>
<l>The informing joy, clear, lucid, beautiful,</l>
<l>That lurks within all substance as a soul.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I strove, I sulked, I struggled for my breath</l>
<l>In that dark under-life that was like death,</l>
<l>So strange to any enfranchisement it seemed.</l>
<l>And I grew strong in the dark and stubborn-limbed</l>
<l>In that unkindness: yet withal I knew</l>
<l>My stubborn strength was of itself untrue</l>
<l>To   something   in   me,   though   it   was   full-vigoured:</l>
<l>For, nourished on resistance and the niggard</l>
<l>Diet of strife, I could not tell the whole</l>
<l>Truth that was kept a secret in my soul.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Somewhere--but far beyond hearing or seeing--</l>
<l>Somewhere upon the utter brink of being,</l>
<l>There dwelt another me, in other fashion</l>
<l>Occupied, fed upon a generous ration</l>
<l>Of open light and free air.   I had seen</l>
<l>The immortals, in a world of gold and green</l>
<l>And azure, that is only just beyond</l>
<l>The surface of the earth, free of its bond,</l>
<l>And floating all, as though upon a sea,</l>

<l>21</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP 22"/>

<l>Buoyed up on their aerial liberty.</l>
<l>But stranger than to know them anchored there</l>
<l>Almost within my reach--should I but dare</l>
<l>Reach up a moment from my groping toil,</l>
<l>Lift myself but a little from the soil</l>
<l>Into the sun--a voice familiar bade</l>
<l>My heart leave off its striving and be glad</l>
<l>In the translucent blessedness above me:</l>
<l>For these bright presences were they that love me,</l>
<l>And I their kin, companion and compeer.</l>
<l>Inhabitant already of their sphere</l>
<l>Of iridescent light, was I, unknowing:</l>
<l>Groping below, my spirit had been growing</l>
<l>Upward into a leafy-headed tree</l>
<l>That floated even now upon that sea</l>
<l>Of windy light, and was companion with</l>
<l>Those earth-born joys that breathe immortal breath.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I lifted up my heart: I was lift up</l>
<l>So upon gladness that I could not stop</l>
<l>Uttering twiggy praises full of leaf</l>
<l>Into that wondrous light as though all grief</l>
<l>Of my long labour in the dark were over</l>
<l>And I had now no more to do but hover</l>
<l>Upon the air, crooning my happiness</l>
<l>Fond as a pigeon.   Now the pitiless</l>

<l>22</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP 23"/>

<l>Lonely urge of my blind will down and down</l>
<l>Pulsed up out of my trunk into a crown</l>
<l>Of heavenly leaves: my stubbornness became</l>
<l>Gentle with gladness: I shook off the shame</l>
<l>Of my frustrated will, frustrated now</l>
<l>No longer, but achieved in every bough.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Now I have franchise both of sun and earth,</l>
<l>Till my last root is merry with the mirth</l>
<l>Of March, and I outstretch my branches bold</l>
<l>To joy, in the stubborn strength of that root-hold.</l>
<l>I live in the earth: I am no flickering wraith</l>
<l>Of fancy but the embodiment of faith.</l></lg></div>

<div id="binns109" type="section" n="4">
<head rend="center">IV</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>THERE are great spirits that stand up alone</l>
<l>As here and there an oak stands in a zone</l>
<l>Of corn and ample meadows: hero trees</l>
<l>Staunch in themselves against all enemies</l>
<l>And royal to small creatures in bad weather:</l>
<l>And there are spirits as great that stand together</l>
<l>In an inseparable fellowship.</l>
<l>Like the high pines on a hill-slope that's deep</l>
<l>In their long-fallen needles: spirits that are</l>
<l>As the high pines erect and columnar,</l>

<l>23</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  24"/>

<l>Because for many a lustre they have stood</l>
<l>Rank upon rank together in the wood,</l>
<l>Until each one is not so much a tree</l>
<l>As member of that great society</l>
<l>Of friends in whose association dwells</l>
<l>A presence I discover nowhere else.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And I have known a Quaker meeting when</l>
<l>The strangely still, intensely real men</l>
<l>And women ranked about me in the deep</l>
<l>Silence, were like a group of trees that keep</l>
<l>In their mysterious circle the untold</l>
<l>First and last secret of the manifold</l>
<l>Wonder of the world: a group of druid trees</l>
<l>Still haunted by the primal mysteries,</l>
<l>The elemental presences that are</l>
<l>Ever about us unfamiliar.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I was in a great grove of mighty thewed</l>
<l>Storm-challengers, that make a solitude</l>
<l>By their august companionship.  Apart</l>
<l>Spaciously set with magisterial art</l>
<l>To entertain in mutuality</l>
<l>Those vast emotions that could never be</l>
<l>The guests, even of comrades, if they stood</l>
<l>Crowded together in a thicket wood.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I found a freedom in that company</l>
<l>Elsewhere I had not found.   For to be free</l>

<l>24</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  25"/>

<l>You must be rooted in the rock, and keep</l>
<l>Your proper distance for the swing and sweep</l>
<l>Of the impassioning rhythm to vibrate through</l>
<l>Your being and make music out of you,--</l>
<l>One clear note of that full spontaneous speech</l>
<l>That no man sings alone, but many, each</l>
<l>Exulting in a wonder whereinto</l>
<l>Life pours the impetuous current of its blood</l>
<l>Pulsing from its one heart.  Upwells the flood</l>
<l>Of joy in them out of its reservoir</l>
<l>Through every root that has gone groping far</l>
<l>Down through the soil to catch in the still deep</l>
<l>Bosom of the under-earth, that seems to sleep</l>
<l>Always, the secret thrilling of a life</l>
<l>Beyond the utmost reach of stormy strife,</l>
<l>Beyond exhaustion and beyond dispute.</l>
<l>Well may they stand splendid and resolute!</l>
<l>Out of the marrow of the world they draw</l>
<l>Their sustenance.   The everlasting Law</l>
<l>Vibrating like a voice through all earth's frame</l>
<l>Vibrates in each, and every one of them</l>
<l>Shares its authority.    Strangers to fear,</l>
<l>Most royally they give what is most dear</l>
<l>To them.   Rooted in God and independent,</l>
<l>The ardour of their passion shines resplendent</l>
<l>As the moon's raiment when her beamy light</l>
<l>Clings round her dewily in the winter night.</l></lg></div>

<l>25</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP   26"/>

<div id="binns110" type="section" n="5">
<head rend="center">V</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>WHO strays among them, let him have a care</l>
<l>With what companionship he enters there:</l>
<l>For there are hours in which you cannot hide</l>
<l>Aught from the Trees: when you must open-eyed</l>
<l>Behold the shapes of dream you carry about</l>
<l>The world with you--your dark or shining rout</l>
<l>Of dreaded or desired imagining.</l>
<l>To life about you leaps the Magic Ring</l>
<l>Your feet can never step out of, because</l>
<l>It is your self that the dark circle draws</l>
<l>Enclosing you in the curve of its occult</l>
<l>Desire, against whose logic you revolt</l>
<l>With   half  your   will  in   vain.    Darkling,   it sweeps</l>
<l>Its compass, and within securely keeps</l>
<l>You prisoner of the line invisible</l>
<l>Traced by the rebel half of your own will:</l>
<l>Invisible, till in this solitude</l>
<l>Of Great Trees it become strangely indued</l>
<l>With substance,  and confront you with your fate.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Ay, but the Wood is not confederate</l>
<l>Against   you!--These are comrades among whom</l>

<l>26</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  27"/>

<l>The secret that is in your heart may come</l>
<l>Venturing forth out of its secrecy</l>
<l>Into the worship that they make with me--</l>
<l>A spacious living silence underneath</l>
<l>A spread of branches interwoven with</l>
<l>Slant sunbeams, in whose wide beneficence</l>
<l>Our spirits have no more need of defence:</l>
<l>A space of sunshine that dictates to none</l>
<l>The joy wherewith he shall be clothed upon,</l>
<l>But only bids him free his spirit wholly</l>
<l>Of chattering care and murderous melancholy,</l>
<l>And give it to delight: sunshine that quickens</l>
<l>That singing of the heart that flags and sickens</l>
<l>Where love's a prisoner and hath not yet</l>
<l>Climbed up on to the windy parapet</l>
<l>Of boundary cliff that gives upon the vast</l>
<l>Expanse of life, nor yet had heart to cast</l>
<l>Forth trusting to the waters of the sea</l>
<l>Of faith's incredible immensity.</l></lg></div>

<div id="binns111" type="section" n="6">
<head rend="center">VI</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>I AM myself at last, with now no more</l>
<l>Fluttering against the pane, at the locked door</l>
<l>No more entreaty. Now with bitterness</l>
<l>I claim no more forgiveness or redress:</l>
<l>The battle-cries that echo about me cease</l>
<l>To nerve me or unnerve me: I have peace.</l>

<l>27</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP 28"/>

<l>My spirit from his age-long strife arose:</l>
<l>He stood no more contending with his foes:</l>
<l>Flung down his sword and shield: put off his mask</l>
<l>Of warrior, and to his proper task</l>
<l>Turning with a quick gesture seemed no longer</l>
<l>The self I knew: wiser he was and younger.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I felt my body quicken with that might</l>
<l>Of mastery that is the soul's delight</l>
<l>When, from its secret chamber issuing,</l>
<l>Clad in the candour of a May-morning,</l>
<l>Comes the Almighty Fiat forth that changes</l>
<l>The aspect of the world in all its ranges</l>
<l>With a new rhythm, whereto all circumstance</l>
<l>Responds, and the eternal atoms dance.</l>
<l>Comes a new pattern, comes another norm</l>
<l>Into creation, and the subtle form</l>
<l>Of every creature answering to it, wins</l>
<l>Fresh meaning, and another age begins.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The peace I enter into is alive</l>
<l>With living life, that needs no longer strive</l>
<l>Because it is triumphant as a flower</l>
<l>Whereof the air admits the sovereign power,</l>
<l>The substance of whose delicacy carries</l>
<l>Magic that with the power creative marries</l>
<l>So that its ecstasy, and it alone,</l>

<l>28</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  29"/>

<l>Brings to the earth a hitherto unknown</l>
<l>Henceforth eternally recurrent joy.</l>
<l>When I assign my heart to this employ</l>
<l>It lifts me up that suddenly I dare</l>
<l>Find foothold on the skyey thoroughfare</l>
<l>To journey on my errands.  Joy afresh</l>
<l>Sets her republic up within my flesh</l>
<l>With all its liberties of continence,</l>
<l>Where sullen moody disobedience</l>
<l>Answered the tyrant: for republican</l>
<l>Is the full-statured body of a man,</l>
<l>His freedom and delight are the good-health</l>
<l>Of that irradiated commonwealth</l>
<l>That is so capable of joy its cells</l>
<l>Conspire together against whatever else</l>
<l>Usurps its government, but all their will</l>
<l>Is Gladness, his commandments to fulfil.</l></lg></div>

<div id="binns112" type="section" n="7">
<head rend="center">VII</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>O LARGE is life!--The life I come into</l>
<l>Stretches so large about me as I go</l>
<l>Upon my errands, that I seem to be</l>
<l>Already a dweller in that Liberty</l>
<l>That is itself the immortal blessedness</l>
<l>I sought, but dared not deem I could possess.</l>
<l>I move about in it as in the temple</l>
<l>Built by my spirit for its worship: ample</l>

<l>29</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  30"/>

<l>For it as the whole starry-raftered Night,</l>
<l>But not too lonely-wide for my delight</l>
<l>To fill it, as the worshipping fulfils</l>
<l>All some vast minster, when, crossing its sills,</l>
<l>You enter from the noisy stranger street</l>
<l>And on the instant are a part of it:</l>
<l>So, when out of the traffic I come in</l>
<l>To mine own freedom, once again I win</l>
<l>The great horizon of Reality--</l>
<l>To know in everything I hear and see</l>
<l>My fellowship, as it were all one life with me.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>More than myself it is I: In It alone</l>
<l>I am the master of the fully-grown</l>
<l>Faculties of my spirit, incorporate</l>
<l>Only in its high purpose to create</l>
<l>A body for my joy, a consciousness</l>
<l>That my delight shall hold against distress</l>
<l>If but for an hour: only in it I know</l>
<l>The imperative command, that bade me go</l>
<l>Forth into birth and being, justified:</l>
<l>Only in it, immortal, I abide</l>
<l>Set in my place, as in the firmament</l>
<l>Of godhood, till its purpose be forspent.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>For this my larger life is that wherein</l>
<l>I enter into Freedom, and begin</l>
<l>Participating in the power that flows</l>

<l>30</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP 31"/>

<l>Through all the living fellowship of those</l>
<l>That are its members and embody it.</l>
<l>Though we be only simple folk that sit</l>
<l>Wrapped in its life together, one we are</l>
<l>With all the heavenly host that, star by star,</l>
<l>Declares God's Glory, filling up the span</l>
<l>Of worship, since the dark of death began,</l>
<l>With the inseparable company</l>
<l>Of them that enter into Liberty.</l></lg></div>

<div id="binns113" type="section" n="8">
<head rend="center">VIII</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>I AM among my comrades: my delight</l>
<l>Is all about me like a starry bright</l>
<l>Company.    All the wonder in the air</l>
<l>Is actual communion that I share</l>
<l>With that great fellowship in whom I am</l>
<l>Enkindled from a coal into a flame.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Often when I am most alone that joy</l>
<l>Encircles me with friends: and they convoy</l>
<l>The ship of my desire safe through the shoal-</l>
<l>Waters into the open sea: my whole</l>
<l>Being is theirs because they set me free</l>
<l>Who catch me up into their company</l>
<l>And carry me out to the Open Sea.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>When I am left with my defeated gladness,</l>
<l>And am beset about by sullen madness</l>
<l>That battens upon misery, and my numb</l>

<l>31</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP 32"/>

<l>Spirit cries out for succour--then they come</l>
<l>Thronging about me, and I feel the anguish</l>
<l>That ate into my soul begin to languish</l>
<l>Because of them: I know again the strong</l>
<l>Arms of that joy whereunto I belong.</l>
<l>Anew each day with all my will I break</l>
<l>Out of the circle of these cares that make</l>
<l>A loneliness round the imprisoned heart.</l>
<l>For having once discovered myself part</l>
<l>Of the Great Life that only comrades know,</l>
<l>Something divine in me will not forgo</l>
<l>His birthright, but still challenges whatso</l>
<l>Arrogance of things seen would paralyse</l>
<l>The visionary power that makes me wise</l>
<l>To know my comrades of eternity</l>
<l>Sharing the moment of delight with me,</l>
<l>Respiring with me that immortal breath</l>
<l>That is one life beyond despair and death.</l></lg></div>

<div id="binns114" type="section" n="9">
<head rend="center">IX</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>FELLOWSHIP is a  grove of trees that stand</l>
<l>Taller than the thick wood on either hand</l>
<l>As heroes stand than men. The heart lifts higher</l>
<l>Entering here. It ventures to aspire</l>
<l>To its full manhood: rises up above</l>

<l>32</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  33"/>


<l>Its puerility to imagine love</l>
<l>And friendship as the god-like exercise</l>
<l>Of all the soul.    It catches from the eyes</l>
<l>Of these companions glances that are strange</l>
<l>As sunbeams to the vulgar interchange</l>
<l>Of men and women: vaguely apprehends</l>
<l>As he enters here what is this world of friends</l>
<l>So new, so wide, so full of worship.   Dread</l>
<l>Seizes him lest he let his thoughts instead</l>
<l>Of their clear thoughts ignorantly deceive</l>
<l>His soul, and he begin to disbelieve</l>
<l>In their heroic truth, convinced again</l>
<l>Of the obsequious truths that seem so plain.</l>
<l>It is not death but doubt that comes between</l>
<l>Spirits that for a golden hour have been</l>
<l>One spirit of delight.   Faith can make one</l>
<l>Of many, but in doubt's dominion</l>
<l>There is no bond: love falls asunder: life</l>
<l>Is torn to pieces for the pack of strife</l>
<l>To feed on:   God is argued into naught</l>
<l>By men who cannot hold the faithful thought</l>
<l>Of his transcendent purpose in the whole</l>
<l>World wonder. . . .</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">Entering, I bid my soul</l>
<l>Beseech in veriest humility</l>
<l>To become part of it like any tree</l>
<l>Of this great grove of aspiration planted</l>
<l>Together, by the breath of God enchanted.</l>

<l>33</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  34"/>

<l>I feel the grave humorous light caressing</l>
<l>The creatures of the wood: no dread oppressing</l>
<l>The stillness with solemnity to crush</l>
<l>Their mirthful life: but the half-audible hush</l>
<l>Is of some gracious God whose presence gives</l>
<l>A deeper meaning to each life that lives</l>
<l>In his presiding splendour, until each</l>
<l>Becomes a particle of the God's speech</l>
<l>To tell a truth it cannot comprehend,</l>
<l>Save that to that delight it loves to lend</l>
<l>Its heart.   Now he begins to utter me</l>
<l>Among them.   Now mine eyes begin to see</l>
<l>The meaning of the grove, begin to feel</l>
<l>The presence that these living forms reveal</l>
<l>In every gesture, every living line:</l>
<l>For now their comradeship is become mine,</l>
<l>And this that, all together, they concealed</l>
<l>From me, eagerly now to me they yield.</l>

<l>There is no onlooker may understand</l>
<l>The mystery embodied in that band</l>
<l>Of comrades.    Final truth it is, and they</l>
<l>Only can know it.   He that would betray</l>
<l>The secret that is freedom must declare</l>
<l>The divine wonder in his being--bare,</l>
<l>Body and soul, in that translucent air:</l>
<l>Must become parcel of that infinite,</l>
<l>There is no other way to utter it.</l>

<l>34</l>



<pb n="FREEDOM'S FELLOWSHIP  35"/>

<l>O the world's meaning is a bud, a splendour</l>
<l>Sealed-up, saving as, to some spirit tender</l>
<l>To his caress, Love may vouchsafe a proof</l>
<l>Of what is yet hid.   She thenceforth aloof</l>
<l>A little from the press of men's affairs</l>
<l>Must stand.  Strangely, and all at unawares</l>
<l>The vision was vouchsafed: the unconcealed</l>
<l>Delight   of   earth.     Hers   now   the   perfect wheeled</l>
<l>Glory of a hundred petals, still tight-packed</l>
<l>In its November sheath.   O hers the Fact</l>
<l>That shall fulfil the world we sense and see</l>
<l>With its more intimate reality.</l></lg></div></div>




<pb n="36"/>

<div id="binns003" type="poem" n="3">
<head rend="center">To Love</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>LOVE, to the little-loving nebulous Thou appearest:</l>
<l>Their eyes worship not Thee. Now that I get</l>
<l>Thy range</l>
<l>How beyond belief exquisite is Thy form!</l>
<l>Thou starry Light-bearer, young-eyed Child of the Morning,</l>
<l>Impartest the purposeful meaning of the Creation</l>
<l>To the learners of Thee.--O Joy everlasting,</l>
<l>We that learn Thee are one joy, one composite glory--</l>
<l>As a golden Dandelion, all our florets together</l>
<l>One flower in a field! As the sun, heavenly Dandelion,</l>
<l>Rays light forever out recklessly, keeps no account of it,</l>
<l>What he means is to shine, God help him!--so is the lover.</l>
<l>So is the man raised up in Thee to the power of his manhood,</l>
<l>Stedfastly golden, resplendent, joy-outpouring.</l>


<pb n="TO LOVE  37"/>

<l>Yea, as the god-like Sun, that Unit of Lovers</l>
<l>Stablished in heaven to radiate earth-impregnating joy,</l>
<l>Are we Thy learners, together his fellow, the Company</l>
<l>Of Them that Beget Delight . . .</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>To beget a love-child who would not give the price Earth asks?</l>
<l>But O, bless&#x00E8;d are they that, loving, beget the invisible</l>
<l>Form of Thy pure power, mighty deliverer,</l>
<l>Spirit of Sunshine!--</l>
<l>Apart from Thee, Love, Power is a monster.</l>
<l rend="indent">Empty of value.</l>
<l>Vain all the wealth of nations, if it be not for</l>
<l rend="indent">Thy spending:</l>
<l>Wasted the resolute toil of a people not learn&#x00E8;d in Thee.--</l>
<l>Thine is fruition.   There is no joy but rejoiceth in Thee.--</l>
<l>Love, lacking Thee, the ages miscarry.   Their gathered-up knowledge</l>
<l>Is naught, for without Thee Truth is not.--</l>
<l>Thou alone knowest the whole use of the world.--</l>


<pb n="TO LOVE  38"/>

<l>The use of the world is at last Thy joy that abides:</l>
<l>Substance eternal, ether irradiant with the complete</l>
<l>Purpose of an inexhaustible life outpoured.--</l>
<l>He who carries the wonder within him knows it divine.--</l>
<l>Thou, Love, alone settest free.--I feel Thy passion</l>
<l>Patiently gather within me: Thy procreant power grow</l>
<l>Sure in me of its sanctity: not-to-be-thwarted: god-like:</l>
<l>All of me handling with calm clear eyes of decision :</l>
<l>Pouring my life forth with a Hand that is yet my hand.--</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Thou duly directest the crawling caterpillar,</l>
<l>Else a vain destroyer of delicate promises,</l>
<l>Eater of buds:--Thou transformest him into an airy carrier</l>
<l>To and fro in the fields of the flowers' messages.</l>
<l>It is  only toward Thee  at last that Desire emerges</l>
<l>Out of its chrysalis into the light on wings.--</l>


<pb n="TO LOVE   39"/>

<l>Thou createst a whole out of this confusion of parts,</l>
<l>In Thee the excesses of passion that are not wholesome for life</l>
<l>Are justified: they come at last to their measure in Thee.</l>
<l>Infinite Thy demand, O Love, as the infinite blind</l>
<l>Urge of unuttered longing: wild, pent-up to madness:</l>
<l>Fiery mouth not to be quenched at dear lips: whose kisses</l>
<l>Poison its love, till Thou, God, overpowering</l>
<l>That stormy power with Thy purpose, yoke it, exuberant</l>
<l>To Thy task of creating Joy not less but more passionate.--</l>
<l>Thou givest eyes to Desire.--All my meaningless parts</l>
<l>Love, when thou touchest me, Thou sanctifiest with sight.--</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Thou makest whole that takest not less than all that I can be.</l>
<l>That only Thou ownest for Thine wherein a man pledges</l>
<l>Body and soul and spirit in one passion, holding</l>
<l>Earth for his witness and the eternal stars.--</l>

<pb n="TO LOVE  40"/>

<l>When I began to love, and felt my soul going forth</l>
<l>Away from me to the Unknown, I was afraid to be squandered,--</l>
<l>So many a greedy mouth: many a snatching hunger!--</l>
<l>After, I feared lest this that was precious only for spending,</l>
<l>Life's own seed, in me hoarded remain, and perish.</l>
<l>Of Thee less ignorant now, I fear either death no longer.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Immanent in our loving, Thou transcendest, O Love, our passion:</l>
<l>All of our love together is but a little of Thee.--</l>
<l>Within Thine  orb,  as within the  all-circling horizon,</l>
<l>Each of my passionate loves shines in his place, secure:</l>
<l>Ever-sustainer of loveliness, world-enamouring presence,</l>
<l>Loving them, I give worship, O not to them, but to Thee.</l>
<l>Thou fulfillest, O Love, my entire manhood with praise.</l>


<pb n="TO LOVE  41"/>

<l>Thou art as the Sun. Thou beholdest the ugly secrets of shame</l>
<l>Averting not thence Thy clear eyes: changing not into hatred</l>
<l>Their undismayed regard.--Derelict, desert-defeated,</l>
<l>The poor pilgrim of life in his last extremity</l>
<l>Catches that wonderful gaze and on the instant forgets</l>
<l>His dismay at the cries of the flocking heavy-winged birds.</l>
<l>As with the triumphing choral of the great Ninth Symphony</l>
<l>Joy breaks out of his torn body to Thy embrace.--</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Who now shall sustain the lad, the soldier descending,</l>
<l>Snatched like Kor&#x00E9; the Maid from an April world, down</l>
<l>Into the bowels of death, into the underworld air,</l>
<l>There to do battle, to make corpses with his young hands--?</l>
<l>Only Thou art sufficient, down in that place, to keep</l>
<l>His spirit alive. Day-spring of beauty inexhaustible,</l>



<pb n="TO LOVE   42"/>

<l>Love Divine, in whose Almighty power I uphold him.--</l>
<l>When I forget Thee, how helpless my love is of succour!</l>
<l>Love is a pitiful thing once it is parted from Thee.</l></lg></div>


<pb n="43"/>

<div id="binns004" type="poem" n="4">
<head rend="center">DELAY NOT, LOVE</head>
<lg type="stanza">

<l>DELAY not, Love, lest what I have of power</l>
<l>To hold against Thou come, my marriage-dower.</l>
<l>Be conjured, through some unbelief of mine</l>
<l>That doubts Thee or Thy coming, to assign</l>
<l>Itself to another lord, and so betray</l>
<l>My will to accomplish his desire:--delay</l>
<l>Thy coming to my government no longer,</l>
<l>So many a foe have I--but Thou art stronger.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>When I behold the promise of the world</l>
<l>Blighted, and all a kindly people hurled</l>
<l>In God's face with a lie by one mad will--</l>
<l>Love, I know hardly how to endure until</l>
<l>My little kingdom be possessed by Thee,</l>
<l>There comes so many a royal treachery</l>
<l>To impose upon my will--so many a claimant</l>
<l>To power, kingly and clad in shining raiment.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I am not unacquainted with Thee, Love,</l>
<l>But to know Thee a little is not enough.</l>
<l>Loving a little, must I not admit</l>
<l>These that look like Thee?--Whole and infinite</l>


<pb n="DELAY NOT, LOVE  44"/>

<l>Is my necessity for all Thou art.</l>
<l>Henceforth I will do naught from Thee apart</l>
<l>That, love being all my business and profession,</l>
<l>All of my being may be in Thy possession.</l></lg></div>


<pb n="45"/>


<div id="binns005" type="poem" n="5">
<head rend="center">The Greeting</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>HER pinched uncompromising face was pitiful</l>
<l>Seeming to plead for love, and yet with what a proud</l>
<l>Accent she said, setting my proffered love aside:--</l>
<l>"My friend, if you had only looked with faithful eyes</l>
<l>Into the truth I showed you, if you had not faltered</l>
<l>Upon the sills of sight and, guessing prematurely,</l>
<l>So misconceived the look in which I told you all</l>
<l>As to make foolishness of it with your wild answer,</l>
<l>You would have understood what I can never tell:</l>
<l>You would have seen me, for I ventured forth to you:</l>
<l>To you, unseeing, I came forth out of my secret.</l>
<l>If haply, mirrored in your comprehending gaze,</l>
<l>I might at last behold my spirit unknown to me,</l>
<l>Know myself in your eyes, and solve at last my riddle."</l>
<pb n="THE GREETING  46"/>

<l>I heard her speak, I made a silence of myself</l>
<l>That I might all be, as it were, one word of welcome,</l>
<l>As it were hands held out all ready to receive her--</l>
<l>Wherefore my lips were silent, hands folded before me--</l>
<l>For her, all that I am was waiting in my eyes.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Then she came forth to me, radiant, a spirit of light.</l>
<l>Before whose sovereign pure splendour the condescension</l>
<l>My fond heart had prepared was utterly ashamed:</l>
<l>I saw her: I forgot my folly, worshipping in her</l>
<l>That wonder of else incredible divinity</l>
<l>That searches the world through if there be any place</l>
<l>Unoccupied by the busy turmoil of our cares</l>
<l>Wherein its quiet hands may find employment.</l></lg></div>


<pb n="47"/>

<div id="binns006" type="poem" n="6">****Is it alright to format the poem this way: as a series of quotations?
<head rend="center">THE EXILE</head>

<p>Heribert Freimuth, hyphenated American, writes:</p>

<q><div id="binns115" type="section" n="1">
<head type="sub">I.  OF GERMANY</head>
<lg type="stanza">

<l>SHE had a place midmost among the nations--</l>
<l>Woman, large-built, for the elemental throes;</l>
<l>Her frame a harp superb for the exultations</l>
<l>Of Life, what time his hands were magical</l>
<l>With starry rhythms to draw from her the chant</l>
<l>Inimitable of her being, all</l>
<l>Mysteriously resonant--</l>
<l>And for his solemn, heavy-fingered woes.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Great-hearted she, and like a mother's</l>
<l>Her voice was then!</l>
<l>There was not one among men</l>
<l>Fibred for Freedom's song</l>
<l>--Her music--but was hers: and she was ours:</l>
<l>More than another's</l>
<l>Her mighty voice doth yet of right belong</l>
<l>To the great-chorded harmony</l>
<l>Of Man that wants it now.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Ours still the song that still</l>
<l>Vibrates with her own voice: but she—-</l>


<pb n="THE EXILE   48"/>

<l>Bewitched by warlock Powers</l>
<l>That steal away the will--</l>
<l>Is stol'n from us.</l>
<l>Our joy that was in her they have made dumb.</l>
<l>Now in her place a stranger stands:</l>
<l>For face, a mask: her brow</l>
<l>Blind with a wild possession and piteous</l>
<l>In its blank arrogancy: numb</l>
<l>Is she to all old kinship, strange</l>
<l>To the sisterhood of the Lands.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">As if caught in a curse,</l>
<l>She suffers all some werwolf change:</l>
<l>Horror is in her hands:</l>
<l>Her womanhood perverse</l>
<l>Preys upon that it once caressed:</l>
<l>The mother-fountains of her breast</l>
<l>Turn to a treacherous, devouring drouth</l>
<l>And suckle madness.   Ay, she is</l>
<l>Changed all; but most her mouth,</l>
<l>That wonder-teller, fairy-eloquent</l>
<l>As April's when the influence of the South</l>
<l>Opens her lips with summer promises.</l>
<l>Her spirit on what wildwood breath</l>
<l>Would issue, leading forth for our embrace</l>
<l>From out the ever unspent</l>
<l>Treasure of joys she had in hiding,</l>
<l>Some unimagined grace</l>


<pb n="THE EXILE  49"/>

<l>Whereof, save from her mouth we had no tiding--</l>
<l>Her mouth that now, wolfishly, barks out death.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">O now with what vile rout</l>
<l>Of shameful things that wait upon her</l>
<l>She mocks at those her younger years!</l>
<l>Bewitched, she hath gone out</l>
<l>From the company of her peers</l>
<l>Boasting of her dishonour.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">And who, of those that honoured once her name,</l>
<l>Seeing in her still the light she used to be,</l>
<l>Howso obscured, shall lead her back? Her own</l>
<l>Bleed inly with her shame:</l>
<l>Their every nerve aches to her infamy.</l>
<l>Who love her most, they are least prone</l>
<l>To absolve her unrepentant: to the last,</l>
<l>Implacable in their loving, they would strive,</l>
<l>Withstanding her false will, by any means to cast</l>
<l>Out of her body the deceitful Thing</l>
<l>Whereto she hath given her womanhood</l>
<l>To be its substance, glorying</l>
<l>Because it pulses in her blood.</l>
<l>Vibrates and is alive</l>
<l>Throughout her many-chorded frame.</l></lg>


<pb n="THE EXILE  50"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">He that most loves her, let him now be hard</l>
<l>Against her pitiful distress,</l>
<l>Lest it disarm his love of power to save her!</l>
<l>I dare not pity her howso by battle marred,</l>
<l>Howso sharp anguish cruelly engrave her</l>
<l>Dear old-time loveliness.</l>
<l>For I was bred of her and know</l>
<l>Her too self-pitying weakness:</l>
<l>How loving Liberty a little, to his foe</l>
<l>She yielded up herself with wicked meekness;</l>
<l>For when her love of him brought her to peril, she</l>
<l>Failed in her little love and grew ashamed she had loved liberty.</l></lg></div></q>

<q><div id="binns116" type="section" n="2">
<head type="sub">2.    OF HIS YOUTH</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>ALWAYS I see you, Mother, as a fair</l>
<l>Woman, pleasant in any place to greet,</l>
<l>And smiling with a smile</l>
<l>Childishly innocent.</l>
<l>O it is worse in you than any guile</l>
<l>That, evilly-mated,</l>
<l>You are so debonair,</l>
<l>So well-content.</l>
<l>Spirit so incomplete--</l>
<l>Soul so unconsecrated</l>
<l>By memory or passion, to rebel!</l>

<pb n="THE EXILE  51"/>

<l rend="indent">I wonder if Demeter's sunny-eyed</l>
<l>Daughter submitted so</l>
<l>Obsequiously, once she was Pluto's bride--</l>
<l>Smiled so, being Queen in Hell</l>
<l>And mistress of her foe!</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">Did she--doth she so smile,</l>
<l>Hers is a better right than yours,</l>
<l>Dreadfully mild mother of my exile!</l>
<l>For though, in chambers dark</l>
<l>Beyond imagining, his love she endures,</l>
<l>Its nakedness is not so stark</l>
<l>As your &#x00C6;gisthean lord's,</l>
<l>To whose tyrannous pleasure, rather</l>
<l>Than bid him do his worst,</l>
<l>Your too complaisant beauty accords</l>
<l>What erst</l>
<l>Was sacred to my father.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">

<l>Freedom!--'Twas he begat me!   He whose high begetting</l>
<l>Sings through my being that I am his son</l>
<l>Sprung of his blood and nation:</l>
<l>Sings with your young voice, Mother,</l>
<l>In the utterly sweet singing</l>
<l>Of that forgotten March when Germany</l>
<l>Was at her love's beginning:</l>
<l>Music that still, in each and every one</l>


<pb n="THE EXILE  52"/>

<l>Of all my nerves is mine beyond forgetting,</l>
<l>My spirit's exultation</l>
<l>That he,</l>
<l>He was my sire, none other!</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">I was young when he perished.   I remember</l>
<l>Those far days, and how then you delighted</l>
<l>In his babe.   It is my November</l>
<l>Now, and your joy in me long ago blighted.</l>
<l>But in me it is ever quick-water,</l>
<l>The bubbling-up, throbbing</l>
<l>Of that long-ago joy,</l>
<l>That cradle-singing that before I was a boy</l>
<l>Was mine!</l>
<l>O, still a spring divine</l>
<l>Amid this world of slaughter,</l>
<l>It is the heedless gay</l>
<l>Trill of some bold November robin</l>
<l>Whose small roundelay</l>
<l>Breaks down my grief and sets him sobbing.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">Though I shall always carry about the mark</l>
<l>Of that grim boyhood in a world all dark</l>
<l>To me--Orestes-like, sun-worshipper am I.</l>
<l>But chiefly Thee I praise, O pitiless Apollo,</l>
<l>That, unlike young Orestes, me thou maddest not</l>
<l>With the Avenger's Cry</l>

<pb n="THE EXILE  53"/>

<l>Against a queen so miserably royal:</l>
<l>That me, O pitiless One, thou badest not</l>
<l>Wipe out in blood my mother's shame</l>
<l>Striking at her with dreadful hands.</l>
<l>But, westering, bad'st me follow</l>
<l>Thee hither oversea,</l>
<l>To this, that of all lands</l>
<l>Was worthy of my father's name:</l>
<l>America, ample, republican and loyal</l>
<l>To Freedom her first love, and arbiter to be</l>
<l>Of Justice: pitiless, clear-eyed</l>
<l>As Thou, shadow-denier:</l>
<l>Thou, chain-of-slumber breaker:</l>
<l>Thou, mocker at the tyrant and his bride:</l>
<l>Resolute world-awaker,</l>
<l>Multiplier</l>
<l>Of rebels against vain authority!</l>
<l>This is thy land, Apollo, and at last like thee</l>
<l>The world's peace-maker.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">Wonderful as to a fugitive slave</l>
<l>When he creeps trembling out of the hunted wood</l>
<l>Into the welcoming security</l>
<l>Of a friendly hearth, her welcome was to me.</l>
<l>Slowly to it my numb being unfroze;</l>
<l>Till when I understood</l>
<l>That she too, this America, had foes,</l>


<pb n="THE EXILE  54"/>

<l>How eagerly all that I was</l>
<l>All the Apollo-worship of my spirit, clave</l>
<l>To her good cause!</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">Cut sharply from its trunk, my twig</l>
<l>Flourished upon the free</l>
<l>Flowing, exuberant sap of that young tree</l>
<l>Of Liberty, whereon I was engrafted:</l>
<l>I made bold to declare</l>
<l>The secret manhood in me to that sun,</l>
<l>Responded to the greetings wafted</l>
<l>Me on that virginal air:</l>
<l>Freedom pulsed through me, faith in me grew big,</l>
<l>Ousted my fear and took me all for its dominion.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">With me there was transplanted</l>
<l>Into this generous  soil, this orchard of my choice,</l>
<l>So much of the old Germany</l>
<l>As it was granted</l>
<l>To a young lad to bear away with him.</l>
<l>Answering to the deeds of Liberty</l>
<l>There would thrill in the fibres of my being</l>
<l>Many an old clear voice</l>
<l>Of sunny Rhineland or of grim</l>

<pb n="THE EXILE  55"/>

<l>Forest: my new world was forever freeing</l>
<l>Of its dumb shame some unremembered part of me.</l>

<l rend="indent">And when in battle for her, I became</l>
<l>One body with America, and shed</l>
<l>Wholly mine orphanage of shame,</l>
<l>No more was I an exile hope-defeated,</l>
<l>Mine was this country of the exile's hope:</l>
<l>Even my father was no longer dead,</l>
<l>No longer was he of achievement cheated:</l>
<l>His spirit with mine exulted and found scope</l>
<l>For all its courage in the storm</l>
<l>That burst upon America: I knew him</l>
<l>Then ever beside me, and before</l>
<l>Ever that Siegfried-murdering Attila,</l>
<l>Ever that sinister &#x00c6;gisthean form</l>
<l>That pursues Freedom if he may</l>
<l>Seduce his bride from him once more:</l>
<l>And here in this New World, wrestling with him, we threw him.</l></lg></div></q>

<q><div id="binns117" type="section" n="3">
<head type="sub">3.    TO THE ALLIES</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>O NOT because ye are guiltless, but because</l>
<l>In your own selves ye chiefly hate</l>
<l>The lingering old fierce lust to dominate:</l>


<pb n="THE EXILE  56"/>

<l>With Mammonry and Might</l>
<l>To override the faithful laws</l>
<l>Of Freedom, that uphold</l>
<l>With   a   divine  equality,   each  people  in  his right:--</l>
<l>Because the Day is not yet old</l>
<l>That broke for you upon the haunted Night</l>
<l>When lying Ashteroth</l>
<l>Had you seduced, in the occult half eclipse</l>
<l>Of her slim moon, to forego the bread of truth</l>
<l>And suck the baleful honey of her lips</l>
<l>That promise treacherously:--</l>
<l>The day is not yet old and still your flesh</l>
<l>Is tainted in you with the envenomed sweet</l>
<l>Of the seductress, as itself had been a meat</l>
<l>Offered to the Idol:--</l>
<l>O because afresh</l>
<l>Ye nations are returned to freedom only now.</l>
<l>She doth your hands endow</l>
<l>With virtue against this passion suicidal</l>
<l>Wherein my poor illustrious Germany</l>
<l>Gives herself still to Manhood's Counterfeit.</l>
<l rend="indent">(Not as Psyche, deceived</l>
<l>Far otherwise, to her undoing,</l>
<l>Suspected of infamy her glorious Lover</l>
<l>And put the god to flight,</l>
<l>This hath fondly believed</l>
<l>The subtle serpent's wooing,</l>


<pb n="THE EXILE  57"/>

<l>She hath not lifted up the glittering cover</l>
<l>Nor guessed her shameful plight.)</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Tyrannous lies on her still</l>
<l>The haunted night</l>
<l>Wound all about a will</l>
<l>That cannot but obey:</l>

<l>Till ye shall shock her wide-eyed to the day</l>
<l>Of True Power, and the glory that it is</l>
<l>Already in the awakened air:</l>
<l>Cheat Hell,</l>

<l>Shatter the dream she dreams and shiver</l>
<l>The abominable spell</l>
<l>As kindliness could never!</l>

<l>Then shall she see how graciously beyond</l>
<l>The hard horizon edge</l>
<l>Apollo lifteth up his shining wand:</l>
<l>Then shall she hear the stellar mysteries.</l>
<l>Mute to her all night long,</l>
<l>Make answer in your voices and respond</l>
<l>At the sign of a new day:</l>
<l>Then shall she know the august</l>
<l>High privilege</l>
<l>Of Very Power</l>
<l>That is divinely strong,</l>
<l>For like the sun in his uprising,</l>
<l>He cannot help but must</l>


<pb n="THE EXILE  58"/>

<l>Evoke with magic ray</l>
<l>The myriadicity of joy, surprising</l>
<l>Out of each indistinguishable clod of clay</l>
<l>A different flower:</l>
<l>She too, awake, shall say</l>
<l>"I can no more contend against this power."</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Ye shall shock her wide-eyed,</l>
<l>Because, awakened from your own so-heavy dreams of pride,</l>
<l>Already in yourselves</l>
<l>Ye begin to know the quick thrill</l>
<l>That is like the little feet of elves</l>
<l>Merry in a hill:</l>
<l>Already the numb, the cold</l>
<l>Separate molecules of your earth</l>
<l>Have begun stirring toward the summer, and grown bold</l>
<l>With February mirth</l>
<l>To conspire together and loose the hold</l>
<l>Of separation: ye commence</l>
<l>Telling, among the astonished rocks and roots</l>
<l>With eager, brave inconsequence.</l>
<l>Of the April shoots</l>
<l>That are to issue thence.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Among you is beginning</l>
<l>Another year, another age!</l>
<l>And she,--</l>


<pb n="THE EXILE  59"/>

<l>Her false fond dream irrevocably fled,</l>
<l>The Furies she invited having spent their rage</l>
<l>And sunk exhausted on their leagues of dead--</l>
<l>She shall awake, but first to see</l>
<l>In the blank dawning of disaster,</l>
<l>Her cannon grinning</l>
<l>Upon her, with delight insane</l>
<l>Of that first crime, preluding vaster,</l>
<l>Wherein, betraying a little people's trust</l>
<l>By the mere sacrilege of Power,</l>
<l>She trod its valour for an hour</l>
<l>Into the nameless dust,</l>
<l>And branded in her brain</l>
<l>For all eternity</l>
<l>BELGIUM--challenge forever</l>
<l>To whoso would endeavour</l>
<l>Henceforward to seduce</l>
<l>Her spirit: there, blazing behind her eyes,</l>
<l>With inarticulable agonies</l>
<l>Fiery to wither and annihilate</l>
<l>Any least creeping shadow of thought</l>
<l>Ere it can whisper an excuse</l>
<l>That might abate</l>
<l>The horror of her soul</l>
<l>For this, unspeakable, that she hath wrought.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O, presently across this trampled slough</l>
<l>Of bloody hours,</l>

<l>59</l>



<pb n="THE EXILE  60"/>

<l>Will lie the reconciling light,</l>
<l>And grass and gracious meadow flowers</l>
<l>Will cover it from sight:</l>
<l>To her too, will return the blessed days</l>
<l>Of vision: Life's amaze</l>
<l>Will kindle in that brow,</l>
<l>And deep within that tortured brain</l>
<l>There will well-up anew the healing spring</l>
<l>Of music, for whose mighty murmuring</l>
<l>The heart o' the earth is fain.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Presently!--O but first,</l>
<l>(There is no cure else for this obscene possession)</l>
<l>Down must she go under defeat</l>
<l>And fling her boasting down.</l>
<l>Either herself must perish</l>
<l>With her deceit,</l>
<l>Or she shall cease to cherish</l>
<l>This shadowy Thing accurst</l>
<l>This Hell-begotten Hope,</l>
<l>That she crowned with the high crown</l>
<l>Of her pride.</l>
<l>On no side</l>
<l>Evasion: no new scope</l>
<l>Left it: but blank surrender and abject confession. . .</l>

<l>60</l>



<pb n="THE EXILE  61"/>

<l rend="indent">Then with the end of strife</l>
<l>Comes knowledge of her need--</l>
<l>To repent: to take the oath</l>
<l>To Liberty: to plead</l>
<l>--If such a thing might be--</l>
<l>That, after final rout,</l>
<l>With all the battle won.</l>
<l>Truth should lay by now sword for surgeon's knife:</l>
<l>Discover in his hiding, and pluck out</l>
<l>Of his hold in the quick of the brain</l>
<l>That greedy, that malignant growth</l>
<l>Which like a heaven-obscuring tree</l>
<l>Shadowed her days, and shut her from the Sun</l>
<l>That shining upon all the lands shone upon hers in vain.</l></lg></div>

<l>61</l>

</q></div>



<pb n="Siegesallee Fantasia  62"/>

<div id="binns007" type="poem" n="7">
<p><hi rend="italic">The Avenue of Hohenzollerns near Berlin.
Enter, in full fig, his scabbard dragging at
his heels, the KAISER, talking to himself:</hi></p>

<q><l>I'LD like to pack these ancestors of mine</l>
<l>To K&#x00F6;nigsberg or somewhere over-Rhine</l>
<l>Where they could not keep watch upon me!</l>
<l>How,</l>
<l>With them about me, can I face the now</l>
<l>Obvious fact I need not specify?</l>
<l>Old William with his grandpaternal look</l>
<l>Seems always to be calling me to book:--</l>
<l>Bismarck made fun of him: why cannot I?</l>
<l>And these huge Fredericks in a double row,</l>
<l>Electors, kings and what-nots: I could go</l>
<l>Crazy, seeing them stand, week after week</l>
<l>Glaring at me ! I've got a mind to tweak</l>
<l>That Frederick-William's beard, and make him speak,</l>
<l>Pompous old marble idiot!   If they'ld only</l>
<l>Say what they mean, I shouldn't feel so lonely</l>
<l>Among them.--But nobody ever said</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">That</hi> to me.--Well, he would have lost his head</l>
<l>For his fool's trouble!--But suppose, suppose</l>

<l>62</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  63"/>

<l>Someone   had   spoken   truth   to   me!     Who knows--?</l>
<l>I <hi rend="italic">might</hi> have listened.   One in whose aspect</l>
<l>My Prussian-eagle eye could not detect</l>
<l>Any self-interest or any fear.</l>
<l>For once I should have relished not to hear</l>
<l>My All-highness spoken of.    If, let us say</l>
<l>Some <sic>Roos&#x00E9;velt</sic>, fresh from America</l>
<l>Had flouted all my favourites, confronted</l>
<l>Flattery with stark fact: relentless, hunted</l>
<l>Down the deception that we practise, under</l>
<l>My very eyes; with lightning to my thunder</l>
<l>Had answered like a good Republican:</l>
<l>Had made me wrestle with him, man to man,</l>
<l>Bound only by the hard rules of the Ring--</l>
<l>And he the better man because no king.</l>
<l>Would I have taken a drubbing from him?</l>
<l rend="indent">Well</l>
<l>That is a thing I'll argue out in Hell</l>
<l>When we make nights of it around the blaze</l>
<l>To keep away the memory of these days.</l>
<l rend="indent">I've had twenty-eight years of Kaisering</l>
<l>And, good God, it's enough!   But how to fling</l>
<l>The bauble from me with these looking on!</l>
<l>My spirit might be an automaton</l>
<l>For all they care, and not like Alexander's</l>
<l>Hungry for worlds to conquer, that I can't,</l>
<l>Since first I made a mess of it in Flanders.</l>

<l>63</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  64"/>

<l>The thing is plain. Since other worlds I want</l>
<l>I'll have to look for them where I can find them.</l>
<l>The screens of death are solid.  But behind them</l>
<l>There must be what I am in search of--</l>
<l rend="indent">Change,</l>
<l>And room for my ambition's farthest range!.</l>
<l>(<hi rend="italic">He glances impatiently at his wrist watch</hi>)</l>
<l>Now Where's Our Old Ally? The fellow's late,</l>
<l>Confound him!  But here comes old honest pate.</l>

<p><hi rend="italic">Enter old</hi> MICHAEL,<hi rend="italic"> a gardener with harrow
and besom. He is dressed in a tasseled cap,
leather jacket, and knee-breeches. Seeing
the Kaiser, he salutes with military gesture.</hi></p>

<p>KAISER (<hi rend="italic">benevolent to an ancient retainer</hi>).</p>
<p>Good morning to you, Michael.</p>
<p><l>MICHAEL (shaking his head).   It's a sad</l>
<l> Dark morning. Master, as we ever had.</l>
<l> Beg pardon. It is better where you be</l>
<l> Up yonder, but it's bad for such as we.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.   I am surprised, old friend, to hear you grumble.</l>
<l>Whatever grief may fall upon the humble</l>

<l>64</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  65"/>

<l>Remember heavier falls on Us:   We bear</l>
<l>The burden of the Empire.   None may share</l>
<l>What We must carry.</l></p>

<p><l>MICH.               Hearken now, All-Highest!</l>
<l>When you go reckoning up the chaps you've got</l>
<l>I'm "old man Michael," ain't I?    Toughest, dryest,</l>
<l>Stubbornest, old curmudgeon of the lot?</l></p>
<p><l>KAI.    What's in your head this morning, out with it.</l></p>
<p><l>MICH.   I've been a soldier and I've done my bit:</l>
<l>Sergeant I was under the old king here;</l>
<l>And  "our  Fritz,"  him, your  father.     It's  a queer </l>
<l>Thing that I'm telling you, but it's a true:</l>
<l>Soldiering's done with.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.                       Long ago, for you!     . .</l></p>

<p><l>MICH.    It isn't that way you can save the folk:</l>
<l>And it needs saving, for our hearts are broke,</l>
<l>So that we can't so much as go to church.</l>
<l>So, Master, if you leave us in the lurch,</l>
<l>As you might say, we're perished.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.                                          When did we</l>

<l>Hohenzollerns, desert our peasantry</l>
<l>Of the Mark?   Since five full centuries ago</l>

<l>65</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  66"/>

<l>Led by the voice that we have come to know</l>
<l>For God's own Word within us, Frederick first</l>
<l>Left his rich lands to redeem one accurst,</l>
<l>Converting its mere sand into a rock</l>
<l>Of bronze against which all the nations shock</l>
<l>Their enviousness in vain.   This miracle</l>
<l>To God's praise we have wrought: unto His</l>
<l>Will</l>
<l>We've shaped the stubborn metal of this folk,</l>
<l>Till in our hands it is a living sword:</l>
<l>And now the Mark toils in the easy yoke</l>
<l>Of a divinely led and loving Lord.</l></p>

<p><l>MICH.     That's   just   where   you   mistake,</l>
<l>Master.   This people</l>
<l>Is a lost people.   Each young man's a cripple</l>
<l>That's not a corpse.    But there's worse still than that,</l>
<l>For each new child they get's a devil's brat</l>
<l>Marked for damnation.    People of the Mark,</l>
<l>Ay,  of the  Devil's  Mark--that's us!--And hark,</l>
<l>Master, there's nary good that we can do</l>
<l>Ourselves, there's only one can save us . . .you.</l>
<l>Not by the sword, but yet the sword's a sign</l>
<l>Grasped by the blade, as often I've held mine</l>
<l>And seen it was a Cross, and wondered when</l>
<l>There would be found some Holy One again</l>

<l>66</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  67"/>

<l>To hang there and redeem us with his passion.</l></p>
<p><l>KAI. (<hi rend="italic">severely</hi>).    Old man, you should not rant in heathen fashion</l>
<l>Of what you do not understand.   The price</l>
<l>Of our salvation is not asked for twice.</l>
<l>God paid it once for all.    Each German man,</l>
<l>Woman and child He bought out of the ban</l>
<l>That lies upon the world because of sin.</l>
<l>Are you a Brandenburger and begin</l>
<l>Speaking to us of a lost people?   We</l>
<l>Hold the salvation of our Germany</l>
<l>Secure within our care: to doubt of it</l>
<l>Is the sure symptom of a crazy wit.</l></p>

<p><l>MICH.   Ay, Master, you're our pledge, and</l>
<l>God be praised</l>
<l>For that!     But my old wife  at home she's crazed;</l>
<l>Sits in the chimney-corner all a-dodder</l>
<l>Muttering "Give me again my cannon-fodder"</l>
<l>(Her twenty grandsons that she doted on)</l>
<l>And sits and curses God.   To look upon</l>
<l>You'd say she was a saint.   I gets me gone</l>
<l>Out of my little mad-house, every day</l>
<l>Comes here and works among my kings.    It's they</l>
<l>As comfort me.   Wonderful thoughts do keep</l>
<l>A-running through my noddle while I sweep</l>
<l>The leaves up that are always falling down:</l>

<l>67</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  68"/>

<l>Strange high thoughts that belong under a crown</l>
<l>And not a <hi rend="italic">zipfelhaube!</hi>    Mark my word,</l>
<l>Master.   The whisperings I have overheard</l>
<l>Were  meant  for  you,  but  as  you  were  not near</l>
<l>They said "This is a good old harmless fool</l>
<l>As never saw the insides of a school,</l>
<l>If we can only make old Michael hear</l>
<l>He'll take our message to the Emperor."</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.   We cannot listen to you any more.</l>
<l>Go now, get to your sweeping-------</l></p>

<p><l>MICH.  (<hi rend="italic">sweeping</hi>)                 What they said</l>
<l>Day in, day out, rings in old Michael's head:</l>
<q><l><hi rend="italic">"Tell him: the soldier's day is done,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Another better day's begun</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">With a new glory in it!</hi>"</l></q></p>

<p><l>KAI.   Go further from us there!--But, stay a minute,</l>
<l>What's this about new glory?</l>
<l>MICH.(<hi rend="italic">as before</hi>)        And they said--</l>
<l>Day in, day out, it runs in Michael's head--</l>
<l>"<hi rend="italic">Tell him: there shines a glory on</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">The cross that is not on the crown,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Would he reach up and win it,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Tell him: the world would now repent</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">And live again the life it's meant</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">To live, would he begin it."</hi></l></p>

<l>68</l>


<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  69"/>

<p>[OUR OLD ALLY, <hi rend="italic">who has been sitting</hi> perdu
<hi rend="italic">behind the statue of the Emperor William,
here  makes  himself seen and catches the</hi> KAISER'S <hi rend="italic">eye,  who promptly dismisses</hi> Michael.]</p>

<p><l>OUR OLD ALLY (<hi rend="italic">looking curiously like Dr.Dryander, advances from amid the dead Hohenzollerns</hi>)     Our scourge!   Our Attila!--</l></p>
<p><l>KAI. (<hi rend="italic">saluting</hi>).   Our Old Ally!</l></p>
<p><l>O.O.A. Whenever you're in trouble We are by.</l></p>
<p><l>KAI.   We sought You on this Path of Victory</l></p>
<p><l>In the august company that is fitting . . .</l></p>
<p><l>O.O.A. (<hi rend="italic">with an inclusive gesture</hi>). For Us.</l></p>
<p><l>KAI.   Amid our sovereign Family</l>
<l>We sought you.</l></p>
<p><l>O.O.A.       We were waiting for you, sitting</l>
<l>Beside your grandfather the Emperor</l>
<l>And our first William, our good simple friend.</l>
<l>We both have many things to thank him for.</l></p>
<p><l>KAI. (<hi rend="italic">impatiently</hi>)     Yes, yes! but We have little time to spend</l>
<l>And weightiest matters . . .</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.        Upon us depend</l>

<l>Whenever care weighs heavy on your shoulders.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.   Spare us your rhetoric!--</l></p>

<l>69</l>

<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  70"/>

<p><l>O.O.A. (<hi rend="italic">admiringly</hi>).   You're more imperious</l>
<l>Each  time   we   meet.     What   an   impatience smoulders</l>
<l>Within those royal orbits: something serious</l>
<l>Must have befallen.    Have We somewhere hurt</l>
<l>Your delicate majesty with zeal mistaken?</l>
<l>To each his manners!   We too, can be curt.--</l>
<l>The pledge we  made each other stands unshaken :</l>
<l>Still We supply the Power that still you want.</l></p>

<p><l>Kai.   This power of yours that was so loud a vaunt</l>
<l>We have tried and found it insufficient for</l>
<l>The task we have begun.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.                           You can have more,</l>
<l>There still is plenty: it calls out for using.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.   You are pleased to jest!</l></p>
<p><l>O.O.A.                You too, become amusing!</l></p>
<p><l>KAI.    What good to Us is power of the wrong kind?</l></p>
<p><l>O.O.A.   Ah, yes, we know the tool's always the wrong one</l>
<l>Of a Monday morning!--Presently you'll find</l>
<l>It's still the German Sword, the trusty, strong one,</l>
<l>That rattles so divinely !</l></p>

<l>70</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  71"/>

<p><l>KAI.                                    Even Our Sword</l>
<l>Has failed to make this hand of ours adored.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.    It seems our power is the wrong kind of power</l>
<l>Because it is unkind!   So you've turned Giaour</l>
<l>From the True Faith!</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.                  You mock me in your beard!</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.   Indeed, no!--</l></p>

<p><l>KAI. (<hi rend="italic">expanding</hi>). I am sick of being feared,</l>
<l>I am tired of all this avenue of kings:</l>
<l>Weary of pulling all the silly strings</l>
<l>Of this great puppet-show!   O I am done</l>
<l>With navies and with places in the sun.</l>
<l>I have had all too much of power, too much</l>
<l>Of Germany.  I swear I loathe the touch</l>
<l>Even of my sword, and to tell truth, I'ld die</l>
<l>Rather than go on being your Ally</l>
<l>Another day.   I have had Michael here--</l>
<l>Not    the    Archangel,    my    plain    German</l>
<l>Michael,--</l>
<l>We've talked together, and it's all come clear.</l>
<l>I have been living in another cycle</l>
<l>Of the world--think of it!--and an off-cast one!</l>
<l>When here's a new, beginning:--O a vast one</l>
<l>Beyond those tales you entertained me with.</l>
<l>Already I see my old self as a myth</l>
<l>Of the forgotten days of Grail and Joust !</l>

<l>71</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  72"/>

<l>Farewell!    I go to greet the new!</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A. (<hi rend="italic">aside</hi>)                       Faust! Faust!</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.  (<hi rend="italic">returning</hi>)     But I forgot: there are things to be arranged!</l>
<l>In this to-morrow's world Our part is changed.</l>
<l>We shall put by the sword and give release</l>
<l>To  our armed host,  and become  Prince  of</l>
<l>Peace.</l>
<l>We feel the War-lord grows anachronistic.</l>
<l>At bottom We have always been a mystic.</l>
<l>We foreknew when We stood on Olivet</l>
<l>And wept over Jerusalem, that yet</l>
<l>We too, should suffer: We too, should redeem</l>
<l>The erring nations from the fond false dream</l>
<l>Wherein they dwell: in Us, also, the power</l>
<l>Of Gospel-love should find its passion-flower:</l>
<l>We should be lifted up and all would see</l>
<l>Our body broken for Humanity.</l>
<l>For this We claim your help.    To you, We feel</l>
<l>How mightily our purpose must appeal.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A. (<hi rend="italic">hesitating</hi>)     A new part for a Hohenzollern, eh!</l>
<l>I wonder what the Family will say.</l>
<l>And what henceforth you'll do with your right hand</l>
<l>When no hilt's handy to it?--But command!</l>
<l>We will fulfil your orders as of old.</l></p>

<l>72</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  73"/>

<p><l>KAI.   The change is good to us because it's bold.</l>
<l>Half-measures do not catch the public eye.</l>
<l>Once it is understood that We shall die</l>
<l>A willing sacrifice for all men's good . . .</l>
<l>Do you not see, <hi rend="italic">when it is understood</hi>/</l>
<l>We shall have superadded to the story</l>
<l>Of our tremendous House another glory</l>
<l>Such as will swallow up the rest and hold</l>
<l>The imagination of the world for ever.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.    We will so match your deed with our endeavour</l>
<l>No one shall tell the gilding from the gold.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.    No word of yours to-day but is discordant</l>
<l>With our high mood!   Your wit that once was mordant</l>
<l>Is now a clown's.   Can no occasion oust</l>
<l>This ribald habit?</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.               My good worthy Faust!</l>
<l>To-day you really seem to have grown blind,</l>
<l>Hypnotised not to see what lies behind</l>
<l>This cardboard Siegesallee puppet-show</l>
<l>Wherein you play the Kaiser!--But you know</l>
<l>Me very well--the spirit that affirms</l>
<l>The proper half of truth, which is far better</l>
<l>Than like a pedant, to spell every letter</l>
<l>Where some of them, being unfamiliar terms,</l>

<l>73</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA"/>

<l>Inevitably raise misunderstanding!</l>
<l>The whole of truth is like a flight of stairs</l>
<l>That's far too slow to climb: at unawares</l>
<l>I leap the people up, landing by landing!</l>
<l>My better part of truth is like a lift,</l>
<l>It gets them to the top without the trouble:</l>
<l>Half though it be, it is worth more than double</l>
<l>To any ruler, taken as a gift.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI. (<hi rend="italic">doubtfully</hi>)             A gift?</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.   Oh, as for that, I have my wages,</l>
<l>Though on my tongue the old-fashioned word sound odd.</l>
<l>A Hohenzollern now for several ages</l>
<l>I've valeted as his familiar god.</l>
<l>(What other house can boast a deity</l>
<l>As practical as yours, Vulcan or Venus</l>
<l>Or Mars?)     It's simply understood between us,</l>
<l>The royal Us signifies you and me.</l>
<l>Between us only, but for all the rest</l>
<l>My part, as you may say, is a dead letter.</l>
<l>Acknowledged, but as good as unexpressed.</l>
<l>For here, as always, the half-truth's the better.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.    Come now, to work!    Your words are all too plenty.</l></p>
<p><l>O.O.A.    With pleasure: shall I call up four and twenty</l>

<l>74</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  75"/>

<l>Brand-new, fully munitioned, army corps,</l>
<l>And let old Hindenburg wind up the war?</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.   No, that is not the way the war shall cease.</l>
<l>We've had enough of playing Goth and Vandal:</l>
<l>Now We'll be recognised as Prince of Peace.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.   You really think the game is worth the candle?</l>
<l>Your mind is set on it?</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.                         Our mind is set</l>
<l>On this new title that We have not yet.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.    We've but to whistle Peace and she'll arrive</l>
<l>In her tremendous car.   A Juggernaut</l>
<l>Over obsequious nations you shall drive,</l>
<l>Vishnu's avatar!</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.               You mistake our thought.</l>
<l>We will be lifted up that We may draw</l>
<l>The eyes of all men to Ourself with awe</l>
<l>Of this that never Hohenzollern did</l>
<l>Before Us.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.   Your great deed shall not be hid !</l>
<l>We'll have it filmed for the ages yet to be</l>
<l>When all the universe is Germany.</l>
<l>But now before we call her--in my ear,</l>
<l>Whisper--what is it you have grown to fear</l>
<l>More than the last of terrors, for I think</l>

<l>75</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  76"/>

<l>You  know  the  kind  of  cup  you'll  have  to drink--</l>
<l>Unless of course the whole thing is a bluff.</l></p>
<p><l>KAI.   We Germans fear God only..</l></p>
<p><l>O.O.A.                                           O enough</l>

<l>Of that!   We Germans understand each other!</l>
<l>We're not a Bonn <hi rend="italic">festkommers</hi>, but a brother</l>
<l>Orator.    Come now.    What is this you dread</l>
<l>So much you'd rather be a ghost instead</l>
<l>And lodge with me for ever?</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.                                   As for you</l>
<l>We have no terror of what you can do.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.   Not if I turned old Michael's heart away.</l></p>
<p><l>KAI. (<hi rend="italic">startled, but recovering himself</hi>)   You daren't do that, for then he'd cease to pay</l>
<l>Honour as well to you.   You can afford</l>
<l>As ill as I not to be Michael's lord.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.    There's no denying what you hint is true,</l>
<l>Though I have other subjects--more than you.</l>
<l>However, I'll concede It.   It was partly</l>
<l>Because it's mine I guessed your dread so smartly.</l>
<l>What you dread is to lose the simple thing</l>
<l>Without which nobody could be a king.</l>
<l>And what I dread--a little less, maybe--</l>
<l>Is to cease being feared in Germany.</l>

<l>76</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  77"/>

<l>An uncrowned king and an ungodded devil</l>
<l>Sink at a single stroke below the level</l>
<l>Of consciousness: and that we cannot.    No,</l>
<l>We must hold on together even though</l>
<l>The price be the uncomfortable Cross</l>
<l>(For you!)--It <hi rend="italic">will</hi> secure us both from loss.</l>
<l>You're positive of that?    (Kai. <hi rend="italic">nods</hi>.)    Well,let us trust</l>
<l>The actuaries are right.</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.                          It will.   It must.</l>

<l>There is no other way for Us at all.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.    (<hi rend="italic">considering</hi>)       A Hohenzollern couldn't learn to crawl</l>
<l>As a poor devil might ?</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.                        Certainly not.</l>
<l>We'll set it here upon this very spot.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.   Then, hang it all!--the crosses must be got.</l></p>
<p><l>KAI.   Crosses?   There is but one: and that shall stand</l>
<l>Heaven high.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A. But you will have on either hand . . .</l></p>
<p><l>KAI.    Nor Pope nor Sultan shall with Us divide</l>
<l>This signal glory.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.             No, but malefactors. . . .</l></p>

<p><l>KAI.    Sirrah! upon this stage there are no actors</l>

<l>77</l>



<pb n="SIEGESALLEE FANTASIA  78"/>

<l>But the All-highest.</l></p>

<p><l>O.O.A.                We'll not be denied!    (<hi rend="italic">He produces a scroll with the inscription:</hi></l>
<l>"It was to save Our people that We died!"</l></p></q></div>


<l>78</l>



<pb n="The Blacksmith  79"/>

<div id="binns008" type="poem" n="8">

<lg type="stanza">
<l>WHAT have you in your stithy, Thor,</l>
<l>That now you make your bellows roar</l>
<l>So terribly within?</l>
<l>What is there hidden in the heat</l>
<l>That now you snatch it forth and beat</l>
<l>With such huge din ?</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He shouted--for he would not cease</l>
<l>Hammering--"What I make is peace !</l>
<l rend="indent">Amid this clang of war</l>
<l>I shape to't--I who have the skill--</l>
<l>The stubborn steel of all men's will."</l>
<l>--So I heard Thor.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The metal rhymed the word he spoke</l>
<l>As though each awful hammer-stroke</l>
<l>Gave freedom and release:</l>
<l>Under the blacksmithing of Thor</l>
<l>Anvil and steel together swore</l>
<l rend="indent">World oath of peace.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He took me also, and his blast</l>
<l>Roared, as through all my being passed</l>
<l rend="indent">The permeating heat:</l>
<l>Within the fury of the flame</l>
<l>I, that had stood apart, became</l>
<l rend="indent">For forging meet.</l>

<l>79</l>



<pb n="THE BLACKSMITH  80"/>

<l>Snatched forth and on the anvil laid,</l>
<l>With sudden heavy strokes he played</l>
<l rend="indent">On me his music well:</l>
<l>"Death! Death! Death!" was the hammer clang</l>
<l>And "Faith! Faith! Faith!" the answer rang</l>
<l rend="indent">Clear as a bell.</l></lg></div>





<l>80</l>



<pb n="81"/>

<div id="binns009" type="poem" n="9">

<head rend="center">Decision</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>TO-DAY'S the end.</l>
<l>There is no more to-morrow.</l>
<l>Now I pay: I cannot borrow</l>
<l>Of a friend.</l>
<l>I must shoulder all my sorrow</l>
<l>To-day, and to the utmost end</l>
<l>What I love defend.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>At last, to-day,</l>
<l>It is not any longer</l>
<l>"<hi rend="italic">You</hi> must go, for you are younger:</l>
<l>I can stay."</l>
<l>I have heard the Voice that's stronger</l>
<l>Than the other voices say</l>
<l>"It's your turn, to-day."</l></lg></div>





<l>81</l>

<pb n="82"/>

<div id="binns010" type="poem" n="10">
<head>The Peacemaker--August,<lb/>
<rend type="center"> 1914</rend></head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>THE nightmare that was once Napoleonism</l>
<l>Stalks now the harvest-ready, unharvested</l>
<l>Fields at high noon, to blast them with his red</l>
<l>Laughter, loosing a final cataclysm.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>We boasted him a dream, while he was whetting</l>
<l>His belly's hunger, for he never ceased</l>
<l>Behind the years to gloat on the fair feast</l>
<l>Preparing--all the births of our begetting!</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Is there no spear with which to slay this Slayer</l>
<l>Of nations, this Dragon of massacre, this</l>
<l>Viceroy on earth of the Monarch of the Abyss?</l>
<l>Is there no Champion against Life's Betrayer?</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>There is a hand that yet shall slay the slaughter,</l>
<l>A brand that yet shall smite to the death Love's</l>
<l rend="inline">Cheat!</l>
<l>Ringing across the world the hills repeat</l>
<l>Liberty's challenge, that the mountains taught her.</l>

<l>82</l>



<pb n="THE PEACEMAKER, AUGUST, 1914  83"/>

<l>And she shall not withhold her hand for sorrow,</l>
<l>Or pity, or prudence that counts up the cost:</l>
<l>Either the day is Freedom's, or we have lost</l>
<l>Peace, and the Spectre walks again to-morrow.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>She shall make peace, but never with oppression:</l>
<l>Hallowed her pitiless sword that it may clean</l>
<l>The whole earth utterly of the obscene</l>
<l>Presence that holds the folk in his possession.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O, she shall make an end of war for ever:</l>
<l>Victress,  she   shall  make  peace,   a   radiant-browed</l>
<l>Splendour of fear-defiant Faith, endowed</l>
<l>With all the heart of passionate endeavour.</l></lg></div>


<l>83</l>

<pb n="84"/>


<div id="binns011" type="poem" n="11">
<head rend="center">A Non-Combatant</head>
<div id="binns118" type="section" n="1">
<head rend="center">I</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>I  SAW my neighbour going gay</l>
<l>To France as for a holiday:</l>
<l>Caught out of the cursing battle</l>
<l>Many a burst of boyish prattle:</l>
<l>Heard how many a devilish stroke</l>
<l>Was taken, laughing, for a joke:</l>
<l>Knew the horror, and the sin</l>
<l>In the horror glorying,</l>
<l>Boasting they could make a clod</l>
<l>Of any image of our God,</l>
<l>Boasting they could dim and dull</l>
<l>Love with hatred, and annul</l>
<l>Whatsoe'er is beautiful:</l>
<l>Boasting all the hideous boasts</l>
<l>That glut the ugly battle-ghosts . . .</l>
<l>Clear, among the starry rafters</l>
<l>Of the world, heard angel laughters</l>
<l>Answer with melodious shout</l>
<l>And put the ugly ghosts to rout--</l>
<l>Even while the dead lads lay</l>
<l>In their dreadful disarray,</l>
<l>Even while their women stood</l>
<l>Frozen in their motherhood.</l>



<pb n="A NON-COMBATANT 85"/>

<l>I heard the voice of Liberty--</l>
<l>That was and is and is to be</l>
<l>From first to finish of our span</l>
<l>Son of God and Son of Man--</l>
<l>Cry that splendid word of Death</l>
<l>(That we say beneath our breath)</l>
<l>In its whole divine intent;</l>
<l>And I knew the joy it meant,</l>
<l>Shared the joy that only they</l>
<l>Partake who give themselves away</l>
<l>To the freedom of the world.</l>
<l>I saw the mystic flag unfurled</l>
<l>Of ever-new defiance, flung</l>
<l>To the old world by the young:</l>
<l>Saw that flag--whose sunrise-red</l>
<l>Dissipates despair and dread--</l>
<l>Repay all the dead are giving</l>
<l>With its joy of mightier living:</l>
<l>For I heard the dying cry,</l>
<l>"Freedom! You shall never die !"</l>
<l>Saw their dying as the birth</l>
<l>Of that overmastering mirth</l>
<l>At whose face the devils quail</l>
<l>For their terrors naught avail.</l></lg>
</div>

<div id="binn119" type="section" n="2">
<head rend="center">2</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>I saw soldiers going gay</l>
<l>Over the hills and far away:</l>

<l>85</l>



<pb n="A NON-COMBATANT  86"/>

<l>And I followed through the fern</l>
<l>Sighing, "They will not return!</l>
<l>To the board and to the bed</l>
<l>Grief and Hate will come instead.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The November sun was pale,</l>
<l>But the tall defiant trees</l>
<l>Shook their tops against the gale,</l>
<l>Spurning such impieties:</l>
<l>And within my soul I knew</l>
<l>My fear and sadness were untrue</l>
<l>To something in myself that would</l>
<l>Give my body to make good</l>
<l>My spirit's boasting: fain would give</l>
<l>All that makes me glad to live</l>
<l>For a weapon or a shield</l>
<l>In Freedom's hand, that He may yield</l>
<l>No inch to Tyranny, or 'bate</l>
<l>Any joy of His for Fate.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I believed that I would dare</l>
<l>Naked to confront Despair,</l>
<l>Having given all I might:</l>
<l>Would go dwell in the dark night,</l>
<l>Of my light bereft: defy</l>
<l>Loneliness, if only I</l>
<l>Could feel I had held nothing back</l>
<l>From Freedom in His hour of lack.</l>

<l>86</l>



<pb n="A NON-COMBATANT  87"/>

<l>Evermore I would rejoice</l>
<l>That I had recognised the Voice</l>
<l>Divine, and against any odds</l>
<l>Held to Him against the gods</l>
<l>And princes of this world,</l>
<l>Who have no stomach for the high</l>
<l>Mirth of His flag unfurled</l>
<l>Upon the sky.</l></lg></div>

<div id="binns120" type="section" n="3">
<head rend="center">3</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>When myself I utterly</l>
<l>Give to Freedom, I can be</l>
<l>The hateless weapon in His hand--</l>
<l>Let Him bid me, let me hear</l>
<l>The authentic voice within my ear</l>
<l>That I know for His command.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I have seen the eyes of Him</l>
<l>Who is Freedom: they are dim</l>
<l>With no doubting: naught of weakness</l>
<l>Dulls their gaze of piercing meekness;</l>
<l>It is brighter than the sun</l>
<l>That I cannot look upon.</l>
<l>I have felt His living breath</l>
<l>Challenge in me doubt and death:</l>
<l>Who am I that I should bear</l>
<l>Only to speak gentle and fair?</l>

<l>87</l>



<pb n="A NON-COMBATANT 88"/>

<l>I must be the battle-cry</l>
<l>Of Freedom, or become a lie</l>
<l>On His lips, when they would speak</l>
<l>Mortal Truth, though they be meek.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>There is not, nor ever shall</l>
<l>Be any peace on Earth till all</l>
<l>Life's great truth be spoken out:</l>
<l>Never while we fear to flout</l>
<l>Half-truth; while we dare not be</l>
<l>Hated of complacency:</l>
<l>Never till we give our whole</l>
<l>Being--body, mind, and soul--</l>
<l>To Freedom, and stand forth among</l>
<l>Them who battle against the strong</l>
<l>Proud powers that put Him in the wrong.</l></lg></div></div>





<l>88</l>



<pb n="89"/>

<div id="binns012" type="poem" n="12">

<head rend="center">A Schoolmaster in Picardy</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>MOONLESS, republican, an April night</l>
<l>That the south-west wind burnishes until</l>
<l>Thick-set, the stars blaze in it with the world's</l>
<l>Purposeful thought, which Zoroaster learned</l>
<l>And Abraham was wise in.   This, entrenched</l>
<l>In Picardy, he spells and understands.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Over him circle the Great Seven, sign</l>
<l>Of Labour and Promise.   Through a luminous field</l>
<l>Of stars unspelled,  dips the Sun's pathway; now</l>
<l>It leaves the Lion and the King behind</l>
<l>To enter on Astraea's realm of promise.</l>
<l>Justice, the Virgin, rules here: in her lap</l>
<l>Sits the world's hope: and shine in either hand</l>
<l>The Scales of Judgment and the Spear that is</l>
<l>A golden spear of corn, a Spike of Peace.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>A peasant and a village schoolmaster,</l>
<l>Patiently he had tuned his little world</l>
<l>Scholar by scholar, daily into accord</l>
<l>With Peace, the music that he knew within him.</l>
<l>Rumour of foes designing war against France</l>

<l>89</l>



<pb n="A SCHOOLMASTER IN PICARDY  90"/>

<l>Was bygone folly afar-off that he heard</l>
<l>Smiling amid the garden of his school.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Far-off, till on that sudden First of August,</l>
<l>France calling him with her trumpets, his spirit rang</l>
<l>Out like a trumpet answering hers. Within him</l>
<l>Sang a strange music that he heard amazed</l>
<l>And knew the old happiness was at an end.</l>
<l>He hated war, as though somewhere he had been</l>
<l>A mother, matched a body with a soul</l>
<l>And made them one together magically,</l>
<l>To know the cost and meaning of a man.</l>
<l>Peace was dearer to him than to another.</l>
<l>Gave him her heart, and like a bride demanded</l>
<l>What most he longed to give her, that she might</l>
<l>Transform his ardours into life.   But War</l>
<l>Out of that happiness he was at home in,</l>
<l>Like a pre-destined passion snatched him away.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Transplanted in the miry field of death,</l>
<l>He and the stars night-long kept company.</l>
<l>Often of her he loved War minded him:</l>
<l>Different, yet with the same divine denial</l>
<l>Of the great dreamy idols men bow down to</l>

<l>90</l>



<pb n="A SCHOOLMASTER IN PICARDY  91"/>

<l>With less than the whole passion of their being.</l>
<l>She was a sister to his lady, Peace:</l>
<l>And when her masterful accompaniment</l>
<l>Challenged the singer in him with its strange</l>
<l>Rhythms, his exulting spirit answering cried</l>
<l>New p&#x00E6;ans against it in the praise of Peace.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Through all this visionary April night</l>
<l>He sees her face in memories.   At Leipzig,</l>
<l>He knows again how verily it was she</l>
<l>Fanning the passion that swept Bonaparte</l>
<l>Back over Rhine.   At Strasburg, it was she</l>
<l>Consenting not to a conquest that denied</l>
<l>The only meaning common to the world.</l>
<l>For as, when fond peace-makers intervene</l>
<l>With "Recollect,  the man is now your husband!"</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The  white-faced  woman, answering nothing, sets</l>
<l>Her clear stern eyes aloof--again he saw</l>
<l>Alsace joined to the Stranger.   Faithful she,</l>
<l>Silent, implacable, France in her heart.</l>
<l>Fed there upon such puissant love as nation</l>
<l>Knew never, France became Joan's holy</l>
<l>France,</l>
<l>Country of Freedom. And the emperor</l>
<l>For whom she was the pledge of his dominion,</l>

<l>91</l>



<pb n="A SCHOOLMASTER IN PICARDY  92"/>

<l>Who upon her subjection had built up</l>
<l>Towery dreams, would he but look, might see</l>
<l>The real world reflected in her gaze</l>
<l>Hateless, mockingly patient of his might.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>As Alsace, weariless through the long hours--</l>
<l>The Plough driving its furrow to the zenith</l>
<l>Earthward again turning, descending slow--</l>
<l>He grapples with that false spirit who is</l>
<l>The discord among men, and cries against</l>
<l>Truth, in the name of some obedience it</l>
<l>Would tune the whole world to--and cannot while</l>
<l>Justice endure. He strives, and through the hours</l>
<l>Peace urges and upholds him, striving: Peace</l>
<l>That of all spirits is the only one</l>
<l>That can, to every soul and tribe of Man,</l>
<l>Give that to which his passionate spirit aspires--</l>
<l>For it is in her eyes.   Pitilessly</l>
<l>They demand all the irrevocable whole</l>
<l>Of worship..which long since he gave to her.</l>
<l>Fighting, he fashions what the peace-mongers</l>
<l>Had made impossible.    Dismayed they heard</l>
<l>The name of Justice, for they knew the price</l>

<l>92</l>



<pb n="A SCHOOLMASTER IN PICARDY  93"/>

<l>Was not in their white hands.   The price slips not</l>
<l>His bloody hands, nor his embattled brain</l>
<l>That being sworn-in against injustice, dares</l>
<l>Take the inane days and the nightmare nights</l>
<l>When there are no stars in the monstrous dark</l>
<l>That is too full of strange presences, bred</l>
<l>Of horror and corruption.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent 26">But to-night</l>
<l>Is one great fellowship of stars.   Already</l>
<l>Justice commences. The whole world is flung</l>
<l>Open as never yet to the indomitable</l>
<l>Creators!   Now they labour all its stuff</l>
<l>With hands nor false nor blind, with thinking hands</l>
<l>Spirit-imbued: they put themselves to it</l>
<l>And it responds to them, and it becomes</l>
<l>Human, and brings forth beauty to their touch:</l>
<l>No here-and-there fantastic joy, but all</l>
<l>A consummation and accomplishing!</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Out of the love-dream of the adolescent</l>
<l>Youth of Democracy a passion ripens,</l>
<l>No more the formless shadow of Humanity,</l>
<l>A fond vague aspiration cosmopolitan,</l>
<l>But now the emerging purpose, whole and final,</l>
<l>The Will to Justice, to begin together</l>
<l>The complete life of Man not yet attempted!</l>

<l>93</l>



<pb n="A SCHOOLMASTER IN PICARDY  94"/>

<l>Long had we dreamed, too long had dallied dreaming.</l>
<l>Almost content with hopes we had not realised--</l>
<l>Embrace of bodiless joys--our immature</l>
<l>Manhood spent for the barren behest of vain</l>
<l>Visions, worshipping them in our folly, till</l>
<l>Suddenly Death with hoarse voice shouting our names</l>
<l>We awoke to the grim guns of the adversary.</l>
<l>Only then, will against will, sprang into passionate</l>
<l>Purpose effectual, Freedom, the lad's fancy,</l>
<l>Freedom,   youth's  romance,   now   manhood's sworn</l>
<l>Oath to accomplish or to perish doing it.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>German folk, in whom as in one strong man</l>
<l>The despot's will to power is all embodied,</l>
<l>Now rebuffed, as you shock yourselves against our</l>
<l>Liberty-making will, another purpose</l>
<l>Shall you espouse! This greater, this  incredible</l>
<l>Promise, to which we are now pledged, believing it--</l>
<l>Freedom, a commonwealth built up of nations</l>
<l>Bound together in faithfulness to uphold</l>

<l>94</l>



<pb n="A SCHOOLMASTER IN PICARDY"/>

<l>Justice against dissension and oppressors</l>
<l>Sovereign over themselves and over the earth.</l>
<l>Now together, we shall achieve what long syne</l>
<l>England, France, America, each proposing</l>
<l>Severally began and accomplished not! . . .</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent">The upholding Presences depart.   The stars</l>
<l>Pale: the rhythm flags: he is wrapped in loneliness.</l>
<l>Now at its coming the drab daylight proves</l>
<l>The night's promise inane with what a world--</l>
<l>What an unroofed charnel-house of a world!</l>
<l>But up above the horror on little wings,</l>
<l>The larks, Franciscan-clad, sing canticles</l>
<l>To the sun and praise him. Leaps this peasant heart</l>
<l>With praise for the light of the sun returning:--</l>
<l>"Praise for the  earth-born spirit of Justice!</l>
<l rend="indent">Praise</l>
<l>For whoso is at home in poverty:</l>
<l>Puts wealth away: success for himself abandons</l>
<l>To be the enabling tool of that Prometheus</l>
<l>Who, Titan though he be, requires a man</l>
<l>To effect justice, without which the world</l>
<l>Fails of its hope and still remains a dream.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Carol the larks above the cannon!--Praise,</l>
<l>Praise for the justice that doth undismayed</l>

<l>95</l>



<pb n="A SCHOOLMASTER IN PICARDY"/>

<l>Its dread Augean labour in the stables</l>
<l>Of massacre.   Praise for the comrade-love</l>
<l>Of men devoted who, having forgot</l>
<l>To bargain, on the sill of battle are</l>
<l>Clear prophecies of the peace that shall come after</l>
<l>Builded upon their fear-forgetting gladness,</l>
<l>Their surety of each other and the living</l>
<l>Presence among them of Our Lady France.</l>
<l>Praise, praise for these and Thee, O sun uprising,</l>
<l>And for the day wherein we perish, praise!"</l></lg></div>

<l>96</l>



<pb n="97"/>

<div id="binns013" type="poem" n="13">
<head rend="center">THE HILL-TOP WOOD</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>UP In the hill-top wood</l>
<l rend="indent">I heard the oak-trees sing</l>
<l>As only the great oaks can</l>
<l>When the leaves are down, and they fling</l>
<l>Their arms to the utmost span,</l>
<l>And exult in their brotherhood</l>
<l>Up on the top of the hill.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O but the air was good!</l>
<l>And to feel them glorying</l>
<l>As only the great oaks can,</l>
<l>In their stubbornness and the spring</l>
<l>That is in it--as in a man--!</l>
<l>To exult in their brotherhood</l>
<l>Up on the top of the hill!</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I never thought that I could</l>
<l>Know in my flesh the thing</l>
<l>That only the great oaks can</l>
<l>When the leaves are down and they fling</l>
<l>Their arms out wide--but a man</l>
<l>Is at home in that great-oak-wood</l>
<l>Up on the top of the hill.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I climbed up among them, I stood</l>
<l>In the ranks of the trees that sing</l>

<l>97</l>



<pb n="THE HILL-TOP WOOD  98"/>

<l>As only the great oaks can,</l>
<l>All of the Wonderful Thing:</l>
<l>There, to my uttermost span,</l>
<l>I exulted in this that I could</l>
<l>Up on the top of the hill.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>This that I one time would</l>
<l>If, sometime, the hour should bring</l>
<l>Me mastery!--now I can.</l>
<l>I hold it from taking wing:</l>
<l>I hold it, more wonderful than</l>
<l>Any wonder:--the Making Good</l>
<l>Of my Dream on the top of this hill.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I tumble out all the brood</l>
<l>Of Doubt from my boughs that I swing</l>
<l>As only a great oak can!</l>
<l>I exult with my branches: I fling</l>
<l>My arms to their utmost span:</l>
<l>I have come to my brotherhood</l>
<l>Up on the top of this hill.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>You great hearts!--you that have stood</l>
<l>On this hill-top uttering,</l>
<l>As only the great oaks can,</l>
<l>Your wonder--to-day I bring</l>
<l>Another fragment of Man</l>
<l>To be of your brotherhood</l>
<l>Up on the top of the hill.</l></lg>

<l>98</l>
</div>


<pb n="99"/>

<div id="binns014" type="poem" n="14">
<head rend="center">The Quaker Women</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>FRIENDS, whom from our defence a Voice divine defends,</l>
<l>Let not the thought of us make your obeying hard:</l>
<l>Of your obedience we are the faithful friends:</l>
<l>Fear not for us: the God of love shall be our guard.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He is among us here, though hid from our espial:</l>
<l>It is of doubting Him our spirits are afraid.</l>
<l>For you we have no fear, how stark soe'er your trial,</l>
<l>Though more than flesh may carry be upon you laid.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>His call ye answer. His the inexplicable word</l>
<l>Of your refusal to put forth your manly might</l>
<l>Against His enemies.   We also, friends, have heard</l>
<l>The Voice, and share with you all the wise world's despite.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Blind as stampeded cattle that fear will not release,</l>
<l>The peoples herd together, panic on everyone:—&lt;</l>

<l>99</l>



<pb n="THE QUAKER WOMEN  100"/>

<l>O if amid the battle, we might ourselves be peace</l>
<l>And fear might fail as trampling over us they run! . . .</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>If it be ours to endure Love's uttermost: to suffer</l>
<l>The mocking might of Hatred when he breaks his chain,</l>
<l>'Tis ye shall keep secure our vision of Man's Lover</l>
<l>Redeeming mortals by the price of mortal pain.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Shall ye not, also, bearing the agony we bear,</l>
<l>With us triumphing over fear's delirium,</l>
<l>For us, even then, forswearing your strength to save us, dare</l>
<l>Still with us to endure, with us to overcome?</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Until our wedded faith marry with the creative</l>
<l>Power that through all the ages yet remains unspent,</l>
<l>And unconcerned with death, shall know itself a native</l>
<l>Of the invisible country of Love's government.</l></lg></div>


<l>1OO</l>


<pb n="101"/>


<div id="binns015" type="poem" n="15">
<head rend="center">The Stay-at-Home</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>AS a woman that is with child, my soul already fosters</l>
<l>A life conceived within me, secret as yet and sacred,</l>
<l>As though the herald, Gabriel, in a sudden-shining shaft</l>
<l>Had bidden me glory in this I nourish for men's joy.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>At the clamour of drums without or bidding of voices within</l>
<l>Can I abandon This?   Can I resume my soul?</l>
<l>Am I also free to go, one with the millions</l>
<l>Descending at Freedom's call to the camp and the yonder field,</l>
<l>Spending themselves for Her, as I fain myself would spend?</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He is not free to go who hath already gone:</l>
<l>To give himself afresh who hath already given.</l>
<l>Assigned already my place, I cannot leave it and go:</l>
<l>Mine to stay, to abide, as a woman that is with child.--</l>
<l>And I continue at home, contented, as one without</l>

<l>1O1</l>



<pb n="THE STAY-AT-HOME  102"/>

<l>Trammel, if he should run in the race, runs not but remains.</l>
<l>I see them go: my heart, going not, is one with their heart,</l>
<l>Shares in their gladness going, that now to the uttermost</l>
<l>Farthing they have responded with all that is theirs, as I</l>
<l>Also wholly respond, with all that I am endowing</l>
<l>The intangible hope within me, that is not other than theirs,</l>
<l>The unborn joy I was bidden foster and bring to a birth.</l></lg></div>





<l>102</l>



<pb n="103"/>
<titlePage id="binns304" type="half">
     <docTitle>
       <titlePart type="main">THE PRICE OF FREEDOM
       </titlePart>
     </docTitle>
   </titlePage>

<pb n="[104]"/>
<pb n="105"/>

<div id="binns016" type="play" n="16">
<head rend="center">The Price of Freedom<lb/>
A Footnote to Epipschydion</head>

<p><hi rend="italic">A large room at Pisa, 1820</hi>.SHELLEY,<hi rend="italic"> pacing
to and fro</hi>. Mary Shelley<hi rend="italic"> sewing. He
is twenty-eight, she is five years younger</hi>.
<hi rend="italic">At this time</hi> EMILIA VIVIANI<hi rend="italic"> was about
eighteen.</hi></p>

<p>SHELLEY. My spirit, my real self, once it was awakened into consciousness by your recognition, began to be aware of its need and of its power. I myself awoke to knowledge. All the argument about Truth ceased because I was face to face with Truth; or rather, the argument was changed into a way of revelation, the two parties completing for one another their partial affirmations.</p>

<p>But the great change was n desire. Desire is a seeking-together of parts into their unity.But when once the nature of that unity has been discovered, desire itself becomes different. For the whole, which is Love Himself, is henceforward awake within desire. It is now no more the blind longing of the creature after he knows not what.   For now desire calls upon the God
<l>105</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM 106"/>

within both me and the object of my longing,so worshipping Him that He manifests Himself, ruling, ordering, illuminating, till the desire is changed into delight of His presence.</p>

<p>Love is no wantonness. It is the life of the wakened spirit.</p>

<p>The rhythm of the divine life within me cannot but vibrate with that responding rhythm,of which now and again it is aware in some kindred being. Thus vibrating together, we are married into one whole, as are the notes of a music to which each note belongs.</p>

<p>This realisation of unity is an extravagant thing. It transcends the ordinary terms of speech. It is beyond the measure of the senses. When it seizes me, it seizes me with actual rapture, so that I neither know myself or what I am saying. It is the passion of a fuller incarnation. Do you not see?--It is the Something in which all that we have won together is enlarged and heightened into a fuller meaning.</p>

<p>MARY (<hi rend="italic">without looking up</hi>). So now it is this Italian!</p>

<p>SHELLEY.    Mary . . .</p>

<p>MARY.   Well! . . .</p>

<p>SHELLEY. You have frozen up my words. .</p>

<p>MARY.   I want the truth.   I can bear that so

<l>106</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM 107"/>

much better than anything else. It's the not-knowing what is true that I cannot bear. With her you are happy. When you speak of her, your whole face changes. But with me, see how constrained you are! Why do you stay? I will not keep you. For now, surely you know it, our life together is a mere lie. I cannot go on in it.   One of us must go away.</p>

<p>SHELLEY.   Harriet said that.</p>

<p>MARY.   Poor Harriet!</p>

<p>SHELLEY.   Poor Harriet!   Poor Mary!</p>

<p>MARY.   You dare to pity me! . . .</p>

<p>SHELLEY. Mary, do you remember when it was that Harriet said what you were saying?</p>

<p>MARY.   Said what? . . . Yes, I remember.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. And how you said, "poor Harriet, she's not herself"?</p>

<p>MARY. I did not understand Harriet then. I was happy.   Now I understand.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. You mean, Mary, you feel as Harriet did when she was not herself. So now because you are not yourself, you cannot understand anything at all. You have become a mis-understanding of everything in order that you may hold me back from what you do not understand.</p>

<p>MARY. Do I want to hold you back? But you--you do not know what you are doing, or

<l>107</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  108"/>

where you are going, upon the current of this river.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. So many times you have told me truth, truth that I did not know till you had told me; but this time it is not truth that you are telling.</p>

<p>MARY. I am simply saying we must separate, since, however it be for you, for me this life together is become a lie.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. No, but your going, my going, that would be the lie.</p>

<p>MARY. Give me freedom, since you claim it for yourself.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. Freedom is neither given nor taken. It is the life of a spirit that is true to itself. Now, if you go, you are not true to your utmost self.    If I go, I am but a traitor.</p>

<p>This I know about myself: I have all the weaknesses and follies of which you ever justly accused me:--(for you love and see me as I am. I have no trust in myself at all. I look to you continually for my judgment and my strength.) But yet there is something in me--it is you who have made me know it--there is something that is at last the real Shelley: the essential spirit--that neither passion nor any kind of death can dissolve: something to which I can and must entrust everything that I possess.</p>

<l>108</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  109"/>

<p>Do not make me doubt that, or you will destroy the integrity of my soul which you discovered to me and have nourished. I shall cease to be a man: I shall go back to the days before ever I loved you: before you gave me the pledge of my immortal spirit.</p>

<p>MARY. When you loved me, then I understood.    But now</p>

<p>SHELLEY. What has befallen you, that you say such a thing! As if ever now I could not love you: as if ever now you could be less to me--O God, how infinitely more!</p>

<p>MARY. A woman is either everything or nothing to a man.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. That is the falsehood of love's idolatry, which has nothing in common with our truth and freedom. If that is what you mean by love . .! But it is you yourself who deny it, Mary: there is nothing of that in you.
You freed me from that. That is poor Harriet's talk, that goes into madness.</p>

<p>MARY. I thought myself free and wise. But now I know that every woman who has ever loved is the slave of love. It is her nature. She cannot share that which is the very reason of her being.    Men are different.</p>

<p>It is the eternal tragedy of woman that she is mated with her contradiction.    The man's

<l>109</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  110"/>

need for change is unnatural, it is monstrous to the woman.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. What strange, false doctrine on your lips! You strain and wrest your words out of sheer anguish, as though indeed your time had come. What if this is indeed to be a birth for the new child.. Freedom!</p>

<p>MARY. Freedom! O that is the word you are all always saying! A woman must not hold a man from his freedom--<hi rend="italic">with other women</hi>. I know it is what I too, have thought and said. But now I know, I do not understand I only know--it is a lie. Until men get beyond the illusions of their desires, no happiness can be secure for women. There can be no real freedom : no abiding vision of the truth. A woman who loves as I do, cannot feel otherwise than as I.</p>

<p>It is the very deepest of my being that cries out against this wandering, this prostitution of the man, always pursuing some new pleasure, worshipping at some new altar, never finally faithful to any one. Whereas a woman, when she gives herself to love, gives irrevocably. There is no withholding, no duplication possible. It is her life, total and single, that she gives. She can no more share it with another woman than she can share her body and soul.</p>

<l>110</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  111"/>
<p>You give yourself, for to-day. I give myself for ever. To-morrow you can give yourself again, as though it were a new self. I can never take myself away from you to give myself again.</p>

<p>You have finished with my gift . . it ceases to have value. It is no good any more. It cannot be offered to another. I must find a different way of living: and once a woman has been loved, other ways of living are but degrees of death. Harriet's way was the best. But it is not for me.</p>

<p>SHELLEY.    False! False!</p>

<p>MARY.   No, Shelley, it is true.</p>

<p>SHELLEY.   Wickedly false.</p>

<p>MARY.   For you!</p>

<p>SHELLEY. For you, Mary: most of all for you.</p>

<p>MARY. I have always wanted you to be free.
I am my mother's daughter. Let us be reasonable.   It is hard for you too.   When we are older and the fires have burnt out . . .</p>

<p>SHELLEY. The fires will never burn out! O, Death may quench this little candle that floats upon its dark pool: but as long as there is being anywhere this fire that is both my spirit and yours--our fire--will burn ever fiercelier, fiercelier! . . .</p>

<l>111</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  112"/>

<p>MARY. Aren't we wandering from actuality? I should not have said "fire": when this sex-passion has died down in you</p>

<p>Shelley. Why are you poisoning my soul with worldly thoughts? When one body is done our love will take another: the fire must have its flame. While ever life goes on there must be attraction and fertilisation and birth. Ever new attraction and new birth. But never--O never--with denial and treachery to the old. Always and only as a consequence of the old. I love, because I love you, not because once I loved you. You have lighted in me this that cannot be extinguished: a passion you yourself cannot, may not now withhold. It is indeed I that love, but it is not merely I; it is we. You cannot take yourself away.</p>

<p>MARY. I cannot take myself away, and I do not love her. Your Emilia is nothing to me, but I must give you to her. I must share with a mere stranger what is nearer to me than my flesh.</p>

<p>SHELLEY.  Yes--you must share.</p>

<p>MARY. But how, Shelley--how can I learn this?   It is impossible.    I cannot. If only it were some natural necessity! But we are young yet, you and I. Our children are but babes.</p>

<l>112</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  113"/>

<p>You are more fortunate than most men who are born to love, because you have your art: you can find vent there too for passion.</p>

<p>O if only she were real to me: this convent girl, this half-woman, who feeds her sick fancies upon your emotion. She is but little better than a ghost; and it is horrible to me that you should squander upon her all the treasure of sunshine that we two have gathered into this focus of our love. I gave myself to you, but not for her, Shelley, not for her.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. You gave yourself to Love, never to me. Who am I that I should accept an idolatrous gift? Who am I that I should take you for my own, or offer myself so, to you or to another? As a companion, as a lover, as a comrade in freedom, as a partner in life's enterprise,--O yes, yes!--but that is not what you are saying.</p>

<p>We dedicated our love to freedom, having first dedicated to freedom our own souls. You are not mine, nor am I yours, save only in that. We have no use for one another, save in that.Any other thought is abominable to me--and to you!</p>

<p>And Emilia, she also belongs to freedom, as do we. It is in that I meet and am joined with her. Where we meet, where we love, where

<l>113</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  114"/>

we are one delight together, there is freedom...</p>

<p>Do not misunderstand. You have no right to misunderstand what you yourself have made me realise; freedom is the life of that in us which has the right, the power, the duty to be free. When I say I am joined with her in freedom, I say it out of the world of inspiration. I tell the last truth. Something of me that, without her, was blind and dumb, finds sight and speech because of her. I love her by necessity,as I love you. We share together in a life which becomes conscious and creative in so far as we dare love one another, as we dare to be joined and mingled in its being.</p>

<p>MARY. I feel that you are telling the truth.But is it all the truth? What is this in my soul that resists and denies--that forces me to contest your words?</p>

<p>I had always thought of myself as free, and giving freedom. But now I know that this is what I really am.</p>

<p>O, why can I not love Emilia? My deepest being longs for you to have all that life can give.   But not from her, never from her!</p>

<p>SHELLEY. She is unreal to you, and so my love for her is an unreal thing, a fever, an infatuation. As such you hate and struggle

<l>114</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  115"/>

against it--but with unreal weapons. Fighting this that is not, you too become false. And because this love of mine is false to you, I too have become to you unreal; to you whose intense reality is in your love, to you who only hate this one thing, unreality.</p>

<p>MARY. Make me see her as you see her! Save me from what I see! With my own eyes I can see nothing in her upon which any reverence can take hold. If only I could realise a spirit burning within her--and not be always thrown back shivering from those chameleon eyes, that bloodless skin, as from an empty mask. If I could feel her alive behind those fanciful words she marries so easily with yours!</p>

<p>SHELLEY. If you could <hi rend="italic">see</hi> Emilia you would understand, because you too would love her.</p>

<p>MARY. O if I could.   But what an "if" !</p>

<p>SHELLEY. You will begin to believe in her. You will challenge every day this mask till it yields its reality to you. Because I love her, because you cannot doubt I love her, you too will inevitably begin to know and love her. You shake your head, Mary--and yet your eyes shine.</p>

<p>MARY. I think I shall never be able to see her as you do. Our relation will never be like yours: and only, perhaps, in such a relation can



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM   116"/>

her spirit reveal itself. I must be content never to understand. And it may be my love for you will be strong enough even for this last giving up to Love.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. To love is always to have faith,
always to have more faith and more.</p>

<p>MARY. But this growth in faith demands a struggle in the soul that is little removed from actual madness. At times the creative forces of one's passion make one blind, make one cruel, so tremendous is their struggle with the stubborn substance of one's soul. One suffers till one loses hold of oneself. There are moments when I know I am not myself--moments in which I could hurt you, you who are so much dearer to me even than our children. What is it--tell me what it is, my dear!</p>

<p>SHELLEY. It is the birth-pains of the God. And who shall win to liberty save by this mortal way? Only through a sort of madness can we be sufficiently withdrawn from the grasp of our selves for this new spirit to take possession of us. To be shewn the throes of that new birth taking hold upon and shaping a beloved soul, this utterly humbles as it purely exalts the spirit.</p>

<p>MARY. I have always wanted to pay the price.    I think I have never really wanted any

<l>116</l>



<pb n="THE PRICE OF FREEDOM  117"/>

happiness except upon these terms. Well have I known there was a kind of happiness that might indeed be otherwise won and conferred, but never the reality that alone I sought after,--the final good which a man may obtain in exchange for himself. If he keep back a penny it can never be his. For either the deed is whole,or it is a cheat. The payment is without withholding, or it is without avail. For this is just.O above all else I have loved justice, for the sake of Love.</p>

<p>SHELLEY. Without it there could be no freedom. Freedom is a perfect and final thing even as death and birth are in their order final. And Freedom goes beyond them. It is eternal life. It is immediate participation in the integrity of God himself.</p>

<p>MARY. But never without justice: never without wanting to pay the price.</p>
</div>




<l>117</l>



<pb n="118"/>

<div id="binns017" type="poem" n="17">

<head>Greeting to America Entering the War</head>

<lg type="stage">
<l>A BOY, I dreamed that out of Liverpool</l>
<l>I sailed adventuring to the West.  Romance</l>
<l>Presently led me thither, and th' expanse</l>
<l>Of your wide world of freedom did not fool</l>
<l>My April dream.   Anew, I went to school</l>
<l>To wonder, for I saw all circumstance</l>
<l>Growing obedient to man's spirit, and chance</l>
<l>I saw you take, as it had been a tool.</l>
<l>But now, America, that we are set</l>
<l>Together down, commensal with the worm</l>
<l>At the feast of Slaughter, you have put a term</l>
<l>To all my faith's shortcoming; you have met</l>
<l>Our will with yours. Implacable to affirm</l>
<l>The whole of freedom that was never yet.</l></lg>

<byline>HENRY BRYAN BINNS.</byline>
<dateline><name type="place">London</name><lb/>
<date value="1917-10-28"> October the 28th 1917</date></dateline></div>





<l>118</l>



<pb n="119"/>


<div id="binns018" type="poem" n="18">
<lg type="stanza">

<hi rend="italic"><l>THY love is all about me like the loveliness</l>
<l>Of Earth when she puts by the veiling of the snow</l>
<l>And all her beauty of ploughed and fallow, ochre and red,</l>
<l>Nourishes me anew.  Thy love is all about me,</l>
<l>More intimately near my spirit than the flesh</l>
<l>Wherein I live and move and have my daily being.</l>
<l>For only in the enabling presence of thy love</l>
<l>I can become myself, that else with alien speech</l>
<l>Hear myself strangely utter fancies foreign to me.</l>
<l>Within thy love my spirit is confident, at home</l>
<l>As I was never yet in mind or body of mine;</l>
<l>For thou embracest me with that which is not strange</l>
<l>To my imprisoned spirit, bewildered in the mesh</l>
<l>Of this incomprehensible, this unfamiliar world,</l>
<l>That by the magic of thy love is changed for me</l>
<l>Into a welcoming presence, friendly and wonderful.</l></hi></lg></div>





<l>119</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

</body></text></TEI.2>