<idno type="ocm">ocm11266859</idno>
<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>THE POEMS OF</l>
<l>ROBERT W. STERLING</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>PRINTED  IN  ENGLAND</l>
<l>AT  THE  OXFORD  UNIVERSITY  PRESS</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE POEMS</l>

<l>OF</l>

<l>ROBERT W. STERLING</l>

<l>BORN 19th NOVEMBER, 1893</l>
<l>SCHOLAR OF PEMBROKE COLLEGE, OXFORD</l>

<l>LIEUTENANT, ROYAL SCOTS FUSILIERS</l>
<l>KILLED IN ACTION, S. GEORGE'S DAY, 1915</l>





<l>HUMPHREY MILFORD</l>

<l>OXFORD   UNIVERSITY   PRESS</l>

<l>LONDON   EDINBURGH   GLASGOW   NEW YORK</l>

<l>TORONTO    MELBOURNE    BOMBAY</l>

<l>1915</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>Robert Sterling's career at Oxford was cut</l>
<l>short after two years by the outbreak of war.</l>
<l>But these two years had sufficed to create an</l>
<l>impression of him which will endure. As</l>
<l>a poet he was known only to a few till after</l>
<l>his Newdigate Poem had been written. One</l>
<l>evening, at the urgency of friends, he read this</l>
<l>poem to them, and what they now discovered in</l>
<l>its author they felt to be the corollary of what</l>
<l>they had seen before. Doubtless they under¬</l>
<l>stood him better through it, and found therein</l>
<l>a new interpretation of him; but because it was</l>
<l>so true an expression of himself, they realized</l>
<l>that their experience of him was the best inter¬</l>
<l>pretation of his poetry.</l>

<l>For this reason more than any other, it may</l>
<l>be valuable to say something however brief</l>
<l>about his life; and to attempt, imperfectly</l>
<l>enough, to communicate the impression, itself</l>
<l>fragmentary, which he left upon those who had</l>
<l>begun to know and love him.</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>He came to Oxford from Sedbergh. Here</l>
<l>he had spent four years of his school-life; and</l>
<l>entering into its various activities with a boy's</l>
<l>enthusiasm had grown to be a very part of the</l>
<l>place—' He could see and put into words some¬</l>
<l>thing of what Sedbergh meant to us'. For</l>
<l>he never became absorbed in one aspect to the</l>
<l>exclusion of others. His bent was literary, and</l>
<l>he had a refined classical taste, illustrated espe¬</l>
<l>cially in his Latin Verses. ' His interest in</l>
<l>literature alone', wrote one who shared a study</l>
<l>with him, *was quite enough to keep him busy</l>
<l>and happy. Like a true workman he put his</l>
<l>whole soul into what he did.' But * at the same</l>
<l>time he enjoyed to the full every part of school-</l>
<l>life, especially the various societies, and could</l>
<l>always find some common ground for talk with</l>
<l>any one. Although a classical man, he would if</l>
<l>he wished even discuss chemistry or any other</l>
<l>science, and would build up an argument from</l>
<l>first principles in a most amazing way.' And,</l>
<l>on the other hand, he felt intensely the rapture</l>
<l>of the open air, of the fresh wind upon the fells;</l>
<l>had learnt the beauty of the fells themselves, and</l>
<l>the spirit which for lover's eye they embodied.</l>
<l>He understood also, and shared, the strenuous</l>

<l>vi</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>enjoyment of the football field, as afterwards of</l>
<l>the river; but * perhaps his happiest hours were</l>
<l>spent quietly wandering over the Sedbergh hills,</l>
<l>now leisurely fishing some lonely beck, now</l>
<l>lying on the grass in the sunshine, watching the</l>
<l>clouds drift over Winder' ^</l>

<l>In 1912 he left for Oxford. 'I remember',</l>
<l>wrote another and older friend, ' the delight of</l>
<l>his cavalier soul when he found himself King</l>
<l>Charles', scholar at Pembroke.' Hither the</l>
<l>allegiance he had given his school was extended,</l>
<l>not transferred. His presence still breathed the</l>
<l>freshness of his school-days. This boyishness</l>
<l>and simplicity he never lost; nor did it become,</l>
<l>as is sometimes the case, overlaid with a veneer</l>
<l>of intellectualism. He had no conceit of know¬</l>
<l>ledge, and this was because whatever he learnt he</l>
<l>learnt well, so that it became an intrinsic part of</l>
<l>himself. For the same reason it was characteristic</l>
<l>of him to be conscious of his own ignorance ;</l>

<l>^ ' Winder', which is mentioned more than once in the</l>
<l>poems, is the fell nearest to the school, rising some 1,100 feet</l>
<l>above it. It is the most conspicuous and characteristic object</l>
<l>in the view from the playing-fields, and has always been</l>
<l>regarded by Sedberghians as one source of their school's</l>
<l>inspiration. A new boy is not considered initiated till he</l>
<l>has climbed Winder.</l>

<l>vii</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>besides, he realized better than most the infinity</l>
<l>of knowledge. And so, while a superficial view</l>
<l>might fail to detect peculiar intellectual gifts,</l>
<l>those who could see below the surface discovered</l>
<l>that he had thought on things. There was no</l>
<l>precocity, but rather almost a maturity in the</l>
<l>midst of simplicity. He had in fact a clearer</l>
<l>vision than most around him: he could see in</l>
<l>the things that matter aspects which escaped the</l>
<l>common observation. But in this there was</l>
<l>more than perception, at least in the ordinary</l>
<l>sense of the word: there was an imaginative</l>
<l>force which could reclothe past scenes in their</l>
<l>romantic dress, create in fancy beauties un¬</l>
<l>experienced, or dream an Ideal future fairer</l>
<l>than to-day. He had Indeed In him something</l>
<l>of the visionary, an Indication of which may be</l>
<l>seen in the love which, from his school-days, he</l>
<l>had for Blake ; he used to wish that he could</l>
<l>draw, feeling that so only—by artistic as well as</l>
<l>literary expression, as In Blake—could he give</l>
<l>adequate expression to his ideas. A serenity,</l>
<l>and at times a certain dreamy wistfulness, were</l>
<l>peculiarly typical of him, and the quiet strength</l>
<l>that comes of a firm hold upon a principle of</l>
<l>life.    Generally he would be the most silent of</l>

<l>viii</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>a party, and yet on occasions, as when some</l>
<l>cherished conviction was challenged, he would</l>
<l>burst into an ardour that took his hearers by</l>
<l>storm.</l>

<l>For linked indissolubly with this clearness of</l>
<l>vision was—what has already been implied—a</l>
<l>depth of affection. In everything characteristic</l>
<l>of him these two elements, clear vision and deep</l>
<l>affection, united and grew intenser in the union.</l>
<l>At school they Were expressed In that appreciation</l>
<l>of natural beauty which bespeaks not love alone</l>
<l>but intimacy; at Oxford he found a new world</l>
<l>of beauty—Oxford's spirit. Sensitive to her</l>
<l>influence, he began to see nature In a wider</l>
<l>context: the Beautiful, which hitherto he had</l>
<l>found especially in physical nature, he now</l>
<l>more than before sought and found in human</l>
<l>nature also. Only a nature like his, both affec¬</l>
<l>tionate and discerning, could have had both the</l>
<l>will and the power to look beyond his friends'</l>
<l>shortcomings and to love them no less. For his</l>
<l>affection was not due to ignorance of, still less</l>
<l>indifference to, their defects. It was because he</l>
<l>had a keen enough sympathy to see and believe</l>
<l>In what was best in them; and so it was that</l>
<l>herein he was not false but faithful to his ideals.</l>

<l>ix</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>It is hardly surprising that there was a catholicity</l>
<l>about his friendships: his rooms In college</l>
<l>were a centre where men of very various types</l>
<l>would gather; quite simply and generously</l>
<l>he grappled them to him. 'He could convey</l>
<l>a rare warmth of welcome in one exclamatory</l>
<l>syllable; whilst in his mouth the use of a</l>
<l>Christian name at some surprise meeting or In</l>
<l>farewell was a thing not lightly forgotten.'</l>
<l>There was the same glad responsiveness to</l>
<l>simple human joy as to the joy of the country,</l>
<l>and a tenderness of sympathy with trouble as</l>
<l>precious as it is rare.</l>

<l>Just because it was deep, his affection was</l>
<l>neither ostentatious nor capricious. He never</l>
<l>courted friendships: his friends grew around</l>
<l>him ; and they learnt that the force which had</l>
<l>drawn them to him became stronger with closer</l>
<l>contact. * His personality could always inspire</l>
<l>older friendships with a fresh enthusiasm,' wrote</l>
<l>one who knew him both at Sedbergh and Oxford.</l>
<l>Indeed, inspiration rather than attraction is the</l>
<l>true description of his influence. His friendship</l>
<l>ennobled, because his nature was less mundane,</l>
<l>more spiritual, than that of the ordinary mortal.</l>
<l>* He went about life in the same manner as did</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>the knight-errant of old, who would give his</l>
<l>purse to the first wandering beggar he met, and</l>
<l>forget all about it in a moment. Material things</l>
<l>were taken as they came ; if they did not come</l>
<l>he wasted little time in trying to get them.'</l>
<l>This was written of him as known at school, but</l>
<l>it is true of his character throughout: those</l>
<l>who associated with him realized that here was</l>
<l>finer fabric than any dross of earth. Even</l>
<l>a casual acquaintance could hardly fail to mark</l>
<l>the dignity of character sounding in the clear</l>
<l>crisp voice, or writ fair upon the features.</l>
<l>Here surely beauty within and without combined</l>
<l>into that harmony in which Greeks of old saw</l>
<l>the ideal of human life.</l>

<l>With calm clear gaze</l>
<l>He saw and loved the beauty earth can show :</l>
<l>The love was true, as it was young, no phase</l>
<l>That passed, but strengthening with inward glow,</l>
<l>Which woke in others  fire.    He  drew  from</l>

<l>Heav'n</l>
<l>What only love can take, a vision whole</l>
<l>Of things sublime.    The richer life thus giv'n</l>
<l>Back to his God he gave : his gift—his soul.</l>





<l>XI</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>What followed after he left Oxford for the</l>
<l>Long Vacation of 1914 must be told briefly.</l>
<l>Early in August, on the declaration of war, he</l>
<l>applied for and received a commission. The</l>
<l>same allegiance that he had freely given to his</l>
<l>school, his college, and his friends, he now gave</l>
<l>to his country at need. The rest of the year</l>
<l>he spent training In Scotland. Probably during</l>
<l>this time he wrote out fair the poem ' Maran'</l>
<l>printed at the end of this volume. It seems</l>
<l>that he had begun it In his school-days, working</l>
<l>at it afterwards from time to time, and that he</l>
<l>was intensely fond of Intoning its verses to</l>
<l>himself. It was left unfinished, but he evidently</l>
<l>wished it preserved In case he did not return,</l>
<l>as is suggested by the explanatory note which he</l>
<l>prefixed to it.^</l>

<l>In  February 1915 he went out to France.</l>

<l>^ This note is reproduced immediately before the text of</l>
<l>' Maran '. With certain passages of this poem he associated</l>
<l>other poems, which were apparently meant to interpret its</l>
<l>meaning, A facsimile of this association is included with</l>
<l>the text in the hope that it may serve this object. (Towards</l>
<l>its end, ' before him' and ' behind left' reproduce a clearly</l>
<l>unintentional transposition, as may be seen by reference to the</l>
<l>end of ' Maran', where the associated poems are printed</l>
<l>separately, as written out elsewhere.)</l>

<l>xii</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>'It was a great relief, he wrote, *to get out</l>
<l>here after kicking my heels toy-soldiering at</l>
<l>home.' But he adds, ' I've been longing for</l>
<l>some link with the normal universe detached</l>
<l>from the storm. It's funny how trivial Incidents</l>
<l>sometimes are seized as symbols by the memory;</l>
<l>but I did find such a link about three weeks</l>
<l>ago. We were in trenches in woody country</l>
<l>(just S. E. of Ypres). The Germans were about</l>
<l>eighty yards away, and between the trenches lay</l>
<l>pitiful heaps of dead friends and foes. Such</l>
<l>trees as were left standing were little more than</l>
<l>stumps, both behind our lines and the enemy's.</l>
<l>The enemy had just been shelling our reserve</l>
<l>trenches, and a Belgian battery behind us had</l>
<l>been replying, when there fell a few minutes'</l>
<l>silence ; and I, still crouching expectantly in the</l>
<l>trench, suddenly saw a pair of thrushes building</l>
<l>a nest in a " bare ruln'd choir " of a tree, only</l>
<l>about five yards behind our line. At the same</l>
<l>time a lark began to sing in the sky above the</l>
<l>German trenches. It seemed almost incredible</l>
<l>at the time, but now, whenever I think of those</l>
<l>nest-builders and that all but " sightless song ",</l>
<l>they seem to represent in some degree the very</l>
<l>essence of the Normal and Unchangeable Unl-</l>

<l>xIII</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>verse carrying on unhindered and careless amid</l>
<l>the corpses and the bullets and the madness....</l>
<l>I suppose Kipling meant something when he</l>
<l>said that Life runs large on the Long Trail. In</l>
<l>the sense I take it. It runs large out here, not</l>
<l>only for the reason of which you so eloquently</l>
<l>remind me—the inspiration of a Cause, but</l>
<l>because Death has become its insistent and</l>
<l>intruding neighbour.' This was written within</l>
<l>a week of his own death, and about a month after</l>
<l>the death In battle of his own closest friend.</l>
<l>This friend and he had gone up together for</l>
<l>commissions the August before, but had been</l>
<l>assigned them in dIflFerent regiments, stationed</l>
<l>far apart. They went abroad at different times,</l>
<l>but once, for one dramatic hour, ten days before</l>
<l>the friend's death, they were granted what had</l>
<l>hitherto been denied them : they met unex¬</l>
<l>pectedly. ' As always, we didn't know who was</l>
<l>going to relieve us, and we were sitting in our</l>
<l>quarters—what remained of the shell-shattered</l>
<l>lodge of the chateau, playing cards by candle¬</l>
<l>light, awaiting events, when------knocked at the</l>

<l>door and came in. . . . I walked about with</l>
<l>him for about an hour and a half in the chateau</l>
<l>grounds,   stray   bullets   from   the   firing-line</l>

<l>xiv</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>whistling around us,... but I had no idea I was</l>
<l>afterwards going to treasure every incident as</l>
<l>a precious memory all my life.' Those who had</l>
<l>learnt something of the power of such a friend¬</l>
<l>ship, can best understand the desolation of his</l>
<l>grief when his friend was killed. * I think</l>
<l>I should go mad', he wrote, * If I didn't still</l>
<l>cherish some faith In the justice of things, and</l>
<l>a vague but confident belief that death cannot</l>
<l>end great friendships.' It may be that death</l>
<l>came to confirm that faith. He fell one evening</l>
<l>after holding his trench throughout the day. It</l>
<l>was Saint George's Day.</l>





<l>The latter half of these poems—from 'Oxford,</l>
<l>First Vision* to the end—^have not been pub¬</l>
<l>lished before. Of the others : ' The Burial of</l>
<l>Sophocles' won the Newdigate Prize of 1914 ;</l>
<l>' Early Poems' (except the first two) and</l>
<l>* To B. W.' appeared in school magazines—one</l>
<l>(' Hail') in The Wasp^ the Evans House maga¬</l>
<l>zine, the rest in The Sedberghian.</l>

<l>The Sonnet immediately following is printed</l>
<l>by kind permission of its author and The Glasgow</l>
<l>Herald.</l>

<l>XV</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>SONNET</l>

<l>IN MEMORY OF R. W. STERLING</l>

<l>As If Apollo's self had swept the strings.</l>

<l>From Isis' banks came one clear burst of song,</l>
<l>So sad, so noble, beautiful and strong.</l>

<l>Poised through its flight on such majestic wings.</l>

<l>It might not seem a youth's imaginings.</l>
<l>But to an Attic age might well belong.</l>
<l>Or be the flower of that Miltonlan throng</l>

<l>That for dead Lycidas sobs, and sobbing sings.</l>

<l>O brave Boy-Poet, who, at Duty's call,</l>
<l>Laid down thy lyre, thy chaplet cast aside</l>
<l>To don the armour of a sterner day;</l>

<l>Who scorned the lures that held thy heart in</l>
<l>thrall :</l>
<l>Sped down Parnassus with a warrior's pride</l>
<l>To meet thy death In dark Thermopylae !</l>

<l>ROGER QUIN.</l>





<l>xvi</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE POEMS OF</l>
<l>ROBERT W. STERLING</l>







<l/>




<l/>




<l/>




<l>PAGE</l>







<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>THE</l>
<l>BURIAL OF SOPHOCLES</l>



<pb n="4"/>



<l>Kal €7ri TOV Trarploov rdcjiov krid-q tov eiri t-q 683 ttj koto,</l>
<l>T-t]v   Ae/ceXciav   (pepovorj   Keifievov  vpb  tov reixoys   tvBcKa</l>

<l>crraSitov.....      Kai   tovtov  tov   tottov   tTriTCTei^^iKOTcov</l>

<l>AaKeSai/Aovtoji/ Kar* AOrjvaiiav Alovvoos Kar ovap eTrio-ras</l>
<l>AvtravSpo) cKcXevcrev eTTLTpiif/at TeOrjvai tov avSpa els tov</l>
<l>Ta.&lt;f&gt;ov' (*)S 8' d)Xiywpr]ar€V 6 AvaavBpo&lt;;, Sevrepov avrZ iirioT-q</l>
<l>6 Alovvcros TO avTo KeXtvwv, 6 Se AvcravSpos TrvvOavop.evo'i</l>
<l>irapa, tSv (ftvydBbyv tis ciij o T€XcvTijO"as, Kat paOiav on</l>
<l>'S,0(f&gt;0KX7J&lt;; vTrdpXd, KiqpvKa Tri/jAf/a'; eSiBov OaTTTCiv tov dvBpa.</l>

<l>' And he was laid in the tomb of his fai;hers, that is</l>
<l>situated eleven furlongs in front of the wall, on the road</l>
<l>leading past Decelea. . . Now Decelea had been taken</l>
<l>from the Athenians and fortified against them by the Lace¬</l>
<l>daemonians ; to whose general, Lysander, the god Dionysus</l>
<l>appeared in a dream, bidding him give leave for the man to</l>
<l>be buried in the tomb. When Lysander made light of it,</l>
<l>the God appeared a second time with the same behest.</l>
<l>Then Lysander inquired from deserters who the dead man</l>
<l>was; and learning that it was Sophocles, sent a herald with</l>
<l>permission for the burial.'</l>



<pb n="The Burial of Sophocles    5"/>

<group><body><text>
<div id="sterling100" type="part" n="1">
<div id="sterling001" type="poem" n="1">
<head>THE BURIAL OF SOPHOCLES</head>

<p>Sophocles, <hi rend="italic">the grandson, speaks at the poet's tomb</hi>.</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>GREEN hills that wave your olives to the sun.</l>
<l rend="inline">Who but an hour ago did flaming rise</l>
<l>Over the tombs of hidden Marathon</l>
<l rend="inline">And gave you back your shining jewelleries</l>
<l>What meaning dear can the dull eyes of grief</l>
<l rend="inline">Trace  in  your  moving groves  and wizard streams ?--</l>
<l rend="inline">Have ye a knowledge of our troubled quest,</l>
<l rend="inline">The lamentation brief,</l>
<l>The grey road and the haunting twilight dreams,</l>
<l rend="inline">And the lov'd burden laid this morn to rest ?</l></lg>



<pb n="6    The Burial of Sophocles"/>

<lg type="stanza">

<l>Ah ! surely there is wonder and strange stir</l>
<l rend="inline">Amid Earth's guardian gods, when the last goal</l>
<l>Hath galn'd the crown, and to Earth's sepulchre</l>
<l rend="inline">We bear the way-worn chariot of the soul!--</l>
<l>And surely here a memory shall last,</l>
<l rend="inline">In hill and grove and torrent, of this day,</l>
<l rend="inline">For bards to glean who can : and they shall sing</l>
<l rend="inline">How the sweet singer pass'd</l>
<l>Forth to his rest with war about his way</l>
<l rend="inline">And a dread mask of Ares menacing !</l></lg>


<lg type="stanza">
<l>Alas! poor city, fate-enshadow&#x00E8;d,</l>
<l rend="inline">How powerless all thy pride of piety</l>
<l>To give due service to thy poet dead--</l>
<l rend="inline">Save by the favour of an enemy!--</l>
<l>A bitter hard-won favour; for folks say</l>
<l rend="inline">Lord Dionysus twice in vision came,</l>
<l rend="inline">Jealous  and  wroth, to school Lysander's might,</l>
<l rend="inline">That, where his fathers lay,</l>
<l>The darling prophet of the god's own flame,</l>
<l rend="inline">Cradled in calm, should sleep his endless night.</l></lg>


<pb n="The Burial of Sophocles     7"/>

<lg type="stanza">

<l>'Twas thus, that, ere the arrows of the dawn</l>
<l rend="inline">First shot the peaks of clear Pentelicus</l>
<l>With the day's golden promise, we had drawn</l>
<l rend="inline">Nigh to the house of death and girded us</l>
<l>With the dim livery of the funeral :</l>
<l rend="inline">A small, sad band, whom love or blood allow'd</l>
<l rend="inline">To tend the dead ; while vexing the repose</l>
<l rend="inline">Of stars, who listening all</l>
<l>Peer'd  through  a  shifting  curtain  of frail cloud,</l>
<l rend="inline">Like a wild song the women's wailing rose.</l></lg>


<lg type="stanza">
<l>Slowly we brought him forth--can I forget ?--</l>
<l rend="inline">And soft adown the lantern-hemm&#x00E8;d street</l>
<l>Parted the throngs who paid their pious debt</l>
<l rend="inline">Of patient watching and of reverence meet.</l>
<l>And there were  sudden  tears and  murmurs faint</l>
<l>And floating cries upon the midnight air,--</l>
<l rend="inline">Not that they grudg'd him death, nor would importune</l>
<l rend="inline">The gods in idle plaint :</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">But oh ! he went</hi> (their burthen of despair)--</l>
<l rend="inline"><hi rend="italic">Athens' last light--in Athens darkest fortune !</hi></l></lg>


<pb n="8   The Burial of Sophocles"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>How lingeringly we reached the guarded gate</l>
<l rend="inline">Of the dear city fate-enshadow&#x00E8;d !--</l>
<l>As if reluctantly she bore the fate</l>
<l rend="inline">That stole his presence. For of old ('twas said)</l>
<l>The palaces of Kings had sought in vain</l>
<l rend="inline">To woo him from his Athens, and the long</l>
<l rend="inline">Proof of the years had found him ever true :</l>
<l rend="inline">So, like a lover, fain</l>
<l>Would she have held him from this shelter strong</l>
<l>Once hers, now--gift of a curs'd stranger crew!</l></lg>


<lg type="stanza">
<l>But when we left the wakeful, following crowd</l>
<l rend="inline">Within the walls, and passed the sentinels,</l>
<l>Pausing we turn'd : and lo ! for us the shroud</l>
<l rend="inline">Of silent night hid nothing.  All the bells</l>
<l>Were set a-chiming in each memory,</l>
<l rend="inline">And to fond eyes, that knew the outline clear</l>
<l rend="inline">Of every tower and temple and the whole</l>
<l rend="inline">Form of her majesty,</l>
<l>Athens, the queenly city, bade appear,</l>
<l rend="inline">Rob'd  in   revealing  shade, her wondrous soul.</l></lg>



<pb n="The Burial of Sophocles     9"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Her  wondrous  soul, her wondrous, grieving soul</l>
<l rend="inline">Captur'd and fill'd us.--Oh, how fevrous then</l>
<l>(When we had forfeited the passing toll</l>
<l rend="inline">Of tears, that Love itself exacts from men</l>
<l>On such an errand) did we take the road,</l>
<l>And by Cephlsus' ' sleepless fountains' bore</l>
<l rend="inline">On the dead singer of Colonus fair,</l>
<l rend="inline">Yon kindly last abode</l>
<l>Of the royal Theban martyr, who of yore</l>
<l>Curs'd a  false   son   and dying triumph'd there.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Ah ! Fancy loves to weave at such an hour</l>
<l rend="inline">A faery web of false resemblances.--</l>
<l>And who hath strength to curb her perilous power</l>
<l rend="inline">Of blind divining ?  Many phantasies</l>
<l>Made riot in our thought and seem'd to bring</l>
<l rend="inline">The living children of <hi rend="italic">his</hi> poesy</l>
<l>Winging from out the night to claim a part</l>
<l rend="inline">In all our sorrowing :</l>
<l>While the lorn gale out of the Northern sky</l>
<l rend="inline">Sped its far, sullen mutterings to our heart.</l></lg>


<pb n="10    The Burial of Sophocles"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And then that "darkly-riding company!--</l>
<l rend="inline">What rapid, iron question stabb'd the air ?</l>
<l>Rude force in-bursting on our reverie</l>
<l rend="inline">With Insolence of arms and doubting stare !</l>
<l>But when the whisper flew that this was <hi rend="italic">he</hi></l>
<l rend="inline">Poet of all the nations, rare bequest</l>
<l rend="inline">Of Hellas to the treasuries of Time,--</l>
<l rend="inline">Forgot was enmity,</l>
<l>And, sons of Hellas all, we onward press'd</l>
<l rend="inline">Hot with one fervour and one care sublime.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And last, the tomb.--One struck the dead man's lyre</l>
<l rend="inline">By Death long silenc'd, and our hearkening ears</l>
<l>Were open'd for one moment of desire</l>
<l rend="inline">To the pure, perfect music of the spheres ;</l>
<l>As if his Spirit had vouchsaf'd to us</l>
<l rend="inline">A fragment of eternal harmony</l>
<l rend="inline">From its new dwelling-place. The player ceas'd ;</l>
<l rend="inline">All dumb and tremulous</l>
<l>We smooth'd the coffin, cas'd in greenery</l>
<l rend="inline">And with our own shorn tresses over-fleec'd.</l></lg>


<pb n="The Burial of Sophocles      11"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And so we laid him : even so he lies</l>
<l rend="inline">To be for aye the Muse's pensioner :</l>
<l>Poets unborn shall sing him, centuries</l>
<l rend="inline">Untold tell of his fealty to her.--</l>
<l>For oh ! the service of his life will live</l>
<l rend="inline">Deathlessly eloquent.    But I------alas !</l>
<l rend="inline">Left desolate within this teasing world--</l>
<l rend="inline">What comfort can I give</l>
<l>My comrades ere again those walls we pass</l>
<l rend="inline">Whose flag of hope for evermore is furl'd ?</l>
</lg>


<lg type="stanza">
<l>O multitudinous music of the day--</l>
<l rend="inline">Bird-song and breeze and forest-minstrelsy--</l>
<l>You storm this heart and to your chorus gay</l>
<l rend="inline">Marry its dirge of desolate misery :</l>
<l>Whence a faint song of musing hope is born,--</l>
<l rend="inline">Hope for Earth's children whom the Master lov'd,</l>
<l>And for God's justice that he witness'd e'er,</l>
<l rend="inline">Hope for his Athens torn</l>
<l>By foe and feud : So be my spirit prov'd</l>
<l rend="inline">Not all unworthy him whose name I bear.</l></lg>




<pb n="12   The Burial of Sophocles"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Ah ! Master, when the blast uproots a tree,</l>
<l rend="inline">Its form lies bedded--but a god beneath</l>
<l>Treasures its leaves and perish'd fragrancy</l>
<l rend="inline">To pierce anew the pregnant soils of death :</l>
<l>So from thy poetry, thy spirit-tomb,</l>
<l rend="inline">Shall burgeon wealth of tears and tenderness</l>
<l rend="inline">And beauty, when forgotten is this pit</l>
<l rend="inline">And drain'd is Athens' doom-----</l>
<l>Come, leave his  body,  friends, to  Earth's caress.--</l>
<l rend="inline">Oh, lightly, lightly. Earth, encompass it!</l>
</lg>
</div>
</div>
</text></body>

<pb n="[13]"/>



<l>EARLY POEMS</l>



<pb n="[14]"/>

<pb n="Prologue to a Children's Play    15"/>

<body><text>
<div id="sterling200" type="part" n="2">
<div id="sterling002" type="poem" n="2">
<head type="main">PROLOGUE TO A CHILDREN'S PLAY</head>
<head type="sub">SPOKEN BY FAIRY</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>THE golden deities of legend old</l>
<l>Have passed away. No more the hero bold</l>
<l>Holds free discourse with Gods and Goddesses ;</l>
<l>And Nymph and Satyr 'mid the shady trees</l>
<l>No more do revel in a lonely vale ;</l>
<l>Nor Pan's wild music grace the sylvan tale.</l>
<l>But yet to-day our authoress has made</l>
<l>The fairy brood inhabit still the glade.</l>
<l>The tinkling bells of fairyland do sound</l>
<l>As from a distance, and the country round</l>
<l>Is subject still unto their gentle sway.</l>
<l>My name is Starlight, and in this our play</l>
<l>I am the fairy Good who helps the Weak</l>
<l>Against foul-gotten Strength, 'tis I who seek</l>
<l>To foster Justice and to make the Right</l>
<l>Triumph o'er Evil in the well-fought fight.</l>


<pb n="16      Prologue to a  Childreris Play"/>

<l>This is the very essence of the play</l>
<l>That we present to you, O maidens gay.</l>
<l>And you, O gallant youths, and last of all</l>
<l>(And also least) to you, O puppy small.</l></lg>

<dateline><date value="1909">1909.</date></dateline>
</div>


<pb n="SONNET      17"/>


<div id="sterling003" type="poem" n="3">
<head type="main">SONNET</head>

<head type="sub">ON A PICTURE BY R. MACAULAY<lb/>
STEVENSON</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O GIFTED Hunter, would thy skill were mine !</l>
<l>How could'st thou snare the summer's passing voice?</l>
<l>How could'st thou choose the choicest from the choice</l>
<l>Of dulcet summer melodies, combine</l>
<l>And mould them into this--a thing sublime,</l>
<l>Rich in the luxury of loveliness?</l>
<l>What hallowed musing did thy heart impress?</l>
<l>Surely the thought was God's, thy brush divine.</l>
<l>Oh ! I could feel those gende Zephyrs blow</l>
<l>And see thy river mirroring the sun ;</l>
<l>And I could scent the honeyed flowers that grow</l>
<l>Empurpling that meadow every one ;</l>
<l>And somewhere yonder in the fading sky</l>
<l>I gain the secret of Eternity !</l></lg>

<dateline><date value="1910">1910.</date></dateline>

</div>

<pb n="18    THE RIVER BATHE"/> 


<div id="sterling003" type="poem" n="3">

<head>THE RIVER BATHE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>WHEN the messenger sunbeam over your bed</l>
<l rend="inline">Silently creeps in the morn;</l>
<l>And  the   dew-drops   glitter   on   flower  and tree,</l>
<l rend="inline">Like the tears of hope new-born ;</l>
<l>When the clouds race by In the painted sky</l>
<l rend="inline">And the wind has a merry tune :</l>
<l>Ah! then for the joy of an early dip</l>
<l rend="inline">In the glorious pools of Lune !</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Up !   up from your bed !   Let the sluggards lie</l>
<l rend="inline">In an airy palace of dreams,</l>
<l>Respond to the joyous lapwing's call</l>
<l rend="inline">And the song of the burbling streams !</l>
<l>Oh, balmy the air, and wondrous fair</l>
<l rend="inline">Are the hills with sunlight crowned,</l>
<l>And all the voices of nature seem</l>
<l rend="inline">To mingle in one glad sound.</l></lg>


<pb n="THE RIVER  BATHE    19"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Then hurry along, for as light as the heart</l>
<l rend="inline">Are the feet on a morning in June,</l>
<l>To the banks that are speckled with sunshine and shade,</l>
<l>'Neath the guardian trees of Lune,</l>
<l>Where the eddies play with the rocks all day</l>
<l rend="inline">In a whirl of fretful fun,</l>
<l>And the wavelet kisses the pebbly shore</l>
<l rend="inline">With a mirrored smile from the sun.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>A good brave plunge in the crystal cool</l>
<l rend="inline">Of this grand primeval tub :</l>
<l>Then glowing you stand on the warm dry rocks</l>
<l rend="inline">By the edge of the foaming Dub.</l>
<l>Then homeward along, like the soul of a song</l>
<l rend="inline">That has every note in tune ;</l>
<l>And dear will the memory always be</l>
<l rend="inline">Of the glorious pools of Lune.</l></lg>

<dateline><date value="1919-11"><hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1910.</date></dateline>
</div>

<pb n="20     HAIL"/>

<div id="sterling004" type="poem" n="4">
<head>HAIL</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>CROWN'D is our king to-day,</l>
<l>Bloom on the faded spray,</l>
<l>Dawn and her golden ray</l>
<l rend="inline">After sad night ;</l>
<l>Fled be the clouds that loom,</l>
<l>Routed the year-long gloom,</l>
<l>Shade of our Edward's tomb,</l>
<l rend="inline">By the new Light!</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="inline">Waft it, O breeze !</l>
<l>Whisper the Word on thy rustling wing,</l>
<l>Carry it over the leaping seas--</l>
<l>Kissing the dimly glittering sands--</l>
<l>To the lowly homes of far-off lands,</l>
<l ren="inline">And the palaces of kings !</l></lg>



<pb n="Hail    21"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="inline">Ah ! welcome the Word ;</l>
<l>Wherever the red flag flutters</l>
<l rend="inline">And a people's heart is true,</l>
<l>Wherever the olden songs are heard</l>
<l rend="inline">Commingling with the new ;</l>
<l>Where they think on sea-girt Britain,</l>
<l rend="inline">And fight the wilful tears ;</l>
<l>And the old home is the dear home</l>
<l rend="inline">To wistful sojourners.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>As when a weary captive lies,</l>
<l rend="inline">Pale-peering through the bars,</l>
<l>And a noble thought flushes his brain,</l>
<l>And, all oblivious of pain,</l>
<l>His soul soars upward to the skies</l>
<l rend="inline">And the bright joy-sobbing stars :</l>
<l>So, men on earth, O myriad-minded throng,</l>
<l rend="inline">Scorning your narrow fetters, upward soar,</l>
<l rend="inline">And with one voice to the wild air outpour</l>
<l>The thunderous magic of the patriots' song :</l></lg>



<pb n="22       Hail"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Crown'd is our king (ye say),</l>
<l>Crown'd are our hearts to-day,</l>
<l>One heart and crown for aye,</l>
<l rend="inline">One song we sing;</l>
<l>Nobly his life be spent</l>
<l>For the world's betterment,</l>
<l>Peace, honour, and content:</l>
<l rend="inline">Long reign our king!</l></lg>

<dateline><date value="1911-06"><hi rend="italic">June</hi>, 1911.</date></dateline>
</div>

<pb n="In Hendencasyllables    23"/>

<div id="sterling005" type="poem" n="5">


<head>IN HENDECASYLLABLES<lb/>
DYING LILIES</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O  CHASTE queens of a fairy flow'ry kingdom,</l>
<l>Beauteous progeny of the kindly sunshine</l>
<l>And soft show'rs, ever In my heart the fragrance</l>
<l>From you stealing awakes a dreamy vision</l>
<l>Of things beautiful, olden, and eternal:</l>
<l>Passing beautiful!--harmonies so dulcet</l>
<l>That they give to me viewless happy pinions,</l>
<l>On which soaring up into lofty temples,</l>
<l>I drink Truth in a world of airy fancy.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Once you liv'd in a fairy flow'ry kingdom,</l>
<l>Lov'd, and ruling it, innocently happy ;</l>
<l>Now more beautiful in the hour of old age</l>
<l>You still breathe ev'ry perfume of the woodland,</l>
<l>Drooping gracefully, like the last repining</l>
<l>Of some sage who has help'd the weary people,</l>
<l>And whose message at ending is the sweetest.</l>
</lg>


<pb n="24    In  Hendecasyllables"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="inline">Untaught wisdom ! (in all the fields of Eden</l>
<l>No more lovely an emblem of Creation!)</l>
<l>Your souls, dying, appear to sigh the knowledge,</l>
<l>Heav'n-born, forth to the hearts of all around you,</l>
<l>Breathing sympathy, calmness, and achievement.</l>
<l rend="inline">Queens, farewell!    In an age when 'all the laughter's</l>
<l>With  pain fraught', when  a wrinkled, angry brow shows</l>
<l>Discontent ev'rywhere among my fellows,</l>
<l>Sure 'tis good to devote a fleeting half-hour,</l>
<l>O'er you musing upon the joys eternal . . .</l>
<l rend="inline">And I hope in an after age to see you</l>
<l>Still more joyfully grace the Heav'nly Gardens!</l></lg>

<dateline><date value="1911-07"><hi rend="italic">June</hi>, 1911.</date></dateline>
</div>


<pb n="THE TREASURES OF THE SNOW    25"/>

<div id="sterling006" type="poem" n="6">

<head>THE TREASURES OF THE SNOW</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>LOVE you the sun's gaze on the brow of Winder,</l>
<l rend="inline">Toning the world to the faery voice of Spring ?</l>
<l>Love you the storm-rack riding o'er him ghostly,</l>
<l rend="inline">While rush the streamlets, madly bickering ?</l>
<l>Fairer I ween is the dower of horn&#x00E8;d Winter ;</l>
<l rend="inline">Joy-shafts keener than arrows he can throw ;</l>
<l>Lovelier  his  tresses  than   all   the  wealth  of Summer:</l>
<l rend="inline">Say, have you seen the treasures of the snow ?</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Silently and softly, tender and caressing,</l>
<l rend="inline">(Soft as the down that lines the linnet's nest :</l>
<l>Silent  as   the   Music that soothes the ear of Fancy:</l>
<l rend="inline">Tender as the wind's love, sighing from the West!)</l>
<l>Embodied smiles from the white sky falling,</l>
<l rend="inline">Come the white flakes in airy revelry,</l>
<l>Over the whole earth swiftly, surely weaving</l>
<l rend="inline">One rare carpet of delight for me.</l></lg>


<pb n="26     The  Treasures of the Snow"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Run, little burn, fast flying from your lover</l>
<l rend="inline">Strong and  importunate to  make  you his own:</l>
<l>Rapidly, oh rapidly, else he will detain you,</l>
<l rend="inline">Grip you, and embrace you, and kiss you all to stone !</l>
<l>Ah! fantastical glory 'mid the branches:</l>
<l rend="inline">Frost wed to snowflake : masonry sublime:</l>
<l>Beauty death-dealing, pitiless and lovely,--</l>
<l rend="inline">Sure,   the   fair   effulgence    of   an   angel's crime!</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>So  sings  the  heart,  as we  glide  adown  the valleys,</l>
<l rend="inline">Borrowing wings from the glittering below,</l>
<l>Careless of all things, save the world around us,--</l>
<l rend="inline">World of white palaces and kingdoms of the snow:</l>
<l>Wanton, ye  gods.   In   the   cloudy   space   of Heaven!</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">We</hi> are as free, and we choir as free a song.</l>
<l>Flying?--<hi rend="italic">We</hi> fly,   as   to   heights   unmeasur'd soaring:</l>
<l rend="inline">This is no Earth, that is sweeping us along.</l></lg>



<pb n="The Treasures of the Snow   27"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Pleasure, says the Bard, is as fleeting as the snowflake:</l>
<l rend="inline">Fleeting as pleasure is the glory of the snow:</l>
<l>Fades the fair shroud that has hush'd the earth to wonder,</l>
<l rend="inline">Soon, soon evanishing the earth below.</l>
<l>What if the dank rain patters down to ruin,</l>
<l rend="inline">Printing me the lesson that Beauty may not last?</l>
<l>Is the snow lost in the wilderness of dead things?</l>
<l rend="inline">Nay, for I glean'd its treasure as it pass'd.</l></lg>

<dateline><date value="1912-02"><hi rend="italic">February</hi>, 1912.</date></dateline>
</div>

<pb n="28    The Faery Birth"/>

<div id="sterling007" type="poem" n="7">

<head>THE FAERY BIRTH</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>A WAND'RING maiden travel-worn,</l>
<l rend="inline">Scorch'd by the red sun's cruelty,</l>
<l>Espied a little hut forlorn ;</l>
<l rend="inline">Enter'd and grateful down did lie.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>From sweet repose she woke at last,</l>
<l rend="inline">And 'mid the dirt about the ground,</l>
<l>Lone relic of the silent past,</l>
<l rend="inline">A candlestick of brass she found.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>She pluck'd it from the floor below,</l>
<l rend="inline">And softly musing to herself</l>
<l>She rubb'd it with her rags of woe;</l>
<l rend="inline">Then set it on the lonely shelf.</l></lg>


<pb n="The Faery Birth    29"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>She went.  But lo! the fiery King,</l>
<l>Now <hi rend="italic">kindly smiling</hi> from above,</l>
<l>Shone through the dust upon the thing</l>
<l rend="inline">Bright burnish'd by the maiden's love:</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And from that wedding glance was born</l>
<l rend="inline">A dream of golden charities,</l>
<l>Which first illum'd the hut forlorn,</l>
<l rend="inline">Then flitted forth to glad the skies.</l></lg>

<dateline><date value="1912-03"><hi rend="italic">March</hi>, 1912.</date></dateline>
</div>


<pb n="30   Gleams and Glimspes"/>

<div id="sterling008" type="poem" n="8">

<head>GLEAMS AND GLIMPSES</head>

<div id="sterling8000" type="short poem" n="1">
<head>MORNING--AND EARLY PREP.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O SEDBERGH and the Morning</l>
<l rend="inline">And the dancing of the air;</l>
<l>See the crown of Winder glancing</l>
<l rend="inline">To the sun his welcome rare !--</l>
<l>And we valley-folk are scorning</l>
<l rend="inline">All the labour and the care:</l>
<l>For heart and feet are dancing</l>
<l rend="inline">With the dancing of the air !</l>
</lg></div>


<div id="sterling8001" type="short poem" n="2">

<head>NIGHT AND DEJECTION</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="inline">MIRROR'D light the moon doth shed,</l>
<l rend="inline">And the sun 's remember&#x00E8;d:</l>
<l rend="inline">For she promises the gloom</l>
<l rend="inline">Day arising from her tomb.</l>
<l>Alas! no Hope doth lighten so</l>
<l>The starless midnight of my woe!</l></lg>
</div>

<pb n="Gleams and Glimpses    31"/>


<div id="sterling8002" type="short poem" n="3">
<head>ON THE WEATHER</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>TELL me not what again, again</l>
<l>We hear about the Sedbergh rain;</l>
<l rend="inline">Yes, with a kindly frown,</l>
<l>Full oft on Eden send the skies,</l>
<l>To spangle all her greeneries,</l>
<l rend="inline">A dower of diamonds down!</l>
</lg></div>

<div id="sterling8003" type="short poem" n="4">
<head>ANOTHER ON THE SAME</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>'STERN nurse of men' and Nature's mother, I:</l>
<l rend="inline">Homeward to sleep</l>
<l>On my hilly bosom, Thunder and Tempest fly,</l>
<l rend="inline">And Clouds that weep!</l>
</lg></div>

<pb n="32     Gleams and Glimpses"/>

<div id="sterling8004" type="short poem" n="5">

<head>RETURNING FROM THE RIVER BATHE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The morning music</l>
<l rend="inline">In the heart revels fair :</l>
<l>The river water</l>
<l rend="inline">Still brightly in the hair</l>
<l rend="inline">Glistens, glistens.</l>
<l>Then the glad bells to Heaven</l>
<l rend="inline">And the Mind of Man give birth :</l>
<l>And the song of my heart,</l>
<l rend="inline">Hush'd music of the Earth,</l>
<l rend="inline">Listens, oh ! listens.</l></lg>
</div>



<div id="sterling8005" type="short poem" n="6">

<head>EVENING FROM THE CRICKET FIELD</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The grey-wing'd Evening flits adown the dale,</l>
<l>And shades dissolve in undetermin'd shade:</l>
<l>The mystic music of the scented gale</l>
<l>Sings the dead day: and all the objects fade,</l>
<l>Making their separate hues one blended whole..</l>
<l>Chapel and Church and Field--whatever made</l>
<l>Glorious the day--richly together roll</l>
<l>In single wealth : Sedbergh reveals her soul.</l></lg>

<dateline><date value="1912-06"><hi rend="italic">June</hi>, 1912.</date></dateline>
</div>



<pb n="Gleams and Glimpses   33"/>

<div id="sterling8006" type="short poem" n="7">

<head>VALE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>WE'VE wander'd by the well-lov'd ways</l>
<l>That burgeon with remembrances</l>
<l rend="inline">Of time that's flown:</l>
<l>Our song is low,--a farewell song,--</l>
<l>But its theme shall linger with us long,</l>
<l rend="inline">Loud blown from out thy breezes, Sedbergh,</l>
<l rend="inline">To our hearts from out thy breezes blown.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>We've seen thee smile and sternly frown;</l>
<l>Or grief or joy becomes thy crown,</l>
<l rend="inline">Shine-, shadow-dress'd:</l>
<l>Our eyes have draln'd the cup to-day,</l>
<l>But the wine shall ever with us stay,</l>
<l rend="inline">So press'd from out thy vintage, Sedbergh,</l>
<l rend="inline">Unto Time from out thy vintage press'd.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Yon kindly peaks, yon fells have seen</l>
<l>Our pleasure, toil, and striving keen,</l>
<l rend="inline">The songs we've sung:</l>
<l>But Time shall spend his treasuries</l>
<l>Or ever the wing&#x00E8;d Spirit dies,</l>
<l>Far flung from out thy bosom, Sedbergh,</l>
<l rend="inline">To the world from out thy bosom flung.</l></lg>



<pb n="34  Vale"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O shrouded in the mystic Word,</l>
<l>Thou queenly Servant of the Lord,</l>
<l rend="inline">Accept, nor scorn :</l>
<l>Sung by the lordly trump of fame,</l>
<l>Shall rise the glory of thy Name</l>
<l rend="inline">Proud borne upon thy banner, Sedbergh,</l>
<l rend="inline">To the stars upon thy banner borne.</l>

<dateline><date value="1912-07"><hi rend="italic">July</hi>, 1912.</date></dateline></lg>
</div>
</div>



<pb n=""/>



<l>POEMS</l>

<l>1913-1915</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>To B. W.</l>

<l>(Thirty-seven years master at Sedbergh ; died January, 1913.)</l>

<l>So, kind, unconquered spirit, fare you well.</l>

<l>Sedbergh   must  onward yet with  steadfast</l>
<l>mind,</l>
<l>(For such would be your wish)—nor must we</l>
<l>tell</l>

<l>The world of sorrow that you leave behind.</l>
<l>And yet we feel Winder doth surely grieve</l>

<l>His well-loved pilgrim of the happy years.—</l>
<l>Surely the day droops sadly: and at eve</l>

<l>Our Heaven trembles into starry tears 1</l>





<l>37</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>OXFORD—FIRST VISION</l>

<l>I SAW her bow'd by Time's relentless hand.</l>
<l>Calm as cut marble, cold and beautiful.</l>
<l>As if old sighs through the dim night of years,</l>
<l>Like frosted snow-flakes on the silent land.</l>
<l>Had fallen: and old laughter and old tears,</l>
<l>Old tenderness, old passion, spent and dead.</l>
<l>Had moulded her their stony monument:</l>

<l>While ghostly memory lent</l>
<l>Treasure  of form and harmony to drape her</l>
<l>head.</l>





<l>Proud-stooping statue 1 still her arm, up-rais'd.</l>
<l>Pointed the sceptre skyward, like a queen</l>
<l>Gleaning bright wonder from the world amaz'd.</l>
<l>Thrilling the firmament with rapturous awe;</l>
<l>Yet blind in giving light—unseeing, seen:</l>
<l>Self-wrapp'd in gloom of wisdom and deep law.</l>

<l>38</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Oxford—First Vision</l>

<l>Oh, could I pluck (methought) from out yon</l>

<l>breast</l>
<l>A share of her rich mystery, and feel</l>
<l>Flushing my soul with new adventurous zeal</l>
<l>The fiery perfume of that flame-born flower</l>
<l>Which grows in man to God:   then I might</l>

<l>wrest</l>
<l>Glad secrets from the past,—the golden dower</l>
<l>Of the world's sunrise and young glimmering</l>

<l>East.</l>





<l>39</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>OXFORD'S PROMISE</l>

<l>She show'd me where the wakeful gardens grow</l>
<l>Bright with the opening blossom of the Spring,</l>
<l>The fairy births that ever burgeon—lo!</l>
<l>Out of the teeming shadowland of thought:</l>
<l>Such new delight, new hope, new life they bring</l>
<l>(Heart cannot feel nor these dull numbers tell)</l>
<l>As all rare poets down the years have sought,</l>
<l>—Gardens of light and Spring perpetual.</l>
<l>She told me how the Traveller in the way</l>
<l>Borrows fair wings from all the flowery pride</l>
<l>Empurpling the hedge-row at his side:</l>
<l>And how, sped onward by each glad delay—</l>
<l>By wayward Fancy, sudden to Inspire,</l>
<l>Or Peril calling Valour to the fray.</l>
<l>Or human Love yet hot with Heav'nly fire—</l>
<l>He gains the city gate—past foe and friend—</l>
<l>With full spoil laden at the journey's end.</l>





<l>40</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>OXFORD'S DAWN</l>

<l>There was a day when valleys laugh'd aloud.</l>
<l>And Joy danc'd on the waters, and the world</l>
<l>With all its treasure, beast and tree and cloud,</l>
<l>Quiver'd with wisdom,—so the Fancy tells.</l>
<l>Not rarely then upon the earth were hurl'd</l>
<l>Sparks from the fountain-furnace of the sky;</l>
<l>But, as the sea yet roars in hollow shells</l>
<l>Forlorn, so clear from God an endless stream</l>
<l>Flow'd wild among his children from on high:</l>

<l>Who, ever gleefully.</l>
<l>Drank in full flush of innocence that Heav'nly</l>
<l>beam.</l>





<l>Happy, oh, happy fled the rushing years,</l>
<l>Until alas !  the wilful and the blind</l>
<l>Lost the rare glory In a mist of tears.</l>
<l>And the great Father hid his face and mourn'd:</l>
<l>But through the poisonous wrack the light behind</l>
<l>Came palely struggling, and to men return'd.</l>

<l>41</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Oxford''s Dawn</l>

<l>For some great souls with swords of true desire</l>
<l>Pierc'd the gross shroud, and gaining fitful gleams</l>
<l>Fashion'd anew the wisdom of the past;</l>
<l>And scatter'd to their fellows In the mire</l>
<l>The shining fabric of their gather'd dreams.</l>
<l>They grop'd to find the links that couple fast</l>
<l>All things within the Universe.    They lit</l>
<l>The lamp of passionate Faith, and tended It</l>
<l>'Mid scorn and strife.    They dipp'd the poet's</l>

<l>pen</l>
<l>Into the rainbow, and In simile</l>
<l>Join'd fair to fair.    They search'd the mystery</l>
<l>Of that old Eden long denied to men.</l>

<l>And thou, my Oxford, gracious citadel</l>
<l>Of these who foUow'd Truth,—thou didst arise,</l>
<l>The hopeful darling of our western skies,</l>
<l>Sung into being by an antique spell:</l>
<l>Or whether, as the dim old fables tell.</l>
<l>Brut and his pilgrims from unhappy Troy</l>
<l>Built thee: or, servant of high destiny.</l>
<l>Fierce Mempric, red with slaughter of his foes</l>
<l>Cover'd dark evil with a deed of joy.</l>
<l>And hearing in the night a troubled cry—</l>
<l>'Dawn! Dawn!'—unknowing to the favour rose,</l>

<l>42</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>HISTORIC OXFORD</l>

<l>Ah ! Time hath loaded thee with memories</l>
<l>Processional.    What could these piles unfold</l>
<l>Of war's lost travail, and the wearied cries</l>
<l>Of vexhd warriors, struggling to hold</l>
<l>Their hearth secure against proud Norman arms.?</l>
<l>-—And yet the while thy quest was not forgot;</l>
<l>'Mid war and waste and perilous alarms</l>
<l>Ever thy purpose stood, and yielded not.</l>
<l>Noble In faith, gallant In chivalry.</l>
<l>Thou flung'st a radiant Word to all the land,</l>
<l>—Pluck'd from the wealth of thy philosophy.</l>
<l>And to the world upon the breezes strewn;—</l>
<l>When, great with loyalty, thou didst withstand</l>
<l>The kingly perjuror in battle brave:</l>
<l>While England's Lady by the Winter's boon</l>
<l>Fled from thy peril o'er the frozen wave.</l>
<l>What need to tell of all thy generous sons ?—</l>
<l>The priestly Theobald, and in his train</l>
<l>Master Vacarius, mighty in old law.</l>
<l>And the great multitudes that now remain</l>
<l>But shadows flitting in dim pageantry</l>

<l>43</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Historic Oxford</l>

<l>Across the low-lit stage.    In life they saw</l>
<l>Service of toil and striving for thy gain:</l>
<l>The Muse's pensioners in death they lie.</l>
<l>They cherlsh'd thee through bitter strife and</l>

<l>strain</l>
<l>Faithful.    They fought the zealous heretic.</l>
<l>Rapt Wyclif, zealously to guard their Truth.. ..</l>
<l>Nor worthy less were they who serv'd the sick</l>
<l>'Mid hopeless plague, and rifled Nature's store</l>
<l>To bless mankind: nor who for creed or king</l>
<l>Chang'd learning's mantle for the arms of war,</l>
<l>Their lives and treasuries surrendering.</l>
<l>Martyrs and saints have dower'd thee:   one In</l>

<l>Truth,</l>
<l>Old Faith, new Hope, have died to save or mar</l>
<l>The idols of flown ages; for Truth's sun</l>
<l>Shines glad alike upon all enterprise</l>
<l>That in the Father's eyes</l>
<l>Flatters the fledgling soul till the pure heights</l>

<l>be won.</l>

<l>These golden memories sit round thy throne—</l>
<l>They are all thine; and thou art all my own.</l>





<l>44</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>TO PEMBROKE COLLEGE</l>

<l>Full often, with a cloud about me shed</l>
<l>Of phantoms numberless, I have alone</l>
<l>Wander'd in Ancient Oxford marvelling :</l>
<l>Calling the storied stone to yield its dead :</l>
<l>And I have seen the sunlight richly thrown</l>
<l>On spire and patient turret, conjuring</l>
<l>Old glass to marled beauty with its kiss.</l>
<l>And making blossom all the foison sown</l>
<l>Through lapsM years.   I've felt the deeper bliss</l>
<l>Of eve calm-brooding o'er her loved care.</l>
<l>And tingeing her one all-embosoming tone.</l>
<l>And I have dream'd on thee, thou college fair.</l>
<l>Dearest to me of all, until I seem'd</l>
<l>Sunk in the very substance that I dream'd.</l>
<l>And oh ! methought that this whole edifice,</l>
<l>Forg'd in the spirit and the fires that burn</l>
<l>Out of that past of splendent histories.</l>
<l>Up-towering yet, fresh potency might learn.</l>

<l>And to new summits turn.</l>
<l>Vaunting the  banner   still of what hath been</l>
<l>and is.</l>

<l>45</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>A SONNET</l>

<l>Yea, Oxford, for the glories of one wreath</l>

<l>The wither'd fragrance of all time Is fee ;</l>

<l>Trees draw their sacrifice of greenery</l>

<l>From the old charnels that repose beneath ;—</l>

<l>So let me feel the impulse of thy breath.</l>

<l>Like an enchanter's spell, awak'ning me</l>

<l>To thy new treasures of Eternity</l>

<l>Bursting from out the pregnant soils of Death :</l>

<l>And therefore through my lips to all the earth</l>

<l>Adown the ages be thine anthem sung.</l>

<l>Undying Truth's perennial rebirth—</l>

<l>The burthen of the Old and ever Young:</l>

<l>'For  me and  mine  new wealth from old is</l>

<l>grown :</l>
<l>And sure, who love me, shall be all my own !'</l>





<l>46</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>LINES WRITTEN ON LOCH LOMOND</l>





<l>Lonely I llnger'd when you went.</l>
<l>Recalling how the days had fled</l>

<l>Each with its mingled treasure pent</l>
<l>Of shine and shade remembered. . . .</l>

<l>Oh, how I crush'd the grapes divine.</l>

<l>Blending a flood of wakeful wine.</l>

<l>Next look'd I on the well-lov'd scene,</l>
<l>Eager its ready wealth to glean :</l>

<l>And forg'd therefrom a cup of gold—</l>
<l>Red hills, blue loch, and islands green—</l>

<l>(Rare alchemy!).    So could it hold</l>
<l>That vintage of our joy, and I</l>
<l>Drink deep the draught of memory.</l>

<l>July, I9I4.</l>





<l>47</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Lines written on Loch Lomond</l>





<l>II</l>





<l>Love be not sad, but listen</l>

<l>To the laughter of the wave.</l>
<l>Sweeping ever madly after</l>

<l>His desire above yon cave :</l>
<l>See the leaping shingle glisten</l>

<l>With the fire his kisses gave. . .</l>
<l>Oh, mingle, love, your laughter</l>

<l>With the laughter of the wave !</l>

<l>July, 1914.</l>





<l>48</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>LINES WRITTEN IN THE TRENCHES</l>





<l>Ah !   Hate like this would freeze our human</l>
<l>tears,</l>
<l>And stab the morning star :</l>
<l>Nof it, not it commands and mourns and bears</l>
<l>The storm and bitter glory of red war.</l>





<l>II</l>
<l>To J. H. S. M., killed in action, March 13, 1915.</l>

<l>O BROTHER, I have sung no dirge for thee :</l>

<l>Nor for all time to come</l>
<l>Can song reveal my grief's infinity :</l>
<l>The menace of thy silence made me dumb.</l>





<l>49</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>MARAN</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>The fragment Maran is valuable, not for its theme or</l>
<l>language (which are both in parts immature, uncertain, and</l>
<l>childish), but for its rhythm, which reveals a new music,</l>
<l>and properly handled might afford a contribution to literature</l>
<l>and the melody of the world.</l>

<l>The poem is an attempt to recover for the English tongue</l>
<l>a lost heritage—that bequeathed by the old Saxon epicists</l>
<l>(see Bridges' Cforistmas Carol, Iplj)-</l>

<l>Stress and all'tteration.</l>

<l>Lyrical; stanzas superficially resembling Norman conven¬</l>
<l>tion. Should be intoned, with emphasis on each stressed</l>
<l>word, with special care to mark the structure-rhymes of the</l>
<l>even lines. Only one accentuated syllable in each line is</l>
<l>unalliterative.</l>

<l>The wind was wailing over the Mnd wfldly</l>

<l>56ng-jfghing, and the m6on</l>
<l>/.Anguishing, a /6ve-/6m maiden</l>

<l>Pale-/6ering from a shr6ud.</l>

<l>i 1          2                            3    4</l>

<l>I.   X —X —XXXX-------X</l>

<l>t'             1    2                      3</l>

<l>2.-------X XX —</l>

<l>1                   2    3   4</l>

<l>3.  — X X X----------X</l>

<l>12                  3</l>

<l>4.------X X X —</l>

<l>The number of unaccentuated syllables (x) does not</l>
<l>matter. Accentuated syllables ( —) must be four and three</l>
<l>alternately.    Second and fourth lines coincide in structure.</l>





<l>53</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>i.</l>





<l>f</l>
<l>%</l>

<l>CO</l>

<l>"Z  ^   ^ ^</l>





<l>3   54*^</l>





<l>■4    «f</l>
<l>5-^</l>





<l>-5</l>





<l>3^-^.</l>





<l>O</l>





<l>- j«</l>





<l>i 1 J</l>





<l>I 1 '^^</l>





<l>.J</l>
<l>4</l>





<l>1 1 '='</l>





<l>/^</l>





<l>M</l>





<l>c^</l>





<l/>





<l/>





<l>^</l>







<l>X</l>

<l>3</l>





<l>- i</l>





<l/>





<l>J</l>





<l>*</l>





<l/>





<l>I.</l>





<l>.i</l>

<l>»-</l>





<l/>





<l/>





<l>i   i</l>





<l>-^      «*</l>





<l>■i</l>

<l>^  J   -^       1</l>





<l/>





<l/>





<l>^ 3</l>





<l>J</l>





<l>5</l>



<pb n=""/>





<l/>





<l>^   v5 1? j4   ^</l>





<l>3^</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>■J ^^</l>





<l>«&gt;</l>

<l>5</l>





<l>t^</l>





<l>^   ..3</l>
<l>i</l>

<l>*5?</l>





<l>-  1^</l>





<l>1 ^</l>





<l>3     .</l>





<l/>





<l>:i</l>





<l>a2    *j</l>





<l>9^</l>





<l>U_.</l>







<l>c/»</l>





<l>J</l>

<l>i</l>

<l>cr</l>





<l>O</l>

<l>^   "I   -^</l>
<l>-1   -^  ~i</l>





<l/>





<l>-i</l>





<l>ft-         ^ C^</l>





<l>C/^</l>





<l>.3</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>MARAN</l>

<l>The wind was wailing over the land wildly</l>

<l>Song-sighing, and the moon</l>
<l>Languishing, a love-lorn maiden</l>

<l>Pale-peering from a shroud.</l>





<l>Then friendless there fled through the sobbing</l>
<l>forest</l>

<l>Maran, a maid gende</l>
<l>Striving to save herself from the murderer</l>

<l>Kroston the King-slayer.</l>





<l>Burning ambition ! in his blind heart</l>
<l>Hate rankled against the Royal ones :</l>

<l>And when the mountain mist had rolled to the</l>
<l>meadows</l>
<l>Crime-covering, he had slain them.</l>

<l>55</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>When the sun had sped to the  ever-hungry</l>
<l>shadows.</l>

<l>Lone in the land, friendless.</l>
<l>Left of the house of Landa now but lived</l>

<l>Maran the maid gentle.</l>

<l>Then Kroston cried to the other King-slayers,</l>
<l>' Allow we this fledgling to flee us }'</l>

<l>' The Black Brethren would blush at the triumph</l>
<l>Of Maran the maiden, O Kroston.'</l>

<l>Panting and panic-pale as a dove</l>
<l>Doth flutter before the cruel falcon :</l>

<l>So fearful fled the maiden through the forest.</l>
<l>That sobb'd ever to the wind's wildness.</l>

<l>Blood on her bonnle feet, and bruises :</l>

<l>Like deer before dread tiger.</l>
<l>So fearful fled the maiden from the fury</l>

<l>Of Kroston the King-slayer.</l>

<l>Sympathy she sought from the trees sobbing,</l>
<l>But no sympathy had the twining trees ;</l>

<l>And the wind wall'd as with woe laden,</l>
<l>Yet all careless of her cruel woe.</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>Pity she pleaded from yon pale maiden</l>
<l>Tears, spangled in the sky.</l>

<l>Fiercely the fond hope freezing.</l>
<l>Dim glitter'd through the gloom.</l>





<l>And in her mind, grief-murky and madden'd.</l>

<l>Memory sparkled sweet:</l>
<l>Brutal as the beam that mocks the blind.</l>

<l>Stinging the sighdess eye.</l>





<l>As when lowly a forest lord is laid</l>

<l>In winter by the axe wasted.</l>
<l>Dusty, with arms undrap'd and drooping.</l>

<l>Where melody of old haunted,</l>





<l>Yet sweetest of all  the Spring are his scarce</l>
<l>tresses.</l>
<l>Smiling amid Death strangely ;</l>
<l>And the woodman is weeping, of his work peni¬</l>
<l>tent.</l>
<l>Sorrowing o'er Might murder'd ;</l>

<l>57</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>As a star that hath shone in the sky-furnace.</l>

<l>Bright-burning through the ages.</l>
<l>Falters and falls on a day fated</l>

<l>(Dread doom to every beauty !) ;</l>

<l>Then flames he brightest with a flare of fury.</l>

<l>Rushing to dark ruin ;</l>
<l>And silent in  their  spheres  are  the sons of</l>
<l>morning</l>

<l>Dimm'd by their dead brother :</l>

<l>So 'mid stifling Sorrow did burning Sweet</l>

<l>Wanton in Maran's mind.</l>
<l>Grief gaining a spectre of gladness.</l>

<l>Darkness a demon light.</l>

<l>(O garden of years, golden and glad.</l>

<l>Bright with the blossom Love ;</l>
<l>O ancient home of a happy people :—)</l>

<l>Woe ! 'tis a wither'd dream !</l>

<l>(Ever-lighted lamp of holy labour.</l>

<l>Land of the singing swain :—</l>
<l>Happy my eyes that gloried in that heaven,)</l>

<l>Curst that behold this hell !</l>

<l>58</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>(O ye fields fair with corn and fruits,</l>
<l>Trees breaking 'neath their treasure :—)</l>

<l>O heart of me hea-vy with the fruits of happiness</l>
<l>Dead,—breaking 'neath the burden.</l>





<l>(O loving father, and lord beloved.</l>
<l>Thou mirror of Landa's light!—)</l>

<l>Ah ! cruelty to murder a king kindly !-</l>
<l>What darkness is mine to-day }</l>





<l>(O valley singing to the sound of streamlets,—)</l>

<l>Nay, the light Is for thee lost:</l>
<l>Shall thy songs not evermore be with sorrow</l>
<l>sounding.</l>

<l>And thy rivers with blood red }</l>





<l>(O Peace of the Past!) they have depos'd and</l>
<l>sold thee</l>

<l>So blindly by a blind one led :</l>
<l>For cruelly have they murder'd their king kindly,</l>

<l>And darkness is on all to-day.</l>

<l>59</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>So she raving ran with a rage pitying,</l>

<l>Maran the maid gentle.</l>
<l>Striving ever to save herself from the murderer,</l>

<l>Kroston the King-slayer.</l>

<l>But ever pitiless he followed with poor passion</l>

<l>Burning in his blind heart.</l>
<l>Scorning the sacred gods as shadows,</l>

<l>Lusting for the maid's life.</l>

<l>And onward the cruel hunt hasted ;</l>

<l>Nor stay'd the forest his steps:—</l>
<l>Ah! shame on you, shame, ye trees sobbing,</l>

<l>To let him pitiless pass.</l>

<l>Panting and panic-pale his quarry</l>

<l>Still ran the fateful race!</l>
<l>Twice shame on you, ye trees tangling.</l>

<l>To stay her flying steps.</l>

<l>But sudden the wind song-sighing</l>
<l>Hush'd "amid the high branches;</l>
<l>And  the  leaves  murmur'd  with  a  mournful</l>
<l>mystery,</l>
<l>Silenc'd after wild sobbing.</l>

<l>60</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>And the clouds becalm'd, with their vap'rous</l>
<l>cohorts</l>

<l>Commingling In grim mass.</l>
<l>Fraught with unutterable future, floated</l>

<l>Expectant in the vast vault.</l>





<l>And  the  maiden  moon,  unshrouded  for the</l>
<l>moment.</l>

<l>In her grief gazed awfully.</l>
<l>As if innocence should utter a doom of the ages.</l>

<l>Or a child pale prophecy.</l>





<l>And the forest creatures In fretful fear</l>
<l>Stirr'd within their lairs sleepless:</l>

<l>The Hon growl'd as about to lose a lov'd thing.</l>
<l>Dreading an unseen spoiler.</l>





<l>So all nature, nursing a nameless terror,</l>

<l>Listen'd and waiting watch'd:</l>
<l>As, when lightning flashing from the fever'd</l>
<l>firmament</l>
<l>Swoops on the nerveless night,</l>

<l>6i</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>Then the shepherds, in lonely silence sitting,</l>

<l>Listen and waiting watch.</l>
<l>In pious prayer to the gods impasslon'd.</l>

<l>Fearing the following peal.</l>

<l>Yet ever onward the cruel hunt hasted;</l>

<l>Do they know not of all Nature's watch.-'</l>
<l>Will fear fly and fury pursue</l>

<l>Till the treasuries of Time be spent}</l>

<l>Nay! ... for the unknown is near, and Kroston</l>

<l>In his course sudden stopt:</l>
<l>And his men marvell'd at the awful madness</l>

<l>Of his cry woe-wild.</l>

<l>But silent they stood round the king-slayer.</l>
<l>And they felt his fear in their hearts:</l>

<l>And  waiting they watch'd for the untellable</l>
<l>wonder</l>
<l>That was coming, coming to pass.</l>

<l>Then forth from his limbs a form of fairness</l>

<l>Sped, like a wan wave</l>
<l>Of living cloud, light-laden,</l>

<l>Seeing and dim seen.</l>

<l>62</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>Oh, agony beyond utterance, and stained horror I</l>

<l>He watch'd the winged shadow</l>
<l>Fast flitting through the aw'd forest</l>

<l>To Maran the maid gentle.</l>

<l>And she stopt and turn'd, and saw it sailing</l>

<l>Swift and sure in her path;</l>
<l>And in wondrous wise her fear wan'd!</l>

<l>Dawning day after night !</l>

<l>Her body enfolded it beautifying, emboldening.</l>

<l>Till Its light in her eyes did leap.</l>
<l>And  there   stately she   stood   like   a   queen</l>
<l>sorrowing.</l>

<l>And she rals'd to the air her hand.</l>

<l>Then the men of Kroston, amaz'd and madden'd</l>

<l>In taut sorrow shriek'd;</l>
<l>For releas'd and lost, their bodies leaving,</l>

<l>Each fair phantom pass'd.</l>

<l>And Nature knew of the nameless terror</l>

<l>That carp'd her haunted heart:</l>
<l>And her gaunt bosom, great with grief,</l>

<l>Like swollen ocean, shook.</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>Then flash'd her phantoms, tongues of fire,</l>

<l>From earth and sky streaming.</l>
<l>Filling the maiden's form with a fairness</l>

<l>Unknown to mind mortal.</l>

<l>With unending hue empurpling the air</l>

<l>And soft shapes innumerable</l>
<l>(Even drear depths of darkness sent</l>

<l>Their bright burdens glitteringly)—</l>

<l>Lovelier than the light of lonely skies</l>

<l>O'er snow-white wastes.</l>
<l>When for pale mariners in perilous passage</l>

<l>The dance-rays dart—</l>

<l>Purer than the palace of pale heat</l>
<l>In yon throbbing ember on the altar.</l>

<l>Which glows and gives the priest of Its glory,</l>
<l>And his soul is nourish'd by Its splendour.</l>

<l>Each flower or blossom through the far forest.</l>

<l>Each branch or lowly blade.</l>
<l>Sent forth its soul—or the soul of Something</l>

<l>It felt and lov'd before.</l>

<l>64</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>Maran</l>

<l>Then wall'd the wind in bereavement wasted.</l>

<l>Sighing a broken song.</l>
<l>Like a mermaid moaning the drowned millions</l>

<l>Lost in the sceptred sea.</l>

<l>And the forest sobb'd : and feeble and fainting</l>

<l>The tribes of the teeming earth</l>
<l>Utter'd a lament from the heart's agony:</l>

<l>But vain was their voice of woe.</l>





<l>And   the   people   of mountain  and   meadow,</l>
<l>miserable.</l>

<l>The angulsh'd beasts of the earth.</l>
<l>And the stars of the sky and their sad mistress,</l>

<l>All paid the pitiless toll.</l>

<l>O tears of the land! what toll terrible !</l>

<l>What lov'd and lost delight!</l>
<l>O land of tears ! so lonely and loveless,—</l>

<l>What trembling tears are thine!</l>





<l>65</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>The wind among</l>
<l>The willows seems</l>

<l>To sing a song</l>
<l>Of many themes :</l>

<l>Now joyous soft :</l>
<l>Now musing slow :</l>

<l>Tempestuous oft</l>
<l>Or wild with woe.</l>





<l>The moon looks down</l>

<l>Upon the sea ;</l>
<l>With smile or frown</l>

<l>Inconstant she:</l>

<l>For waves reflect</l>
<l>Her as they will,—</l>

<l>With storm-foam fleck'd</l>
<l>Or clear and still.</l>





<l>Man's mind is a sea</l>
<l>The moon doth scan.</l>

<l>And a willow tree</l>
<l>Is the mind of man.</l>





<l>66</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>1 TIP-TOED from the palace gates</l>
<l>To find the toy</l>

<l>The rainbow spilt:</l>
<l>In fearful joy</l>

<l>And innocent guilt;</l>
<l>Nor heard the laughter of the Fates.</l>

<l>And straight Into a painted sphere</l>
<l>Of rainbow mist</l>

<l>I seem'd to rise :</l>
<l>And phantoms kiss'd</l>
<l>Of starry eyes,</l>
<l>And all forgot my palace dear.</l>

<l>But when the shadows set me free</l>
<l>A memory yet tormenteth me :—</l>
<l>And oh ! that laughing mockery.</l>





<l>67</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE ROUND</l>

<l>Crown of the morning</l>
<l>Laid on the toiler:</l>
<l>Joy to the heart</l>
<l>Hope-rich.</l>

<l>Treasure behind left ;</l>
<l>Riches before him,</l>
<l>Treasur'd in toil.</l>
<l>To glean.</l>

<l>Starlit and hushful</l>
<l>Wearily homeward :</l>
<l>Rest to the brow</l>
<l>Toil-stain'd.</l>





<l>68</l>



<pb n=""/>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

