
<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>THE MAN WHO SAW</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>BY THB SÃMB AVTHOR</l>

<l>THE POEMS OF WILLIAM WATSON.</l>

<l>In 2 V'oIb., with Portrait. Comprising nearly the</l>
<l>entire contents o£ the Author's 12 previously pub-</l>
<l>lished Volumes.   9s. net.   London : John Lane.</l>





<l>LATBR rOLUMBS BY THE SAME AUTHOR</l>

<l>NEW  POEMS.     5*. net.    London :  John</l>

<l>Lane.</l>

<l>SABLE   AND   PURPLE.    2s.   6ã.   net.</l>

<l>LONDON :  EVELEIOH NaSH.</l>

<l>THE   HERALDS   OF  THE  DAWN.    A</l>

<l>Dramatic Poem.   is. 6d. net.    London : John Lane.</l>

<l>THE    MUSE   IN    EXILE.     3s. 6d.   net.</l>
<l>London : Herbert Jenkins, Ltd.</l>

<l>RETROGRESSION.   Ss. U. net,    London :</l>

<l>JOHN  LANE.</l>





<l>PROSE WORKS BY THE SAMB AUTHOR</l>

<l>EXCURSIONS IN GRITIGISM.    5t. net.</l>

<l>LONDON : JOHN Lane.</l>

<l>PENGRAFT : A Plea for the Older Ways.</l>

<l>Ss. 6d. net.   London : John Lane.</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE MAN WHO SAW</l>

<l>AND  OTHER POEMS ARISING</l>
<l>OUT OF THE WAR</l>





<l>BT</l>

<l>WILLĨAM WATSON</l>





<l>LONDON</l>
<l>JOHN MURRAY, ALBEMARLE STREET, W.</l>

<l>1917</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>All Rights Rbsebved</l>



<pb n=""/>


<div id="watson" type="preface">
<head>PREFACE</head>

<p>TWICE in his lií'e the author of this little book has had the experience, so painful to a patriotic man, of difFering from the majority of his countrymen on the moral issues involved in certain large and complex questions of international or imperial policy. In both cases he recorded his views and feelings very unambiguously in verse, incurring not a little odium and losing some friends. In both cases public opinion has since moved round into a position fundamentally much nearer his own than it had at first occupied. During the present war, with all its agonies and horrors, he has had at any rate the one private satisfaction of feeling not even the most momentary doubt or misgiving as to the perfect righteousness of his country's cause. There is nothing on earth of which he is more certain than that this Empire, throughout this supreme ordeal, has shaped her course by the Hght of purest duty. Her way has been the way of the just; and even if it be arguable that a base expediency would have dictated another path--even if it be held that by



<pb n="vi                    PREFACE"/>

acquiescing in the initial assault upon France through Belgium she could have purchased a doubtful and transient safety by a sure and lasting infamy--none but a coward and a knave would at any time have counselled so hateful a bargain.</p>

<p>The author owes much to Germany. Though he cannot use her tongue, he has been nourished all his life upon her unmatched achievements in an art which speaks a universal language, the art of Music. To many this art perhaps appears non-moral, yet in the works of the greatest Germanic masters of harmony--and in Beethoven most of all--there is a strangely bracing moral quality, a power which seems to arm the soul for its battle with Circumstance. It must be plain that one who has the feeling of profound obligation to Germany which is here confessed could hardly have had any malice aforethought against her when hostilities began. He was in fact one of those Englishmen who were hardest to convince of her evil intentions, till these flamed forth into acts. When she crossed the fateful bourne one of his uppermost feelings was a purely human regret that a people whose spirit had helped and fed his own should have now taken their irrevocable stand against tlie forces of light and growth and ascension.</p>

<p>The contents of this volume include little that can be described as poems of action. The author



<pb n="PREFACE                              vii"/>

desires his book to be considered as an intermittent commentary on the main developments, and some of the collateral phenomena, of the war. Respecting the arrangement of the poems he feels that a word of apology is due to the reader. Almost the last written is placed íîrst; and though the contents of each separate section of the book are in the main arranged chronologically, the sections themselves pretend to no such order, but are really concurrent, not sequent. He regrets the resulting interruptions of continuity, but they were forced upon him as perhaps the lesser of two evils by the following considerations. Twenty-four of the poems are sonnets. That is to say, they are cast in a mould which, when used in the spirit and tradition of its stricter masters from Milton onwards, is not a loose aggregation of lines which chance to be fourteen in number, but one of the most rigorously exacting  poetic forms; a form usually demanding from him who employs it no little mental concentration, and enjoining upon him a certain artistic asceticism such as forbids his being seduced into mere by-play of thought or emotion. This came to be rather generally understood amongst us in the early "'eighties," when the history of various poetic vehicles or instruments was perhaps more discussed than in later years; but at the present time it is quite a common thing for a sonnet to be referred


<pb n="viii     PREFACE"/>

to vaguely as its writer's "lines" on this or that, thus showing that whatever special labours may have gone to its shaping have been largely or entirely lost upôn the preoccupied critic. A poet has a duty towards the offspring of his brain, even as toward the heirs of his body; and it is out of a perhaps pardonable regard for their interests and welfare, and as far as possible to secure for them their reasonable dues, that the author has thought fît to detach the sonnets in this volume from their companion poems, and give them a place apart. To dwell, though but for a moment, upon a matter so intensely literary, and at the same time so narrowly personal, may to some readers appear unseemly in a book concerned with the stupendous events now convulsing the world, and written under their shadow; but " Peace hath her victories," and even Poetry her toils, and the latter are not among the least arduous of human efforts.</p>

<p>It only remains for him to add that although many of these poems have already appeared--some of them under now-abandoned titles--in various newspapers, periodicals, and other publications,<ref target="viii">1</ref> the

<note place="foot" id="viii" n="1">&#x00B9; The <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Daily News</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Morning Post</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Guardian</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Daîly Telegraph</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Daily Chronicle</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Evening News</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Westminster Gazette</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Observer</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">English Review</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Weekly Dispatch</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Sunday Pictorial</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">New York Herald</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">New York Independent</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth Century</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">King Albert's Book</hi>.</note>



<pb n="PREFACE                          ix"/>

editors of which are here thanked for permission to reprint them, not a few have since undergone a process for which " revision" would be a feeble word. Indeed, it is scarcely an exaggeration to say that in numerous cases the version originally published was little more than the ground-plan of what is offfered in the ensuing pages.</p>

<byline>W. W.</byline>

</div>

<l>THE  MAN  WHO  SAW</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n="17"/>

<div id="watson001" type="poem" n="1">

<head>THE MAN WHO SAW</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>THE master weavers at the enchanted loom</l>
<l rend="inline"> Of Legend, weaving long ago those tales</l>
<l>Through which there wanders the grey thread of truth,</l>
<l>Lost in the gorgeous arras of romance,</l>
<l>Tell how King Vortigern resolved to build</l>
<l>A Tower of Safety, mid the solitudes</l>
<l>That are the hem of the great druid robe</l>
<l>Of Snowdon, Mount of Eagles.  So each day</l>
<l>The builders laboured, marrying stone to stone ;</l>
<l>But ever in the night an adversary</l>
<l>Invisible as malevolent cancelled those</l>
<l>Cold nuptials, and with impish wanton rage</l>
<l>Shattered the walls. And thither, from beyond</l>
<l>That congress of grave mountains, met like seers</l>
<l>And bards august, though in a rivalry</l>
<l>Of silence rather than of song--from where</l>
<l>The vales are not so tranced with awe, nor yet</l>
<l>So far below the hilltops as to feel</l>
<l>Aching estrangement--fortune one day brought</l>
<l>A youth whose very brow was a command.</l>


<pb n="18           THE  MAN  WHO  SAW"/>

<l>His name of Merlin had not clambered then</l>
<l>To fearsome greatness, like a dusky star ;</l>
<l>Yet ev'n thus early his subduing eyes</l>
<l>Seemed to have known all things in life but tears ;</l>
<l>And standing where wrecked hopes bestrewed the ground,</l>
<l>He said to them whose toil was shards and dust:</l>
<l>" Go search beneath your tower's foundations ; there</l>
<l>Are the Unbuilders, busy while you build ;</l>
<l>The Undoers are there." And every man obeyed.</l>
<l>And digging deep, they found a hollow abysm,</l>
<l>Where waters gnawed the ribs of the Earth, and sapped</l>
<l>Her sinews, till her frame tottered infirm ;</l>
<l>Where also monsters heaved their tumid bulk</l>
<l>In ancient ambush, and with tremors vast</l>
<l>Palsied those ramparts as they yearned to rise :</l>
<l>Blind dragon shapes, of blindest darkness born,</l>
<l>That save in darkness could not live an hour,</l>
<l>And, touched by Light, made their dull moan, and died.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="inline">Such is the tale, which one, who chronicled</l>
<l>Old shadowy wars in sanctuaries of peace,</l>
<l>Found amid crumbled pomps, the hushed domain</l>
<l>Of mildew, and the empire of the moth,</l>
<l>Nigh on eight hundred years ago.  And now,</l>
<l>Out of that land where Snowdon night by night</l>

<pb n="THE MAN WHO  SAW                 19"/>

<l>Receives the confidences of lonesome stars,</l>
<l>And where Carnarvon's ruthless battlements</l>
<l>Magnificently oppress the daunted tide,</l>
<l>There comes--no fabled Merlin, son of mist,</l>
<l>And brother to the twilight, but a man</l>
<l>Who in a time terrifically real</l>
<l>Is real as the time ; formed for the time ;</l>
<l>Not much beholden to the munificent Past,</l>
<l>In mind or spirit, but frankly of this hour;</l>
<l>No faggot of perfections, angel or saint,</l>
<l>Created faultless and intolerable;</l>
<l>No meeting-place of all the heavenlinesses;</l>
<l>But eminently a man to stir and spur</l>
<l>Men, to afflict them with benign alarm,</l>
<l>Harass their sluggish and uneager blood,</l>
<l>Till, like himself, they are hungry for the goal;</l>
<l>A man with something of the cragginess</l>
<l>Of his own mountains, something of the force</l>
<l>That goads to their loud leap the mountain streams.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="inline">And he too comes to bid the builders probe</l>
<l>Deep undemeath the Tower of Safety, lest</l>
<l>A pit lie cavernous and covert there,</l>
<l>A long baulked, ravening emptiness, a grave</l>
<l>That famishes for its expected food.</l>
<l>Nay, in his hands he takes the delver's spade,</l>
<l>Lays bare the hoUow, o'er which to build at all</l>
<l>Were to build woe and ruin, and 'stablishes</l>



<pb n="20               THE  MAN  WHO  SAW"/>

<l>A mightier tower, bastioned so broad and firm,</l>
<l>In life, in manhood, and in womanhood,</l>
<l>Founded upon so massy a human rock,</l>
<l>And with such living bulwarks against them</l>
<l>Who first poured death from where the lark strews bliss,</l>
<l>That when, at last, ours shall be Triumph, though</l>
<l>Triumph perhaps too weary to rejoice,</l>
<l>Save with a mournful jubilation--when</l>
<l>Hate shall reel back from these embattled walls,</l>
<l>And having spent so long its hurtling bolts</l>
<l>With such poor thrift, shall stand before the stars</l>
<l>Bankrupt of thunder--then indeed shall Time</l>
<l>Add yet another name to those the world</l>
<l>Salutes with an obeisance of the soul:</l>
<l>The name of him, the man of Celtic blood,</l>
<l>Whom Powers Unknown, in a divine caprice,</l>
<l>Chose and did make their instrument, wherewith</l>
<l>To save the Saxon : the man all eye and hand,</l>
<l>The man who saw, and grasped, and gripped, and held.</l>
<l>Then shall each morrow with its yesterday</l>
<l>Vie, in the honour of nobly honouring him,</l>
<l>Who found us lulled and blindfold by the verge</l>
<l>Of fathomless perdition and haled us back.</l>
<l>And poets shall dawn in pearl and gold of speech,</l>
<l>Crowning his deed with not less homage, here</l>
<l>On English ground, than yonder whence he rose:</l>

<pb n="THE MAN WHO  SAW                21"/>

<l>Yonder where crash the cataracts through the chasms,</l>
<l>And unto the dark tempests the dark hills</l>
<l>Offer their stubborn sides all gored, but keep</l>
<l>A heart invincible and impregnable;</l>
<l>While with long arm and piercing spear the sea</l>
<l>Thrusts far into the valleys, that of old</l>
<l>Heard the twin raptures of the harp and sword,</l>
<l>The heroic strife, and the heroic strings,</l>
<l>Amid the battling torrents, and beneath</l>
<l>The happier peaks, that without strife, prevail.</l>
</lg>


<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>SONNETS</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>


<div id="watson002" type="poem" n="2">
<head>THE FOURTH  OF AUGUST, 1914</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>AT last we know you, War-lord. You, that flung</l>
<l>The gauntlet down, fling down the mask you wore,</l>
<l>Publish your heart, and let its pent hate pour,</l>
<l>You that had God for ever on your tongue.</l>
<l>We are old in war, and if in guile we are young,</l>
<l>Young also is the spirit that evermore</l>
<l>Burns in our bosom ev'n as heretofore,</l>
<l>Nor are these thews unbraced, these nerves unstrung.</l>
<l>We do not with God's name make impious play;</l>
<l>We are not on such easy terms with Heaven ;</l>
<l>But in Earth's hearing we can verily say,</l>
<l>"Our hands are pure; for peace, for peace we have striven ";</l>
<l>And not by Earth shall he be soon forgiven</l>
<l>Who lit the fire accurst that flames to-day.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="26  TO THE UNITED STATES"/>

<div id="watson003" type="poem" n="3">
<head>TO THE  UNITED  STATES</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>GREAT, O majestic Nation, great is calm !</l>
<l>Great, when old bounds dissolve, to tower apart,</l>
<l>There beyond Europe's throes, and with a heart</l>
<l>At peace, from northern pine to southern palm.</l>
<l>Great, in glad harvest-time, to send the psalm</l>
<l>Rolling to Heaven, nor be as they who start</l>
<l>At mutter of far cannon : and when the Mart</l>
<l>Rocks to and fro delirious, great is calm.</l>
<l>But when a Despot, swoln with the desire</l>
<l>Of boundless sway, forbears not to uncage</l>
<l>War's wolves on shieldless youth and guardless age,</l>
<l>Greater, O Nation, greater then is ire!</l>
<l>Doff <hi rend="italic">then</hi> thy placid mien : unleash thy rage,</l>
<l>And sear and blast him with thy lips of fire.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="TO THE GERMAN EMPEROR  27"/>

<div id="watson004" type="poem" n="4">

<head>TO THE  GERMAN EMPEROR,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">after the sack of Louvain</hi></head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>WHEREFORE are men amazed at thee, thou Blot</l>
<l>On the fair script of Time, thou sceptred Smear</l>
<l>Across the Day? Thou wert divulged full clear--</l>
<l>Hell's sponsor--long ago!  Has earth forgot</l>
<l>Thy benison on a monster reeking hot</l>
<l>From shambles bloody as these,--thy orient peer,</l>
<l>Thy heart's mate, and infernal comrade dear ?</l>
<l>His red embrace do men remember not ?</l>
<l>Fall'n is thy fellow and withered from the scene:</l>
<l>Follow him thou !  And when the hounds of doom</l>
<l>Rend thee, and for thy carrion there hath been</l>
<l>Fit dust-heap found, and no relenting broom,</l>
<l>Purged be Life's palace of thy trail unclean,</l>
<l>And Earth made bride-sweet with returning bloom.</l>
</lg>
</div>



<pb n="28  TERMONDE"/>


<div id="watson005" type="poem" n="5">
<head>TERMONDE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>IN wrecked Termonde, still quaking from the bellow</l>
<l>Of war's mad herd--'mid ruin on ruin piled,</l>
<l>A stranger found a shrine, not all defiled,</l>
<l>Of Art's old sculptured glories without fellow;</l>
<l>And there--while Autumn's banners rustled yellow--</l>
<l>High above seas of desolation isled,</l>
<l>Unbruised, unmarred, with her unwounded child,</l>
<l>Leaned a serene Madonna of Donatello.</l>
<l>O'er a fledged Hermes, lord of speed and spoil,</l>
<l>O'er the vast throes of the Laoco&#x00F6;n,</l>
<l>And Milo's lurking marble smile, she shone:</l>
<l>Throned above piUage, and agony's serpent coil,</l>
<l>And carnal charms that fever and embroil,</l>
<l>Motherhood, scatheless, lived divinely on.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="BELGIUM   29"/>

<div id="watson006" type="poem" n="6">

<head>BELGIUM</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O LITTLE ship among the Dreadnoughts vast,</l>
<l>Where is the Dreadnought that is great as thou?</l>
<l>The seas break over thee from poop to prow;</l>
<l>Gone are thy sails and rigging, gone each mast;</l>
<l>Thy tackle and gear are to the midnight cast;</l>
<l>But though the tempest ripped and stripped thee, how</l>
<l>Thy crew and Captain bore them is ev'n now</l>
<l>As Saga and Song that Ught the unpassing Past.</l>
<l>Thou need'st not the world's tears! The coldly wise</l>
<l>That, safely harboured, clutch the sheltering lee,</l>
<l>With something of strange envy in their eyes</l>
<l>Gaze on the splendour of thine agony,</l>
<l>And hear the fleets of God saluting thee,</l>
<l>From anchorage old, under no neutral skies.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="30    TO KING ALBERT"/>

<div id="watson007" type="poem" n="7">
<head>TO KING ALBERT</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>RECEIVE, from one who hath not lavished praise</l>
<l rend="inline"> On many Princes, nor was ever awed</l>
<l>By Empire such as grovelling slaves applaud,</l>
<l>Who cast their souls into its altar-blaze,--</l>
<l>Receive the homage that a freeman pays</l>
<l>To Kinghood flowering out of Manhood broad,</l>
<l>Kinghood that toils uncovetous of laud,</l>
<l>Loves whom it rules, and serves the realm it sways.</l>
<l>For when Your people, caught in agony's net,</l>
<l>Rose as one dauntless heart, their King was found</l>
<l>Worthy on such a throne to have been set,</l>
<l>Worthy by such as They to have been crowned :</l>
<l>And loftier praise than this did never yet</l>
<l>On mortal ears from lips of mortals sound.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="TRANQUIL   LIBERTY  31"/>

<div id="watson008" type="poem" n="8">
<head>TRANQUIL LIBERTY</head>
<q><epigraph>(" Pax est tranquilla libertas.--<cit>CICERO</cit>)</epigraph></q>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>PEACE is no peace when all its dream is war;</l>
<l rend="inline">Nor are repasts beneath the hair-swung sword,</l>
<l>That awed in Syracuse the tyrant's board,</l>
<l>Such banquets as the peoples hunger for.</l>
<l>Not to Europa's bull need toreador</l>
<l>Wave scarlet provocation ; and Accord</l>
<l>Blooms ill from arsenals for ever stored</l>
<l>With mouths of death for ever in act to roar.</l>
<l>An areopagus of nations let</l>
<l>Men found hereafter, puissant to restrain</l>
<l>Flaunted armipotence, whether on earth or sea</l>
<l>Or the outraged air, and suchlike peace beget</l>
<l>As TuUy envisioned ; peace itself being vain,</l>
<l>That is not also tranquil liberty.<ref target="watson31">1</ref></l></lg>

<note place="foot" id="watson31" n="1"> First   published, Oct. 23, 1914, in the <hi rend="italic">Westminster Gazette</hi>.</note>
</div>


<pb n="32  THE GIFTS OF HINDUSTAN"/>

<div id="watson009" type="poem" n="9">
<head>THE  GIFTS  OF HINDUSTAN</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>THIS day do maharajah and zemindar</l>
<l rend="inline">Show forth the Orient's most imperial mood.</l>
<l>Satrapies old, and kingdoms that were food</l>
<l>For ravening Time already in years afar,</l>
<l>Long ere Hydaspes' tide disdained to bar</l>
<l>The hosts of Alexander, bring unwooed</l>
<l>Their offerings, and the East forgets to brood,</l>
<l>And leaps to foUow in tempest England's star.</l>
<l>For there, where first it bloomed, still wisdom flowers,</l>
<l>And Hindustan knows well her friends, being wise!</l>
<l>Hither, with smouldering empires in her eyes,</l>
<l>She pours unasked her tributary gold,</l>
<l>Pouring therewith her heart's goodwill, in showers</l>
<l>Richer than all Golconda an hundredfold.</l></lg>
</div>

<pb n="ARABIA FELIX   33"/>

<div id="watson010" type="poem" n="10">
<head>ARABIA  FELIX</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>EMIR of Heaven, Fatima's gorgeous heir,</l>
<l rend="inline">Thou golden-scimitar'd Aldebaran,</l>
<l>Who, since the million-tented world began,</l>
<l>Hast journeyed slow through desert night, and there,</l>
<l>In pilgrimage unhalting, dost repair</l>
<l>To some celestial Mecca unknown of man--</l>
<l>Look down from thine eternal caravan</l>
<l>On earth's dim mosque, with Time's pale minarets fair,</l>
<l>And shower harmonious influences around</l>
<l>Yon myriads of Mohammed's faithful ones</l>
<l>O'er whom this Empire folds a fostering wing,</l>
<l>That, whensoe'er to their last orisons</l>
<l>Life's last muezzin calls them, they be found</l>
<l>Starry with praise from prophet and from king!</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="34  TO AMERICA CONCERNING ENGLAND"/>

<div id="watson011" type="poem" n="11">

<head>TO AMERICA, CONCERNING<lb/>
ENGLAND</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>ART thou her child, born in the proud midday</l>
<l rend="inline">Of her large soul's abundance and excess,</l>
<l>Her daughter and her mightiest heritress,</l>
<l>Dowered with her thoughts, and lit on thy great way</l>
<l>By her great lamps that shine and fail not ? Yea!</l>
<l>And at this thunderous hour of struggle and stress,</l>
<l>Hither across the ocean wilderness</l>
<l>What word comes frozen on the frozen spray ?</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Neutrality!</hi>   The tiger from his den</l>
<l>Springs at thy mother's throat, and canst thou now</l>
<l>Watch with a stranger's gaze ?    So be it, then !</l>
<l>Thy loss is more than hers; for, bruised and torn,</l>
<l>She shall yet live without thine aid, and thou</l>
<l>Without the crown divine thou might'st have worn.</l></lg>
</div>


<pb n="YOU AT THE HELM   35"/>

<div id="watson012" type="poem" n="12">
<head>YOU AT THE  HELM</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>YOU at the helm of Empire, that with wise</l>
<l rend="inline"> Or fooUsh steersmanship her course control,</l>
<l>Where, if she 'scape not murderous reef and shoal,</l>
<l>She sinks in tempest, nevermore to rise--</l>
<l>'Tis yours to ope or shut a nation's eyes,</l>
<l>'Tis yours to feed or starve a people's soul,</l>
<l>To give as noble dues, or meanly dole</l>
<l>As niggard alms, the truth for which she cries.</l>
<l>She bade you be custodians of the light,</l>
<l>Not its extinguishers; and if she fall</l>
<l>Into a slumber of the heart or brain,</l>
<l>Because you stopped her ears and veiled her sight,</l>
<l>Then, though you come with trumpets, you may call</l>
<l>A too deep sleeper, and may call in vain.</l>
</lg>
</div>

<pb n="36  COMMEMORATIVE"/>

<div id="watson013" type="poem" n="13">
<head>COMMEMORATIVE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>NOW doth the Year, with gorgeous ritual, don</l>
<l rend="inline">Raiment  of priesthood, cope o'erlaid  with gold,</l>
<l>But soon, from autumn's purfled scarf unstoled,</l>
<l>The grey cowl of November must put on ;</l>
<l>And shaking the thinned locks that shall anon</l>
<l>Cumber his ways, he hears around him rolled</l>
<l>A nation's knell for Youth and Valour tolled,</l>
<l>Heroic Youth and knightly Valour, gone</l>
<l>Where, after clangorous day, is evenfall;</l>
<l>Love's <hi rend="italic">requiescat</hi> after battle's throes;</l>
<l>After the cannonade and bugle call,</l>
<l>Earth's whispered leave, <hi rend="italic">in pace</hi> to repose;</l>
<l>Lull after hurricane ; and crowning all,</l>
<l>Glory's white Uly after war's red rose.</l>
</lg>
</div>

<pb n="TO ROOSEVELT   37"/>

<div id="watson014" type="poem" n="14">
<head>TO  ROOSEVELT</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>HADST thou been sitting yet in Lincoln's chair,</l>
<l rend="inline">A different voice had pealed across the sea,</l>
<l>Another hand had struck a deeper key,</l>
<l>A larger note had pulsed upon the air.</l>
<l>Thou, in whose blood our Scotland hath a share--</l>
<l>As once on thine own soil august and free</l>
<l>Thyself didst not unproudly tell to me</l>
<l>'Mid talk of statecraft wise and songcraft fair--</l>
<l>Thou hadst  not  watched  our  throes  with breast supine,</l>
<l>Nor dost thou now, nor doth thy mighty land.</l>
<l>Something of her vast soul we understand,</l>
<l>And well we know, that in this hour malign,</l>
<l>Not human heart she lacks, but tongue divine,</l>
<l>To rouse the thunders lulled in her right hand.</l>
</lg>
</div>

<pb n="38  TO A WOULD-BE UMPIRE"/>

<div id="watson015" type="poem" n="15">
<head>TO A WOULD-BE UMPIRE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>GREAT Perseus babbled not of peace, while free</l>
<l rend="inline">To rend were still the Gorgon's talons.  Nor</l>
<l>Did wrathful Theseus, while the Minotaur</l>
<l>Took his red toll of white virginity,</l>
<l>Crave mediation. Glaucus' son, when he</l>
<l>Vanquished the triple-mouthed Chimæra for</l>
<l>The Lycians, reined not back his furious war</l>
<l>Till he had felled the monster's foreheads three.</l>
<l>Nor shall St. George of England stay his spear</l>
<l>In parley, while yon ravening Shape accurst</l>
<l>Ramps over Life and treads down arts and laws!</l>
<l>To you far westward we will give an ear,</l>
<l>Where sage and safe you sit; but hew we first</l>
<l>The dragon's teeth out of the dragon's jaws.</l>
</lg>
</div>



<pb n="CONDOLENCE    39"/>

<div id="watson016" type="poem" n="16">
<head>CONDOLENCE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>THE language wherein Goethe did record</l>
<l rend="inline">Wedlock of Christian Art with pagan Joy--</l>
<l>Of Faust with Helen, and Calvary with Troy--</l>
<l>That tongue I speak not; but at yon key-board,</l>
<l>Which is the grandchild of the harpsichord,</l>
<l>Rapt have I sat and listened from a boy,</l>
<l>While Schubert's, Schumann's gold without alloy</l>
<l>Flashed amid thunder, from my own hands poured.</l>
<l>Bach, his great coils by giant shuttles woven,</l>
<l>Companioned oft my youth ; and oft this soul</l>
<l>By Wagner's Siegfried-sword was pierced and cloven:</l>
<l>And with the sorrowing Earth would I condole,</l>
<l>Hearing Man's masterpiece of dissonance roll</l>
<l>From the same mighty breast that nursed Beethoven.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="40  DAS VOLK"/>

<div id="watson017" type="poem" n="17">
<head>DAS VOLK</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>WE did but smile, beholding the o'erfraught</l>
<l rend="inline">Sumpter, caparisoned and proud to appear</l>
<l>The snorting charger of a Cavalier</l>
<l>Whose joy was when his casque the sunbeam caught;</l>
<l>And half-amused we watched the packhorse taught</l>
<l>To caracole and curvet in the gear</l>
<l>Of battle, and bear, through an august career,</l>
<l>The paladin of a hundred fields unfought!</l>
<l>But when, full war-horse now, and plunging thus</l>
<l>About the innocent earth of France and Flanders,</l>
<l>He foams his fury's virulent overplus</l>
<l>On the ancient plains where rippling life meanders,</l>
<l>Not blameless quite, this new Bucephalus!</l>
<l>Not all the guilt, his would-be Alexander's!</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="THE DOMINANT THREE   41"/>

<div id="watson018" type="poem" n="18">
<head>THE DOMINANT THREE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>LIKE lordliest Day, that to each crannied rafter</l>
<l rend="inline">Of Life's great hall would pierce, was Goethe's Muse.</l>
<l>Like emerald twilight, when no heavenly dews</l>
<l>Assuage its bosom, Heine shimmered after</l>
<l>Heine, who flung himself with antic laughter,</l>
<l>In elfin armour of chameleon hues,</l>
<l>FuU on Philistia's never conquered thews,</l>
<l>The gates of Gaza, and the sons of Caphtur!</l>
<l>Then did unstarry night succeed to that</l>
<l>Rich-tinted dusk ; and no large, mastering strain,</l>
<l>No nightingale's incomparable pain,</l>
<l>Goldenly stormed the silence; but there sat</l>
<l>Nietzsche the loveless, like a vampire bat,</l>
<l>Malign on the broad breast of Allemaine.</l></lg>
</div>

<pb n="42  TO SIR JAMES"/>


<div id="watson019" type="poem" n="19">
<head>TO<lb/>
SIR JAMES  CRICHTON-BROWNE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>AROUND your northern home, where never cease</l>
<l rend="inline">The ebb and flow of Nith, whose waters glide</l>
<l>Rich with their memories of the Muse; whose tide,</l>
<l>In haunts of moorfowl and the wandering fleece,</l>
<l>Down by Caerlaverock beyond old Dumfries,</l>
<l>To Solway brings its dowry, like a bride;</l>
<l>There do the lowland mothers mourn with pride</l>
<l>The lowland sons, whom War hath lapped in Peace.</l>
<l>But you--be glad, be uplifted, seeing that what</l>
<l>Was great aforetime still disdains to fade ;</l>
<l>The spirit pervervid of the heroic Scot,</l>
<l>Its fire unlulled, and hardly in earth allayed:</l>
<l>The ancient native prowess unforgot,</l>
<l>Valour undrooped, and manhood undecayed.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="TO ONE FROM BEYOND  43"/>


<div id="watson020" type="poem" n="20">
<head>TO ONE FROM BEYOND HUMBER</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>ONE shire, our greatest in mere leagues of loam,</l>
<l rend="inline">And nowise least in all that makes life's wine</l>
<l>A ruddy and potent draught, is yours and mine:</l>
<l>One norland shire, our broad ancestral home.</l>
<l>There, where the Swale and Ure converging roam,</l>
<l>My own dim roots with the far Past entwine,</l>
<l>And yours are 'midst the Wolds that breathe the brine,</l>
<l>Odorous and acrid from the eastern foam.</l>
<l>Strong men did Yorkshire heretofore beget,</l>
<l>And stainless women ! And we who come of both</l>
<l>Have seen the valour of the dales leap high</l>
<l>In hearts unvanquishable, that kept their troth</l>
<l>With England, when Death cast for her his net</l>
<l>By land and sea, and from the insuUed sky.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="44  TO A SON OF WALES"/>


<div id="watson021" type="poem" n="21">
<head>TO  A SON  OF  WALES<lb/>
[<hi rend="italic">Owen Pritchard, Esq., M.D.</hi>]</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>SINCE first I saw your mountains long ago,</l>
<l rend="inline">Dark behind Conway's or Carnarvon's hold,</l>
<l>I have watched the Alps put on their evening gold,</l>
<l>And morning kindle peaks of Afric snow;</l>
<l>I have crossed Niagara's flood and Delaware's flow,</l>
<l>And loitered 'midst Italian vinelands old,</l>
<l>And visited isles which the far deeps enfold,</l>
<l>Where Spain is ashes and a sunset-glow.</l>
<l>But lovely as in youth are yet to me</l>
<l>Mona's bleak fields and Glaslyn's torrent wave;</l>
<l>And dearer now than ever their wild charm,</l>
<l>When hardy Wales pours forth her children free,</l>
<l>Hungering to aid her ancient Conqueror's arm</l>
<l>Lest Freedom's self reel to a blood-red grave.</l>
</lg>
</div>

<pb n="TO THE RIGHT HON.  45"/>

<div id="watson022" type="poem" n="22">

<head>TO THE RIGHT HON. SIR EDWARD CARSON, ON LEAVING ANTRIM, JUNE 30, 1916</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>THESE cUffs, the anvils of the hammering sea,</l>
<l rend="inline">You know them well ! These winds that sweep or swerve</l>
<l>O'er bays that have the sickle's gleam and curve,</l>
<l>They are Ulster's, and you fought to keep her free.</l>
<l>But now a greater claims you more than she,</l>
<l>Claims your strong  brain, clear speech, and virile nerve,</l>
<l>And best shall you the lesser mistress serve,</l>
<l>Serving the greater yet more vehemently,--</l>
<l>Her who demands, from souls of signal dower,</l>
<l>Amid the tempest that is not yet stayed,</l>
<l>No piecemeal service and no parcelled aid,</l>
<l>But their whole wealth of valour, zeal, and power,</l>
<l>Needing it all, and needing it each hour,</l>
<l>Till her vast adversary in dust be laid.</l>
</lg></div>



<pb n="46  TO THE RIGHT HON."/>

<div id="watson023" type="poem" n="23">

<head>THE THREE ALFREDS<ref target="wat23">1</ref></head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>THREE Alfreds let us honour. Him who drove</l>
<l rend="inline">His foes before the tempest of his blade</l>
<l>At Ethandune--him first, the all-glorious Shade,</l>
<l>The care-crowned King whose host with Guthrum strove.</l>
<l>Next--though a thousand years asunder clove</l>
<l>These twain--a lord of realms serenely swayed;</l>
<l>Victoria's golden warbler, him who made</l>
<l>Verse such as Virgil for Augustus wove.</l>
<l>Last--neither King nor bard, but just a man</l>
<l>Who, in the very whirlwind of our woe,</l>
<l>From midnight till the laggard dawn began,</l>
<l>Cried ceaseless, " Give us shells--more shells," and so</l>
<l>Saved England; saved her not less truly than</l>
<l>Her hero of heroes saved her long ago.</l></lg>

<note place="foot" id="wat23" n="1">Friends have asked the author not to re-publish this sonnet. He does so because he believes it to be the truth.</note>

</div>

<pb n="THE VOICE FROM THE SUNSET  47"/>

<div id="watson024" type="poem" n="24">

<head>THE  VOICE  FROM   THE  SUNSET</head>

<l>THERE came, from out the ocean porticoes</l>
<l rend="inline">Of that great ice-palace, Neutrality,</l>
<l>This far-blown word: " No difference do I see,</l>
<l>In aught they fight for, betwixt these and those."</l>
<l>O Puissance of the West! the whole world knows</l>
<l>Our enemy fights to bind, we fight to free.</l>
<l>Our aims are bared to the sun's scrutiny,</l>
<l>The noonday's inquest.  And if these our throes</l>
<l>Have no divineness, then all struggles known,</l>
<l>AU deeds embalmed and consecrated, all</l>
<l>Defying of powers that manacle and enthral,</l>
<l>From Hellas locked with Persia to your own</l>
<l>First mighty strife, have been but kennel-brawl,</l>
<l>And hubbub of the gutter round a bone.</l>
</div>



<pb n="48   AMERICA ONCE MORE"/>

<div id="watson025" type="poem" n="25">

<head>AMERICA ONCE MORE</head>

<l>THIS, this is the America that we knew!</l>
<l rend="inline"> Not she whose armour against Hell was reams</l>
<l>Of ratiocination ; who in streams</l>
<l>Of most invincible ink was lost to view ;</l>
<l>But she that once her golden clarion blew</l>
<l>At Gettysburg; she on whose forehead gleams</l>
<l>The   unvanquished   Morn;   the   America  of  our dreams--</l>
<l>Of those immortal dreams that yet are true.</l>
<l>O change not back to marble, mighty brow!</l>
<l>This human wrath is more majestic far,</l>
<l>Man needs thee, and our cause, being Man's, is thine.</l>
<l>Thy place is with the great who know not how</l>
<l>To falter, though their night be without star,</l>
<l>And their vast agony without anodyne.</l>
</div>



<pb n=""/>



<l>OTHER POEMS</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>


<div id="watson026" type="poem" n="26">
<head>CROSSING THE RUBICON</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>WHO draws to-day a traitor's sword ?</l>
<l rend="inline">Behold him stand, the Man Forsworn,</l>
<l>Him of the shameless, faithless word,</l>
<l rend="inline">The pledge disowned, the covenant torn,</l>
<l>Who prates of honour, truth and trust,</l>
<l>While he befouls them in the dust.</l>
</lg>


<lg type="stanza">
<l>When, to yon towers of hoary fame</l>
<l rend="inline">That Windsor lifts against the sky,</l>
<l>In martial cloak the Kaiser came,</l>
<l rend="inline">We did not dream it cloaked a spy ;</l>
<l>Yet there he sat, as now we know,</l>
<l>That basest thing, a guest and foe.</l>
</lg>


<lg type="stanza">
<l>France was a gallant foe and fair,</l>
<l rend="inline">That looked her enemies in the face,</l>
<l>With her proud eyes and freeborn air,</l>
<l rend="inline">And valour half-concealed in grace.</l>
<l>Noblest of all with whom we strove,</l>
<l>At last she gives us noble love.</l>
</lg>

<pb n="52            CROSSING THE  RUBICON"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>But he that took our proffered hand,</l>
<l rend="inline">Plotting to take our birthright too,</l>
<l>He, in this hospitable land,</l>
<l rend="inline">Bore him as only dastards do.</l>
<l>Here, where the Earth still nurtures men,</l>
<l>His hand shall soil not ours again.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Let us a League of Man proclaim,</l>
<l rend="inline">Against such knavery 'neath a crown</l>
<l>As rightly would be held to shame</l>
<l rend="inline">A swineherd and his fellow clown.</l>
<l>Shall all the loathsome creeping things</l>
<l>Find a last refuge araong Kings ?</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O you that wed your sword with ours</l>
<l rend="inline">To break his pride who mocks at laws,</l>
<l>You wear, 'mid yonder perjured Powers,</l>
<l rend="inline">The armour of a spotless cause.</l>
<l>Forward, in knightliest faith arrayed,</l>
<l>And Truth herself shaU whet your blade.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>From fields of peace, from citied shores,</l>
<l rend="inline">Where Neva to the Baltic runs,</l>
<l>Where Volga to the Caspian pours,</l>
<l rend="inline">You have not poured in vain your sons.</l>
<l>From lands of Loire and Rhône and Seine</l>
<l>You have not poured your sons in vain.</l>
</lg>


<pb n="CROSSING THE RUBICON            53"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Nor idly here, in this rough North,</l>
<l rend="inline">Hath she whose bosom is our home</l>
<l>Sounded her mandate speeding forth</l>
<l rend="inline">Our steps of thunder on the foam.</l>
<l>There, till the Thrones of Falsehood fall,</l>
<l>She guards the deeps that guard our all.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>There sitting by her old sea gate,</l>
<l rend="inline">Slow to be roused, slow to take fire,</l>
<l>And slow, being kindled, to abate</l>
<l rend="inline">The blast and volley of her ire,--</l>
<l>With grey brows catching from afar</l>
<l>The red flare of the torch of war,--</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Reluctant to the last, she throws</l>
<l rend="inline">Her doubts behind, bids dreams depart,</l>
<l>Shakes off the rust that in repose</l>
<l rend="inline">Had gathered round her iron heart,</l>
<l>In proud sad calm her anger clothes,</l>
<l>And leaps to embrace the fate she loathes.</l>
</lg>
</div>

<pb n="54   LI&#x00C8;GE"/>

<div id="watson027" type="poem" n="27">

<head>LI&#x00C8;GE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>BETWIXT the Foe and France was she--</l>
<l rend="inline">France the immortal, France the free.</l>
<l>The Foe, like one vast living sea,</l>
<l rend="inline">Drew nigh.</l>
<l>He dreamed that none his tide would stay;</l>
<l>But when he bade her to make way,</l>
<l>She, through her cannon, answered, " Nay,</l>
<l>Not I!"</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>No tremor and no fear she showed:</l>
<l>She held the pass, she barred the road,</l>
<l>While Death's unsleeping feet bestrode</l>
<l rend="inline">The ground.</l>
<l>So long as deeds of noblest worth</l>
<l>Are sung with joy, and tears, and mirth,</l>
<l>Her glory shall to the ends of the Earth</l> 
<l rend="inline">Resound.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Watched by a world that yearned to aid,</l>
<l>Lonely she stood but undismayed.</l>
<l>Resplendent was the part she played,</l>
<l rend="inline">And pure.</l>


<pb n="LI&#x00C8;GE                        55"/>

<l>Praised be her heroes, proud her sons !</l>
<l>She threw her soul into the guns.</l>
<l>Her name shall, with the loveliest ones,</l>
<l rend="inline">Endure.</l></lg>
</div>


<pb n="56   THE HARVEST MOON"/>

<div id="watson028" type="poem" n="28">

<head>THE HARVEST MOON</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>WITH swords agleam and guns aflame--</l>
<l rend="inline">In troop and squadron and platoon--</l>
<l>At harvest-home the Reapers came,</l>
<l rend="inline">Under the waning harvest moon.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Their sickle neither paused at Dark,</l>
<l rend="inline">Nor idled in the fervent noon :</l>
<l>Their sheaves lay livid, cold, and stark,</l>
<l rend="inline">Under the dwindling harvest moon.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Benignly, without stint or dearth,</l>
<l rend="inline">Nature had given her annual boon,</l>
<l>And crowned with gold the feastful Earth,</l>
<l rend="inline">Under the golden harvest moon.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Man only--learning, all too well,</l>
<l rend="inline">Her deadlier secrets bared too soon--</l>
<l>Poured, from new phials, old Death and Hell,</l>
<l rend="inline">Under the dying harvest moon.</l>
</lg></div>



<pb n="THE SOUL OF ROUGET DE LISLE   57"/>

<div id="watson029" type="poem" n="29">

<head>THE SOUL OF ROUGET DE LISLE</head>

<l>[Verses founded on an early încident ofthe War]</l>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>THEIR arms shall conquer--to victory led</l>
<l rend="inline">By a voice like a trumpet's peal;</l>
<l>For a great Ghost marches at their head--</l>
<l rend="inline">The Soul of Rouget de Lisle.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>He gave them the Song that cannot die</l>
<l rend="inline">Till the world's heart cease to feel;</l>
<l>And they go into battle captain'd by</l>
<l rend="inline">The Soul of Rouget de Lisle.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Not for the first time--not for the last--</l>
<l rend="inline">Does an enemy waver and reel</l>
<l>Before the eternal clarion blast</l>
<l rend="inline">From the Soul of Rouget de Lisle.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>For this is the Song shall break the power</l>
<l rend="inline">That bids men grovel and kneel--</l>
<l>The Song that was born of a mighty hour</l>
<l rend="inline">In the Soul of Rouget de Lisle.</l>
</lg>

<pb n="58   THE SOUL OF ROUGET DE LISLE"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And its music fires the booming gun</l>
<l rend="inline">And edges the gleaming steel,</l>
<l>For the Soul of France herself is one</l>
<l rend="inline">With the Soul of Rouget de Lisle.</l>
</lg></div>


<pb n="THE BATTLE OF THE BIGHT"/>

<div id="watson030" type="poem" n="30">

<head>THE  BATTLE OF THE  BIGHT</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>HAD I that fabled herb</l>
<l rend="inline">Which brought to life the dead,</l>
<l>Whom would I dare disturb</l>
<l rend="inline">In his eternal bed ?</l>
<l>Great GrenviUe would I wake,</l>
<l>And with glad tidings make</l>
<l>The soul of mighty Drake</l>
<l rend="inline">Upheave a glorying head.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>As rose the misty sun,</l>
<l rend="inline">Our men the North Sea scanned,</l>
<l>And each rejoicing gun</l>
<l rend="inline">Welcomed a foe at hand,</l>
<l>Eager, with thunderous throat,</l>
<l>To sound, for all afloat,</l>
<l>The world-awakening note</l>
<l rend="inline">The world can understand.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>For ev'n as birds of night,</l>
<l rend="inline">Hoary and tawny owl,</l>
<l>Do sometimes brave the light,</l>
<l rend="inline">Like bolder, nobler fowl,</l>


<pb n="60       THE  BATTLE  OF THE  BIGHT"/>

<l>So did the foe that day</l>
<l>Come venturing forth for prey,</l>
<l>Where, on the ocean way,</l>
<l rend="inline">Our ocean watchdogs prowl.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>But brief and plain, 'mid men</l>
<l rend="inline">Not born to yield or flee,</l>
<l>Our cannon spoke out then</l>
<l rend="inline">The speech that keeps us free,</l>
<l>And battered, with hoarse boom,</l>
<l>Four warships to their doom,</l>
<l>While one, to a fiercer tomb,</l>
<l rend="inline">Fled blazing down the sea.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Sleep on, O Drake, sleep well,</l>
<l rend="inline">In days not wholly dire!</l>
<l>Grenville, whom nought could quell,</l>
<l rend="inline">Unquenched is still thy fire.</l>
<l>And thou that hadst no peer,</l>
<l>Nelson, thou need'st not fear!</l>
<l>Thy sons and heirs are here,</l>
<l rend="inline">And shall not shame their sire.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="VERITAS VICTRIX   61"/>

<div id="watson031" type="poem" n="31">

<head>VERITAS VICTRIX</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>THE Mill of Lies is loud,</l>
<l rend="inline">Whose overseer, Germania's Over-lord,</l>
<l>Hath overmuch adored</l>
<l>The Over-sword,</l>
<l>And shall be overthrown, with the overproud.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Praised be the overwatching Heavens, that though</l>
<l>Falsehood her blare of brass may pitch yet higher,</l>
<l>Truth hath her trumpets also, and these of gold,</l>
<l>And she can blow</l>
<l>Longer than any liar,</l>
<l>Fronting the sun, high on her mountains old.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="62  THE CHARGE OF THE 9TH LANCERS"/>

<div id="watson032" type="poem" n="32">

<head>THE CHARGE OF THE<lb/>
9TH LANCERS</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>MELINITE, lyddite, darkened heaven,</l>
<l rend="inline"> But straight at the guns the Lancers rode</l>
<l>By the light of the rage that in them glowed--</l>
<l>Straight at the guns, the deadly Eleven</l>
<l>That had raked and shelled them seven times seven.</l>
<l>With never a halt or a needless word--</l>
<l>With never a screen from the shattering breath</l>
<l>Of a myriad iron throats of death--</l>
<l>At the cannon in ambush our horsemen spurred,</l>
<l>Fiercely, grimly--their fathers' sons--</l>
<l>And slew the gunners beside their guns,</l>
<l>And captured the cannon, the roaring Eleven,</l>
<l>That deafened the earth and darkened the heaven.</l>
<l>Then their dauntless remnant came</l>
<l>Out of the hurricane, out of the flame,</l>
<l>Covered with smoke and dust and fame.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Shout, you shires, with a chorus sent</l>
<l>Ringing from Caithness right to Kent,</l>
<l>From far Northumberland down past Devon!</l>


<pb n="THE CHARGE OF THE 9TH LANCERS   63"/>

<l>Shout for your heroes, Britain's sons,</l>
<l>Who stifled the breath of the thundering guns.</l>
<l>The courage that lifted their hearts shall leaven</l>
<l>AU who go forth in England's name,</l>
<l>Born to o'ercome as these o'ercame,</l>
<l>And winnow the earth with the flail of Heaven.</l>
</lg>
</div>

<pb n="64  RHEIMS"/>

<div id="watson032" type="poem" n="32">

<head>RHEIMS</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>GREAT Lord of Rapine, on this fane you trod</l>
<l rend="inline">With mighty foot.   The mightier foot of God</l>
<l>Shall spurn you sprawUng down His minster stair</l>
<l>To Infamy's crypt, and leave you gibbering there.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n="THE FIGHTING FIVE"/>

<div id="watson033" type="poem" n="33">

<head>THE FIGHTING FIVE</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>WHERE the waves are as chargers that curvet and prance,</l>
<l>And toss their white manes in retreat or advance,</l>
<l>The Lennox, the Legion, the Loyal, the Lance,</l>
<l rend="inline">Went forth with the cmiser Undaunted.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The foe, he was brave--let us give him his dues;</l>
<l>For Britons they are not who basely refuse</l>
<l>A gallant salute to an enemy's crews</l>
<l rend="inline">That with cowardice cannot be taunted.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>But they who are brave in a cause that is ill</l>
<l>Have Heav'n for a foe that o'ermatches them still,</l>
<l>And vainly they lavish their valour and skill,</l>
<l rend="inline">And idly their prowess is vaunted.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Their squadron, it opened like hosts that deploy,</l>
<l>And fain had embraced us but found us too coy,</l>
<l>And we sank their Destroyers that could not destroy,</l>
<l rend="inline">And we humbled the flag that they flaunted.</l>
</lg>



<pb n="66            THE FIGHTING FIVE"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Then, back as from pastime, returned without boasts</l>
<l>Our wonderful tars to our worshipping coasts,</l>
<l>O'er the sea that, from age unto age, by the ghosts</l>
<l rend="inline">Of our fathers the Sea-Kings is haunted.</l></lg>
</div>


<pb n="A PLACE IN THE SUN    67"/>


<div id="watson034" type="poem" n="34">

<head>"A  PLACE  IN  THE  SUN"</head>

<p>[Mr. Frederic Harrison has made the suggestion that Devil's Island would be an appropriate residence for the German Emperor after the war.]</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>YES, there, if he ever be captured,</l>
<l rend="inline">Let him live, well laid by the heel,</l>
<l>And become, to a world enraptured,</l>
<l rend="inline">Le diable l&#x00E0;-bas dans l'île.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>When Europe has washed off <hi rend="italic">his</hi> mark,</l>
<l rend="inline">Who stabbed her with poisoned steel,</l>
<l>Let him sigh for a Moltke and Bismarck--</l>
<l rend="inline">Le diable, l&#x00E0;-bas dans l'île.</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Last product of German Culture,</l>
<l rend="inline">There leave him, to make a meal</l>
<l>For some not too dainty vulture--</l>
<l>Le diable--l&#x00E0;-bas--dans l'île.</l>
</lg>
</div>


<pb n=""/>



<l>THE  FIELDS  OF  THE  FUTURE</l>

<l>'T^HOUGH gone the ancient gear of War—though</l>
<l>-■-          men</l>

<l>Fight  not   with   axe,  and   mace,  and   clanging</l>
<l>targe—</l>
<l>StiU does the ancient war-rage goad them, when</l>
<l>The bugles sound a charge.</l>

<l>To that primæval passion may we yet</l>

<l>Give ampler range, in fields of vaster marge !</l>

<l>'Gainst War itself, when this war passes, let</l>
<l>Our bugles sound a charge.</l>





<l>68</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>WHO  WAS  THE AGGRESSOR?</l>

<l>TF two men feU to fighting, of whom one</l>

<l>-*-    Carried, that day, no ready weapon, save</l>

<l>Only an oaken stave,</l>

<l>While the other gUttered in the summer sun</l>

<l>With casque and corselet, lance and whetted glaive,</l>

<l>By which of these would aU but fool or knave</l>

<l>Adjudge the combat to have been begun ?</l>





<l>69</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>A FALSE PROPHET</l>

<l>T TE gradged the gold that sparingly we spent</l>
<l>-*- -■-    To keep this citadel of freedom free.</l>
<l>He bade us heed not arms and armament,</l>
<l>But go unpanopUed on land and sea.</l>

<l>Each week, a dismal joy to fools and bUnd,</l>

<l>His ink-streams gushed, and with duU violence</l>
<l>flowed.</l>
<l>And he knew aU things—Wisdom in his mind</l>
<l>Building notoriously her sole abode.</l>

<l>Ah weU, his day departs!    He is swept aside,</l>
<l>A thin and charmless voice that rails unheard.</l>

<l>And now let charitable obUvion hide</l>
<l>His name in dust, not to be disinterred.</l>





<l>70</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>DESOLATION</l>

<l>OUT of the gutters and slums of HeU—</l>
<l>Disgorged from the vast infernal sewer-</l>
<l>Vomited forth from a world where dweU</l>
<l>Childhood, maidenhood, wifehood pure—</l>
<l>She arose and towered on earth and sea,</l>
<l>Clothed in her green putridity,</l>
<l>She arose refreshed from a bUssful dream</l>
<l>Of anguished age and ravished youth,</l>
<l>And innocence racked with woe extreme:</l>
<l>She arose to make the dream a truth,</l>
<l>And there where storied rivers ran,</l>
<l>And the roots of cities were deep in time,</l>
<l>And the ages pealed a meUow chime,</l>
<l>And the rapt and kneeUng spirit of man</l>
<l>Had Ufted far above dust and mire</l>
<l>Adoring turret and suppUant spire,</l>
<l>Her royal progress at last began.</l>
<l>For the daughter of oíFal, the sister obscene</l>
<l>Of whatever on earth is most unclean,</l>
<l>The spawning mother of nameless things,</l>
<l>Rode forth in a chariot drawn by Kings,</l>
<l>71</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>72                          DESOLATION</l>

<l>And herself by Kings was hailed a Queen.</l>

<l>She wafted, to east and west and south,</l>

<l>Miasma foul, malaria feU,</l>

<l>The carrion reek of her loathsome mouth,</l>

<l>The breath of the gutters and slums of HeU.</l>

<l>She beckoned the vulture poised in air ;</l>

<l>He had long been stinted of dainties rare ;</l>

<l>He was lean with famine and hoarse with drouth;</l>

<l>She promised him rich and sumptuous fare.</l>

<l>And around her she gathered many a Shape</l>

<l>That now seemed man and anon seemed ape,</l>

<l>And at heart was a dragon loosed from its lair.</l>

<l>The things of beak and talon and maw,</l>

<l>The creatures that know but one red law,</l>

<l>They lagged not afar, they were not slack</l>

<l>To answer her summons and foUow her track ;</l>

<l>And with hands of havoc she came to lay</l>

<l>Old Art and Learning in ashes gray;</l>

<l>She came to burn, she came to sack,</l>

<l>She came to devour, deflower, and slay.</l>

<l>She came to stretch aU Ufe on the rack,</l>

<l>And hath she a peer or a feUow ?    Nay !</l>

<l>The jungle's ambushed mouths of prey,</l>

<l>Beside her savagery, what are they ?</l>

<l>Ounce and pard and panther lack</l>

<l>The ensanguined lust that reddens her way.</l>

<l>Their fury stops where the breakers play,</l>

<l>But hers neither land nor sea can stay,</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>DESOLATION                        73</l>

<l>And at deaths of lovers 'mid ocean-wrack</l>

<l>Her soul makes merry, her heart is gay.</l>

<l>O to behold her in sick dismay,</l>

<l>By a hurricane Nemesis buffêted back</l>

<l>On a ravaging plague-wind tempest-black,</l>

<l>And the hounds of vengeance, a raging pack,</l>

<l>At the heels of their quarry with jubilant bay ;</l>

<l>Hunting her out of the Ught of day</l>

<l>And into the pit she graced fuU weU;</l>

<l>Out of the world where children play,</l>

<l>Back to the gutters and slums of HeU!</l>





<l>10</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE  HALF-MAN</l>

<l>OPARING not age, sparing not youth,</l>
<l>^    They tore their way with wolfish tooth</l>
<l>Through human homes, through human hopes</l>
<l>Not men, not men, but lycanthropes !</l>

<l>Thus do the fabled monsters rear</l>
<l>Their heads anew; thus reappear</l>
<l>Old Shapes that freeze us and appal;</l>
<l>And the Half-Man is worst of aU.</l>





<l>74</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>KULTUR:   A DIALOGUE</l>

<l>Staff Officer.</l>
<l>Highness, yon babe his popgun fired,</l>

<l>Crown Prince.</l>
<l>No further pretext is required,</l>
<l>On, my brave Guards, and in God's name</l>
<l>Give old and young to sword and flame.</l>





<l>75</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>AN  EARNEST PETITION</l>

<l>|?REE Trade—let sager wits than mine debate</l>
<l>-■-       Whether it salve, whether it wound the State ;</l>

<l>But when I see our Foe fed early and late</l>

<l>On each new, flattering Ue,</l>

<l>Then, of the Powers that mercifuUy give</l>

<l>Or mercifuUy deny,</l>

<l>I ask a boon : for Free Truth then I cry !</l>

<l>With chartered poverty's prerogative</l>

<l>I haunt Heaven's ear, and clamour—while I wait</l>

<l>A beggar at its gate—</l>

<l>" Rather than be as these who darkUng Uve,</l>

<l>lUumined let me die,"</l>





<l>76</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>NURSE  CAVELL</l>

<l>WHEN that most false evangel ever yet</l>
<l>Proclaimed with souUess voice from shore to</l>
<l>shore—</l>
<l>The gospel of Blood and Iron—shaU have met</l>
<l>Its doom, and be no more;</l>

<l>This woman's Iron courage shaU resound</l>
<l>Above aU fame the gloating sword confers;</l>

<l>This woman's Blood shaU cry out of the ground</l>
<l>Against her Murderers,</l>





<l>77</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE YEAR'S  RETROSPECT</l>

<l>WHAT was the lark to the zenith upspringing</l>
<l>for?</l>
<l>What was he babbUng as summer drew near ?</l>
<l>What were the beU-ringers goldenly ringing for ?</l>
<l>What was the heart of aU maidenhood singing for ?</l>
<l>Love, love, love, at the gush of the year.</l>

<l>What was the arm of the warrior smiting for ?</l>

<l>What could it be that he held it so dear ?</l>
<l>What were the far-parted nations uniting for ?</l>
<l>What were the thrones and the satrapies fighting for ?</l>

<l>Life, Ufe, Ufe, through the surge of the year.</l>

<l>What are the bride's and the mother's eyes weUing for,</l>
<l>Now when the dayUght is niggard and drear ?</l>

<l>What is the hush in the desolate dweUing for ?</l>

<l>What is the toUing and what is the kneUing for ?</l>
<l>Death, death, death, 'mid the lees of the year.</l>

<l>Love that was baulked of the heaven it was sighing</l>
<l>for—</l>
<l>Life that was feUed ere a leaf had turned sere—</l>
<l>What have they left that is worthy our dying for ?</l>
<l>Vengeance, which earth and the deep seas are crying</l>
<l>for,</l>
<l>Round the last flare of the pyre of the year.</l>

<l>78</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE  STARVED LION</l>

<l>TIT'HEREFORE with barking mouths abuse</l>

<l>' *      The hands that dole our " doctored " news ?</l>
<l>Is it not time there rose once more</l>
<l>That nobler sound—the Uon's roar ?</l>





<l>England, thou art a Uon yet!</l>
<l>What meals are these before thee set ?</l>
<l>Stale morsels—no fit fare for thee—</l>
<l>And cooked besides !    Oh, canst thou be</l>
<l>Content to famish—late and soon</l>
<l>Fed Uke an infant with a spoon ?</l>

<l>Lion that ne'er didst loose in vain</l>
<l>The tempests of thy tangled mane,—</l>
<l>If thou would'st shake but one lone note</l>
<l>Of the ancient thunder from thy throat</l>
<l>On these who wrong thee, where were they ?</l>
<l>That blast would wither them away.</l>





<l>79</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>DUTY</l>

<l>/^ IVE gladly, you rich—'tis no more than you</l>

<l>^^         owe—</l>

<l>For the weal of your Country, your wealth's over-</l>

<l>flow !</l>
<l>Even I that am poor am performing my part;</l>
<l>I am giving my brain, I am giving my heart.</l>





<l>80</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>CERES AND  BELLONA</l>

<l>'T^HE cornfield to the battlefield</l>
<l>-*-     Said, " Lo, my fruits, how fair!</l>
<l>Pain, and pain only, thou dost yield:</l>
<l>Peace—only peace—I bear."</l>

<l>" False," said the battlefield, " thy claim !</l>

<l>For when War's boUs fly free,</l>
<l>The warrior's thew, the warrior's frame,</l>

<l>Whence are they but from thee ?</l>

<l>" Thou art the thrust of steel right home,</l>

<l>ITiou art the cannon's blast,</l>
<l>The fangs of heU and aU their foam !</l>

<l>Yea, know thyself at last! "</l>

<l>The sickle gUttered in night's noon,</l>
<l>A sword that hews and cleaves!</l>

<l>And that great shield, the golden moon,</l>
<l>Hung 'mid the golden sheaves.</l>





<l>11                        81</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE YELLOW  PANSY</l>

<l>''There's pansies—that's for thoughts."—Shakespeare.</l>

<l>"Y^ riNTER   had   swooped,  a  lean   and   hungry</l>
<l>^ *         hawk;</l>

<l>It seemed an age since summer was entombed;</l>
<l>Yet in our garden, on its frozen stalk,</l>

<l>A yeUow pansy bloomed.</l>

<l>'Twas Nature saying by trope and metaphor :</l>
<l>" Behold, when empire against empire strives,</l>

<l>Though aU else perish, ground 'neath iron war,</l>
<l>The golden thought survives."</l>





<l>82</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>O'</l>





<l>THE  KAISER'S  DIRGE</l>

<l>Verses for the obsequies ofthe Emperor Wilhelm II</l>

<l>l</l>

<l>kNE boon—'tis the best—</l>
<l>O Earth, we implore !</l>
<l>We bring thee a guest:</l>
<l>Unbar thy door.</l>

<l>O Earth, over whom</l>

<l>His plough drove red,</l>
<l>Deny not a room,</l>

<l>Refuse not a bed.</l>

<l>Dark Mother, whose breast</l>
<l>With his harrow he tore—</l>

<l>Ev'n to this guest</l>
<l>Unbar thy door.</l>

<l>II</l>

<l>Spectres of woe,</l>

<l>His victims aU—</l>
<l>Slow—slow—</l>

<l>FoUow the paU.</l>

<l>Childhood, that wast</l>

<l>In his shambles slain,</l>
<l>FoUow the vast</l>

<l>Funereal train.</l>
<l>83</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>84                THE  KAISER'S  DIRGE</l>

<l>Youth defiled—</l>
<l>Widowhood wan-</l>

<l>FoUow the wild</l>
<l>Cortége on.</l>

<l>III</l>

<l>Thundering di'ums,</l>

<l>TeU it afar!</l>
<l>In peace he comes</l>

<l>Who was Lord of War.</l>

<l>Piercing fife</l>

<l>And clamorous brass—</l>
<l>CaU to aU Ufe</l>

<l>To see him pass !</l>

<l>For he comes with sound</l>
<l>Of pawing steeds;</l>

<l>With aroma crowned</l>
<l>Of his odorous deeds ;</l>

<l>Borne to his bed</l>
<l>With escort due—</l>

<l>A miUion dead</l>
<l>For his retinue.</l>

<l>IV</l>

<l>Carnage, whose brows</l>
<l>Beetle o'er HeU,</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>THE KAISER'S DIRGE               85</l>

<l>Here is thy spouse,</l>
<l>Cherish him weU.</l>

<l>Lust-in-Hate,</l>

<l>With thy fangs aU foam—</l>
<l>O hail thy mate,</l>

<l>O welcome him home.</l>

<l>And thou first of aU spies</l>

<l>This earth to o'errun,</l>
<l>Father of Lies,</l>

<l>Receive thy son,</l>

<l>V</l>

<l>Now, to plumed hearse</l>

<l>And balsam'd shroud,</l>
<l>Bring proud verse,</l>

<l>Worthy the proud:</l>

<l>Garland august</l>

<l>To the catafalque bring,</l>
<l>Rich as the dust</l>

<l>Of the heart of a King,</l>

<l>And in high-reared pride,</l>

<l>On a summit untrod—</l>
<l>Where is nothing beside</l>

<l>But the gaze of God—</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>86                THE  KAISER'S DIRGE</l>

<l>From lands hate-riven</l>
<l>Let a cenotaph cUmb</l>

<l>To the hateless Heaven</l>
<l>That leans o'er Time ;</l>

<l>And grave it with none</l>
<l>Of man's words but twain</l>

<l>Luútania one—</l>
<l>And one, Louvain.</l>

<l>VI</l>

<l>Fashion his bed</l>

<l>Deep, deep;</l>
<l>Earth o'er his head</l>

<l>Heap, heap:</l>

<l>Load upon load</l>
<l>Let him not lack,</l>

<l>Lest his abode</l>
<l>Vomit him back.</l>

<l>Here are his court,</l>
<l>Empire, and crown:</l>

<l>Rites be short,</l>
<l>Lower him down.</l>

<l>Conquering Spade,</l>

<l>Cover him o'er.</l>
<l>He shaU invade</l>

<l>Life no more.</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>RECRUITING VERSE</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>



<l>SONS  OF BRITAIN</l>

<l>SONS of her who keeps her faith unbroken,</l>
<l>Her who gave you might of Umb and nerve,</l>
<l>Her whose service—be it devoutly spoken—</l>
<l>Perfect freedom is, for aU who serve :</l>





<l>Her who gave you dower of iron sinew,</l>

<l>Her who made you strong and fleet and brave-</l>

<l>Give her aU the manhood that is in you :</l>
<l>'Tis the royal gift her own hands gave.</l>





<l>England's safety—England's dearer honour—</l>
<l>Both forbid that you should halt and wait</l>

<l>TiU the enemy be indeed upon her,</l>

<l>He who vaunts and flaunts him at her gate.</l>





<l>Heed^not overmuch when she is slandered;</l>

<l>Yours to guard her from a BuUy's blow :</l>
<l>Yours to rise, and raUy to her standard:</l>

<l>Yours to arm, and face the brutal foe.</l>
<l>12                       89</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>90                  SONS OF BRITAIN</l>

<l>Would you sit at home, and watch and ponder,</l>
<l>While the warriors agonise and dare ?</l>

<l>Here for you is shame, but glory yonder:</l>
<l>Choose the glory—yea, a hero's share.</l>

<l>Then, though darksome be the hour, and grievous,</l>
<l>You shaU make it great and splendid too,</l>

<l>And her love who bore and did conceive us</l>
<l>ShaU for ever crown your deeds and you.</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>KINDRED</l>

<l>COME AustraUa, come New Zealand-</l>
<l>Canada, with heart of gold,</l>
<l>Come and help to keep this free land</l>
<l>Free for ever as of old.</l>





<l>Hangs her fortune in the balance,</l>
<l>Mighty is her foe and fierce.</l>

<l>Help to pmne his Eagle's talons</l>
<l>Ere its beak her bosom pierce.</l>





<l>Yonder rants the lord of legions,</l>
<l>False of heart as you are true,</l>

<l>You as weU, O younger regions,</l>
<l>He has lusted to subdue.</l>





<l>Not alone shaU we Ue cloven</l>
<l>If he scale our iron waU.</l>

<l>With our fate is Yours inwoven,</l>
<l>And as one we stand or faU.</l>
<l>91</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>92                           KINDRED</l>

<l>Fain would he ride ruthless o'er us,</l>
<l>Strong in Wrong, with hoof abhorred.</l>

<l>Strong in Right is She that bore us—</l>
<l>Make her stronger with your sword.</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>AWAKE!</l>

<l>T^EATH hunts for us beneath the seas,</l>
<l>-*—^    Death hawks at us amidst the air.</l>
<l>Awake, O slumberers luUed in ease !</l>
<l>Up and prepare!</l>





<l>ShaU England bow her head at last,</l>

<l>The badge of vassalage to wear ?</l>
<l>Awake—the hour for sleep is past;</l>
<l>Up and prepare!</l>





<l>Know you what fate on Belgium feU,</l>

<l>You that have wives and daughters fair ?</l>
<l>ShaU they, too, feed the lusts of HeU ?</l>
<l>Up and prepare!</l>





<l>What sound is this that rises o'er</l>

<l>The squadron's tramp, the bugle's blare ?</l>
<l>'Tis Doom, knocking at England's door !</l>
<l>Up and prepare!</l>
<l>93</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>94                               AWAKE!</l>

<l>Arm as your sires were proud to arm,</l>
<l>Dare as your brothers yonder dare!</l>
<l>In mart and mine and forge and farm,</l>
<l>Up and prepare!</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>OUR MEN</l>

<l>OUR men, they are our stronghold,</l>
<l>Our bastioned waU unscaled,</l>
<l>Who, against Hate and Wrong, hold</l>

<l>This Realm that never quailed ;</l>
<l>Who bear the noblést burden</l>

<l>Life lays on shoulders broad,</l>
<l>Asking not fame or guerdon,</l>
<l>Asking not gold or laud.</l>

<l>They go where England speeds them ;</l>

<l>They laugh and jest at Fate.</l>
<l>They go where England needs them,</l>

<l>And dream not they are great,</l>
<l>And oft, 'mid smoke and smother</l>

<l>By bUnding warstorm fanned,</l>
<l>Sons of our mighty Mother,</l>

<l>They faU that she may stand,</l>

<l>Our sailors, save when sleepiug</l>

<l>The Ught sleep of the sea,</l>
<l>Their ancient watch are keeping,</l>

<l>Mother, for thine and thee!</l>
<l>95</l>



<pb n=""/>



<l>96                             OUR MEN</l>

<l>They guard thy maiden daughters</l>
<l>From worse than death or pain ;</l>

<l>The men who ward the waters,</l>
<l>The men who man the main,</l>

<l>When navies meet and wrestle,</l>

<l>And their vast arms strike home-</l>
<l>Vessel \\ ith monstrous vessel</l>

<l>Matched on the flame-Ut foam—</l>
<l>What fleet returns in glory ?</l>

<l>What fleet makes haste to fly ?</l>
<l>O Sea, that knowest our storv,</l>

<l>Thou, thou canst best reply !</l>

<l>Then hail to aU who gave us</l>

<l>Their might of arm and soul,</l>
<l>Hot and athirst to save us,</l>

<l>To heal, and keep us whole ;</l>
<l>Whether they serve where yonder</l>

<l>Far-burrowing trenches run,</l>
<l>Or where the ocean thunder</l>

<l>Peals with the thundering gun.</l>





<l>Pimted hy HarMl, ^Vaíson &amp; Yinty, Ld., London and AyUthvry, EngU</l>



<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

<pb n=""/>

