<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Volunteer and Other Poems: Electronic Edition</title>
            <author><name type="person" reg="Asquith, Herbert">Herbert Asquith</name></author>
         </titleStmt>
	 <publicationStmt>
	   <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic Collections
	   and Services, Emory University</publisher>
	   <pubPlace>Atlanta, GA</pubPlace>
	   <address>
	     <addrLine>540 Asbury Circle</addrLine>
	     <addrLine>Woodruff Library</addrLine>
	     <addrLine>Atlanta, GA 30322</addrLine>
	   </address>
	   <availability><p>&#x00A9;Emory University. Permission is
	   granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce,
	   distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
	   by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
	   provided this header is included in its entirety.  For
	   inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Institute
	   for Jewish Studies, Emory University, Atlanta GA 30322 or
	   the Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic Collections and
	   Services, Woodruff Library, Emory University, Atlanta,
	   Georgia 30322 </p></availability> 
	   <date>2004</date>
	 </publicationStmt>
	 <seriesStmt>
	   <title>The Great War</title>
	 </seriesStmt>
	 <notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
	     <title>The Volunteer and Other Poems</title>
	     <author>Herbert Asquith</author>
	     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
	     <publisher>Sidgwick &#x0026; Jackson</publisher>
	     <date>1917</date>
	   </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
	<projectDesc><p>Poetry contemporary to World War I (the Great
	War) has been digitized by OCR or rekeying. The work has been
	done in conjunction with Dr. Harry Rusche of the English
	Department, Emory University</p></projectDesc>
	<tagsDecl>
	  <rendition id="quote">Paragraphs including q or quote
	  elements indicate material that is in a block
	  quote.</rendition>
	  <rendition id="title">Where the title of a work is
	  italicized, it is marked with a title element, both in the
	  text and in footnotes.</rendition>
	  <tagUsage gi="q" render="quote">blockquote</tagUsage>
	  <tagUsage gi="quote" render="quote">blockquote</tagUsage>
	  <tagUsage gi="title" render="title">italic</tagUsage>
	</tagsDecl>
	<refsDecl><p>The page numbers of the volumes are indicated by
	page break elements</p>
	<p></p>
	</refsDecl>
	<classDecl>
	  <taxonomy id="lcsh">
	    <bibl>
	      <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
	    </bibl>
	  </taxonomy>
	</classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
	   <rs type="collection">poetry</rs>
	   <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs>
            <rs type="form">Unedited</rs>
            <rs type="genre">Poetry</rs>
            <rs type="geography">Great Britain</rs>
            <date>1900-1999</date>
         </creation>
	 <textClass>
	   <keywords scheme="lcsh">
	     <list>
	       <item>World War, 1914-1918--Poetry.</item>
	       <item>English poetry--20th Century.</item>
	       <item>War.</item>
	     </list>
	   </keywords>
	 </textClass></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!-- add your information here -->
	<change>
	  <date>2004</date>
	  <respStmt>
	    <name>Josh Klehr</name>
	    <resp>Beck Center staff</resp>
	  </respStmt>
	    <item>encoded according to TEI encoding guidelines</item>
	</change>
	<change>
	  <date>2004</date>
	  <respStmt>
	    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
	    <resp>Beck Center Staff</resp>
	  </respStmt>
	  <item>Header added. Encoding corrected.</item>
	</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div id="asquith01" type="anthology" n ="The Volunteer And Other Poems">
   <docAuthor n="Asquith, Herbert">Herbert Asquith</docAuthor>
   <head>The Volunteer And Other Poems</head>
   <docDate>1917</docDate>
   <bibl>London: Sidgwick &#x0026; Jackson.</bibl>

<div id="asquith02" type="poem" n="The Volunteer">
<head rend="center">THE VOLUNTEER</head>

<lg><l n="1">HERE lies a clerk who half his life had spent</l>
<l>Toiling at ledgers in a city grey, </l>
<l>Thinking that so his days would drift away</l>
<l>With no lance broken in life's tournament </l>
<l>Yet ever 'twixt the books and his bright eyes </l>
<l>The gleaming eagles of the legions came, </l>
<l>And horsemen, charging under phantom skies, </l>
<l>Went thundering past beneath the oriflamme.</l></lg>

<lg><l>And now those waiting dreams are satisfied </l>
<l>From twilight to the halls of dawn he went; </l>
<l>His lance is broken; but he lies content</l>
<l>With that high hour, in which he lived and died. </l>
<l>And falling thus, he wants no recompense, </l>
<l>Who found his battle in the last resort </l>
<l>Nor needs he any hearse to bear him hence, </l>
<l>Who goes to join the men of Agincourt.<pb n="10"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith03" type="poem" n="War's Cataract, 1915">
<head rend="center">WAR'S CATARACT, 1915</head>

<lg><l n="1">In this red havoc of the patient earth,</l>
<l>Though higher yet the tide of battle rise,</l>
<l>Now has the hero cast away disguise,</l>
<l>And out of the ruin splendor comes to birth.</l>
<l>This is the field where Death and Honour meet,</l>
<l>And all the lesser company are low :</l>
<l>Pale Loveliness has left her mirror now,</l>
<l>And walks the Court of Pain with silent feet.</l></lg>

<lg><l>From cliff to cliff War's cataract goes down,</l>
<l>Hurling its booming waters to the shock,</l>
<l>And tossing high their manes of gleaming spray</l>
<l>The crested chargers leap from rock to rock,</l>
<l>While over all, dark though the thunder frown,</l>
<l>The rainbows climb above to meet the day.<pb n="11"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquit04h" type="poem" n="On A Troopship">
<head rend="center">ON A TROOPSHIP, 1915</head>

<lg><l n="1">FAREWELL, the village leaning to the hill,</l>
<l>And all the cawing rooks that homeward fly ;</l>
<l>The bees; the drowsy anthem of the mill</l>
<l>The willows winding under April sky !</l>
<l>We watch the breakers crashing on the bow,</l>
<l>And those far flashes in the Eastern haze :</l>
<l>The fields and friends, that were, are fainter now</l>
<l>Than whispering of ancient waterways.</l>
<l>Now England stirs, as stirs a dreamer wound</l>
<l>In immemorial slumber ; lids apart,</l>
<l>Soon will she rouse her giant limbs, attuned</l>
<l>To that old music hidden at her heart.</l>
<l>The small occasions and the menial cries</l>
<l>Fade fast away : the little men beware :</l>
<l>She rises in her circuit of the skies,</l>
<l>An eagle drinking of the mountain air.<pb n="12"/></l>
<l>We come to harbour in the breath of wars; </l>
<l>Welcome again, the land of our farewells </l>
<l>In this strange ruin, open to the stars, </l>
<l>We find the haven, where her spirit dwells.<pb n="13"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith05" type="poem" n="Ares, God Of War">
<head rend="center">ARES, GOD OF WAR</head>

<lg><l n="1">UNDER the stars the armies lie asleep: </l>
<l>Between the lines a quiet river flows </l>
<l>Through brakes of honeysuckle, and of rose, </l>
<l>And fields where poppies droop in languor deep: </l>
<l>The night as with a mantle now enfolds </l>
<l>The muffled forms upon the pasture low; </l>
<l>The scent of thyme comes down across the wolds, </l>
<l>And on the roses of the dark hedgerow </l>
<l>The summer starlight falls in flakes of silver snow.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Here, from the wooded haunt of nymph and fawn, </l>
<l>The hidden guns peer forth across the hills, </l>
<l>Their wheels are on the trampled daffodils, </l>
<l>And so they wait the coming of the dawn. </l>
<l>In dappled shadows, where the fairy weaves </l>
<l>On grasses tall his web of sparkling lace, </l>
<l>The gunners lie, their heads upon the sheaves: </l>
<l>White falls the moon on many a sunburnt face, </l>
<l>That ere the day shall feel another God's embrace.<pb n="14"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>Among the barrows of the sunken plain,</l>
<l>Where sleep the soldiers of another day,</l>
<l>On misty meadow and on upland gray,</l>
<l>On many eyes, that close but once again,</l>
<l>The peaceful earth her benediction throws,</l>
<l>The waves of healing music from the streams,</l>
<l>That though the willows softly comes, and goes ;</l>
<l>And now the face of all the country seems</l>
<l>A mirror consecrated to an army's dreams.</l></lg>

<lg><l>From far away is borne a woman's pray'r</l>
<l>To Ares, restless in his iron crown :</l>
<l>"Sleep, Ares, Sleep ! For, once the dice are thrown,</l>
<l>Empires to thee are leaves upon the air !</l>
<l>Ere all the homes go smoking to the skies,</l>
<l>And men are swept upon the battle-blast,</l>
<l>Ere all the tears are wept from women's eyes,</l>
<l>O Queen of Love, hold now the Lover fast,</l>
<l>And let him taste eternal anodyne at last !"<pb n="15"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>But with the dawn there comes a soldier's song:</l>
<l>"When all the guns have fired their last salute,</l>
<l>And the tongues of all the world are mute,</l>
<l>And life is dearer than to right a wrong,</l>
<l>Then may he weary of his burnng wine,</l>
<l>And rest forever in the arms divine</l>
<l>Of Aphrodite passionate and pale-</l>
<l>But Hark !  He comes !  Hail, Ares ! Lord of Thunder, Hail !</l></lg>

<lg><l>"He rides above the ocean and the snow,</l>
<l>His trail is on the curtain of the skies :</l>
<l>Brighter than dawn, his young eternal eyes</l>
<l>Shine in the eyes of Valour far below :</l>
<l>Now Mammon hides beneath his trembling halls,</l>
<l>While Honour marches singing into war ;</l>
<l>On strange forgotten hearts a radiance falls,</l>
<l>As ever nearer, burning from afar,</l>
<l>The sword of Ares gleams above the morning star."<pb n="16"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>"The other gods are weaker ; thou alone</l>
<l>Dost break the king and bend the emperor's knee:</l>
<l>Lower than unto Christ they bow to thee,</l>
<l>Lord of the slave, and guardian of the free,</l>
<l>Steel-hearted Ares, shaker of the throne ;</l>
<l>Young god of battle, restless lover, hail !</l>
<l>For, once a man has seen thine eyes aflame, </l>
<l>And mounted on the horses of the gale,</l>
<l>Death is a nothing, life an empty name:</l>
<l>Arise and lead us ere our blood be tame, </l>
<l>O lord of thunder, Arcs of the crimson mail !<pb n="17"/>"</l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith06" type="poem" n="The Western Line">
<head rend="center">THE WESTERN</head>
<byline rend="center">FLANDERS, 1915.</byline>

<lg><l n="1">THOR draws a chord invisible </l>
<l rend="indent">Across the shaking sky:</l>
<l>I hear the tearing of the shell, </l>
<l rend="indent">The bullets sing and cry,</l>
<l>As, charging through the flames of hell, </l>
<l rend="indent">The batteries go by.</l></lg>

<lg><l>The gunners laugh about the task, </l>
<l rend="indent">That man to man has given:</l>
<l>Like Titans, now the guns unmask, </l>
<l rend="indent">And fire the veils of heaven.</l>
<l>Above the cloud what lights are gleaming? </l>
<l rend="indent">God's batteries are those,</l>
<l>Or souls of soldiers, homeward streaming </l>
<l rend="indent">To banquet with their foes?</l>
<l>The floods of battle ebb and flow,</l>
<l>The soldiers to Valhalla go!<pb n="18"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>They say that, when the day awoke, </l>
<l rend="indent">And the dying night was wan,</l>
<l>Harry of England rode the smoke,</l>
<l rend="indent">And led the English van:</l>
<l>And bowmen in the battle-glare</l>
<l rend="indent">Rose from the ghostly dew:</l>
<l>The clothyard sang upon the air,</l>
<l rend="indent">And the grey goose-feather flew!</l>
<l>Harry of England is awake,</l>
<l>His archers mind not trench or stake !</l></lg>

<lg><l>And men have seen the Emperor,</l>
<l rend="indent">The Eagle of the South:</l>
<l>God grant the bonds be loosed by Thor</l>
<l rend="indent">That bind that marble mouth!</l>
<l>The silver roads of conquest lie</l>
<l rend="indent">Fast frozen in his brow:</l>
<l>Would those imperious lips were free</l>
<l rend="indent">To give their orders now!</l>
<l>The floods of battle ebb and flow,</l>
<l>The soldiers to Valhalla go!<pb n="19"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>Beyond the thunder of the guns, </l>
<l rend="indent">Beyond the flaming line,</l>
<l>Far from this sky of echoing bronze, </l>
<l rend="indent">The English valleys shine;</l>
<l>The gardens, moated in the wolds, </l>
<l rend="indent">By wind and water kissed;</l>
<l>And dainty girls, that England folds </l>
<l rend="indent">In sunshine and in mist.</l>
<l>The floods of battle ebb and flow,</l>
<l>The soldiers to Valhalla go!</l></lg>

<lg><l>The fighting men go charging past, </l>
<l rend="indent">With the battle in their eyes,</l>
<l>The fighting men go reeling past, </l>
<l rend="indent">Like gods in poor disguise:</l>
<l>And stumbling men, whom none will see, </l>
<l rend="indent">No wife or mother more,</l>
<l>Winged with the wings of Victory, </l>
<l rend="indent">And helmeted by Thor!</l></lg>

<lg><l>Above the cloud what lights are gleaming? </l>
<l rend="indent">God's batteries are those,</l>
<l>Or souls of soldiers, homeward streaming </l>
<l rend="indent">To banquet with their foes?<pb n="20"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith07" type="poem" n="Sunset.">
<head rend="center">SUNSET.</head>

<lg><l n="1">HOODED in angry mist, the sun goes down:</l>
<l>Steel-gray the clouds roll out across the Sea:</l>
<l>Is this a Kingdom? Then give Death the crown,</l>
<l>For here no emperor hath won, save He.</l>
<l>Though from the blackened grasses of the spring</l>
<l>The dead look up to where the swallow flies:</l>
<l>And in this woodland never a bird will sing--</l>
<l>The laughter lives within the sentry's eyes.<pb n="21"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith08" type="poem" n="After The Salvo">
<head rend="center">AFTER THE SALVO.</head>

<lg><l n="1">UP and down, up and down </l>
<l>They go, the gray rat, and the brown. </l>
<l>The telegraph lines are tangled hair, </l>
<l>Motionless on the sullen air </l>
<l>An engine has fallen on its back, </l>
<l>With crazy wheels, on a twisted track </l>
<l>All ground to dust is the little town. </l>
<l>Up and down, up and down </l>
<l>They go, the gray rat, and the brown </l>
<l>A skull, torn out of the graves near by, </l>
<l>Gapes in the grass. A butterfly, </l>
<l>In azure irridescence new, </l>
<l>Floats into the world, across the dew </l>
<l>Between the flow'rs. Have we lost our way,</l>
<l> Or are we toys of a god at play, </l>
<l>Who do these things on a young Spring day?</l></lg>

<lg><l>Where the salvo fell, on a splintered ledge </l>
<l>Of ruin, at the crater's edge, </l>
<l>A poppy lives: and young, and fair, </l>
<l>The dewdrops hang on the spider's stair, </l>
<l>With every rainbow still unhurt<pb n="22"/></l>
<l>From leaflet unto leaflet girt. </l>
<l>Man's house is crushed ; the spider's lives </l>
<l>Inscrutably He takes, and gives, </l>
<l>Who guards not any temple here, </l>
<l>Save the temple of the gossamer.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Up and down, up and down </l>
<l>They go, the gray rat and the brown: </l>
<l>A pistol cracks: they too are dead.</l></lg>

<lg><l>The nightwind rustles overhead.<pb n="23"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith09" type="poem" n="The Fallen Subaltern">
<head rend="center">THE FALLEN SUBALTERN.</head>

<lg><l n="1">THE starshells float above, the bayonets glisten</l>
<l rend="indent">We bear our fallen friend without a sound;</l>
<l>Below the waiting legions lie and listen</l>
<l rend="indent">To us, who march upon their burial-ground.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Wound in the flag of England, here we lay him;</l>
<l rend="indent">The guns will flash and thunder o'er the grave;</l>
<l>What other winding sheet should now array him,</l>
<l rend="indent">What other music should salute the brave ?</l></lg>

<lg><l>As goes the Sun-god in his chariot glorious,</l>
<l rend="indent">When all his golden banners are unfurled,</l>
<l>So goes the soldier, fallen but victorious,</l>
<l rend="indent">And leaves behind a twilight in the world.<pb n="24"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>And those, who come this way in days hereafter,</l>
<l>Will know that here a boy for England fell,</l>
<l>Who looked at danger with the eyes of laughter,</l>
<l> And on the charge his days were ended well.</l></lg>

<lg><l>One last salute; the bayonets clash and glisten; </l>
<l>With arms reversed we go without a sound:</l>
<l>One more has joined the men who lie and listen </l>
<l>To us, who march upon their burial-ground.<pb n="25"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith10" type="poem" n="The Fallen Spire">
<head rend="center">THE FALLEN SPIRE.<lb/>
(A FLEMISH VILLAGE).</head>

<lg><l n="1">THE spire is gone, that slept for centuries, </l>
<l rend="indent">Mirrored among the lilies, calm and low:</l>
<l>And now the water holds but empty skies,</l>
<l rend="indent">Through which the rivers of the thunder flow.</l></lg>

<lg><l>The church lies broken near the fallen spire:</l>
<l rend="indent">For here, among these old and human things,</l>
<l>Death sweeps along the street with feet of fire,</l>
<l rend="indent">And goes upon his way with moaning wings.</l></lg>

<lg><l>On pavements by the kneeling herdsmen worn</l>
<l rend="indent">The drifting fleeces of the shells are rolled</l>
<l>Above the Saints a village Christ forlorn,</l>
<l rend="indent">Wounded again, looks down upon his fold.</l></lg>

<lg><l>And silence follows fast: no evening peace,</l>
<l rend="indent">But leaden stillness, when the thunder wanes,</l>
<l>Haunting the slender branches of the trees,</l>
<l rend="indent">And settling low upon the listless plains.<pb n="26"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith11" type="poem" n="The Fallen Poet">
<head rend="center">THE FALLEN POET</head>

<lg><l n="1">NOW that the soul has left its throne</l>
<l rend="indent">Behind your mortal eyes,</l>
<l>And light, and colour and sound are gone</l>
<l rend="indent">From the body's palaces :</l>
<l>Still in his wood the blackbird calls,</l>
<l rend="indent">But there is one too few to hear :</l>
<l>And one too few to watch the trout</l>
<l rend="indent">Swim through the music of the weir.</l></lg>

<lg><l>And once I dreamt that you were gone,</l>
<l rend="indent">As dust upon the wave ;</l>
<l>Or, as a drop in some deep well,</l>
<l rend="indent">That none could sort or save.</l>
<l>But falling low between the stars,</l>
<l rend="indent">So soon as I had such a fear,</l>
<l>At dusk and dawn a whisper came :</l>
<l rend="indent">"The dead are near: the dead are near."<pb n="27"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith12" type="poem" n="Soldiers At Peace">
<head rend="center">SOLDIERS AT PEACE</head>
<lg><l n="1">Mourn not for these, the children of the spring :</l>
<l>On Flemish plains and far Aegean sand,</l>
<l>Mourn not for these, who had no perishing !</l>
<l>Hang high their swords in churches greatly spanned !</l>
<l>Whose deeds have spoken so, beyond our tears,</l>
<l>Their spirits live, needing no other voice</l>
<l>Above the dimming valley of the years</l>
<l>They live anew, immortal by their choice.</l></lg>

<lg><l>The soldiers' peace of their imagining</l>
<l>has fallen here.  The whirling leaves are still:</l>
<l>Deep in the shadow of the rainwashed hill,</l>
<l>A lustre and a quietude art shed,</l>
<l>When all the valley streams are glimmering,</l>
<l>And the moon swims from the storm-wrack overhead.<pb n="31"/></l></lg></div>



<div id="asquith13" type="poem" n="To A Baby Found Paddling Near The Lines">
<head rend="center">TO A BABY FOUND PADDLING NEAR THE </head>

<lg><l n="1">HAIL! O Baby of the May </l>
<l>In the bubbling river-bed, </l>
<l>Playing where the cannon play, </l>
<l>With the shrapnel overhead!</l>
<l>Sparkling in and flashing out </l>
<l>Through the eddies and the shallows, </l>
<l>With your feet among the trout, </l>
<l>And your head among the swallows; </l>
<l>While the wag-tails on the daisies </l>
<l>Lead you in the minuet, </l>
<l>Twinkling through the flow'ry mazes, </l>
<l>Baby, do you quite forget </l>
<l>That, with shrapnel overhead, </l>
<l>Other babes are put to bed ?</l></lg>

<lg><l>Baby, may the buttercup, </l>
<l>When you tumble, pick you up; </l>
<l>If you fall beside the willow,</l>
<l>Lilies rise to be your pillow!</l>
<l>In the winter should you go </l>
<l>Straying far without a rest,<pb n="32"/></l>
<l>Down beneath the drifting snow </l>
<l>You shall be the mouse's guest;</l>
<l>May the bull-frog be your Knight, </l>
<l>And the tit your templar true!</l>
<l>May the fairy guide you right </l>
<l>Wandering through a misty land, </l>
<l>At the crossings of the dew, </l>
<l>With the rainbow in her hand! </l>
<l>Should you fall from branches high, </l>
<l>And go tumbling down the sky, </l>
<l>May the heron in the air </l>
<l>Take you floating on his wings, </l>
<l>And the cloudlets be your stair, </l>
<l>Over palaces of Kings </l>
<l>Riding high above the wold, </l>
<l>Larks your sentinels shall be, </l>
<l>Challenging with tongues of gold </l>
<l>Those who try to cage the free !</l></lg>

<lg><l>So, philosopher of May, </l>
<l>With my blessing go your way! </l>
<l>If you win such friends as these </l>
<l>You need never have a care, </l>
<l>Cannon you may safely tease,<pb n="33"/></l>
<l>And may juggle, at your ease, </l>
<l>With the whizzbang in the air </l>
<l>Though the world be full of sadness, </l>
<l>You may still have fun and gladness, </l>
<l>And be happy for a day, </l>
<l>Playing where the cannon play.<pb n="34"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith14" type="poem" n=" Fortune Of War">
<head rend="center">FORTUNE OF WAR.</head>
<lg><l n="1">THE far guns boom: shell-struck the church is rolled </l>
<l>Skyward athunder, dust of rose and gold:</l>
<l>The staring villa stands. So goes the War: </l>
<l>The limelight lives: extinguished is the star.<pb n="35"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith15" type="poem" n="Jewels. A Young Man To A Merchant">
<head rend="center">JEWELS.<lb/>
A YOUNG MAN TO A MERCHANT.</head>

<lg><l n="1">OLD Man, your pearls are not for us, </l>
<l rend="indent">Your rubies die too soon:</l>
<l>Have you the pearls of Sirius,</l>
<l rend="indent">Or opals of the moon?</l></lg>

<lg><l>I do not ask for other gems;</l>
<l rend="indent">Flashing with frost and fire </l>
<l>The sky's undying diadems</l>
<l rend="indent">Shall be my love's attire.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Emeralds, that into rubies melt</l>
<l rend="indent">Upon the brow of night,</l>
<l> I've taken from Orion's belt</l>
<l rend="indent">To make her girdle bright.</l></lg>

<lg><l>On high ways of the albatross</l>
<l rend="indent">I scale the purple air </l>
<l>For sapphires of the Southern Cross</l>
<l rend="indent">And wreath them in her hair<pb n="36"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>Her robe it is the morning sky, </l>
<l rend="indent">Her veil it is the West;</l>
<l>So robed, so veiled my love will fly. </l>
<l rend="indent">When I am gone to rest.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Yet all the rays of all the moons, </l>
<l rend="indent">The lights of all the skies</l>
<l>Are pale beside the dim lagoons</l>
<l rend="indent">Of those mysterious eyes.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Old Man, your pearls are not for us, </l>
<l rend="indent">Your rubies die too soon:</l>
<l>Have you the pearls of Sirius,</l>
<l rend="indent">Or opals of the moon<pb n="37"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith16" type="poem" n="Love And Humour">
<head rend="center">LOVE AND HUMOUR.</head>
<lg><l n="1">WHEN first I saw you, in eclipse,</l>
<l rend="indent">A veil about your head, </l>
<l>And wondered at those unseen lips</l>
<l rend="indent">With wit bediamonded:</l>
<l>Then laughing down the street I went,</l>
<l>And sang upon my way, content.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Next time we met in dim surmise, </l>
<l rend="indent">Upon an autumn morn, </l>
<l>And in those understanding eyes</l>
<l rend="indent">Shone humour, rainbow-born:</l>
<l>So travelling through this earthly maze,</l>
<l>A greater light fell on my ways.</l></lg>

<lg><l>But, when I saw your head unveiled,</l>
<l rend="indent">Feature, and form, and hue:</l>
<l>A woodland fairy, silver-mailed,</l>
<l rend="indent">Lightwinged upon the dew:</l>
<l>Then did I pay a heavy cost,</l>
<l>For love, a world of laughter lost.<pb n="38"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith17" type="poem" n="The Bather">
<head rend="center">l>THE BATHER.</head>

<lg><l n="1"> THE sea-breeze beating on her brow, </l>
<l>The foam asurge her shining feet, </l>
<l>She stood,--a silver Victory, </l>
<l>Poised high on some Athenian prow, </l>
<l>Leading against a tyrant fleet </l>
<l>The winged vanguard of the free.<pb n="39"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith18" type="poem" n="The Charioteer">
<head rend="center">THE CHARIOTEER</head>
<byline rend="center">(TO A CHILD).</byline>

<lg><l n="1"> LOVE be thy charioteer: </l>
<l>In all thy brightening and thy darkening hours </l>
<l>May he be at thine ear; </l>
<l>So shalt thou sail at ease above the tow'rs,</l>
<l>Where pale Ambition, in his clouded hood, </l>
<l>Climbs, step by step, the stair; </l>
<l>And Beauty, dancing in the roadside flow'rs, </l>
<l>Or resting in her mountain quietude, </l>
<l>Tresses a-wander on the sunlit air, </l>
<l>Shall meet thee everywhere. </l>
<l>Then the fast-withered leaves of poor Caprice </l>
<l>Shall live again; and she be happy yet. </l>
<l>Freed from the tangle of her glittering net: </l>
<l>And Poverty no longer want for alms, </l>
<l>And everything be blessed, </l>
<l>Save fevered Avarice, </l>
<l>With his discoloured palms, </l>
<l>And talons prisoned in his own gray breast.<pb n="40"/></l>
<l>Above the path of death, </l>
<l>Through field and wood, </l>
<l>Mountain and flood, </l>
<l>Upon the whirlwind's breath, </l>
<l>My way be sped! </l>
<l>If die thou must, </l>
<l>With wine and crust, </l>
<l>Through flow'rs to dust, </l>
<l>Be thou so charioted!<pb n="41"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith19" type="poem" n="The Silver Birch">
<head rend="center">THE SILVER BIRCH.</head>

<lg><l n="1"> O SILVER one, O silver one,</l>
<l rend="indent">Above the valley of the Bane: </l>
<l>O stem with snow-water agleam, </l>
<l rend="indent">And glistening limbs, and trails of pearl.</l></lg>

<lg><l>The sun has sent a slanting kiss:</l>
<l rend="indent">Red fire and gold, his arrows burn: </l>
<l>Now that he aims a shaft at thee, </l>
<l rend="indent">Red fire and gold to silver turn!</l></lg>

<lg><l>When I am spent with the ways of men.</l>
<l rend="indent">I'll wash my hands in melting snow:</l>
<l>And  live with thee among the oaks,</l>
<l rend="indent">And watch the river swirl below.</l></lg>

<lg><l>But I must ever be travelling </l>
<l>From sea to sea, from shoal to shoal: </l>
<l>Farewell ! O still and beautiful, </l>
<l>I would thy valley were my goal!<pb n="42"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith20" type="poem" n="Riding">
<head rend="center">RIDING</head>

<lg><l n="1"> FILL up, fill up the stirrup-cup!</l>
<l rend="indent">The wine is running free:</l>
<l>The blue veils of the Spring are out;</l>
<l rend="indent">She dances on the sea.</l>
<l>In fields of love, in lanes of laughter, </l>
<l rend="indent">Slacken not the pace:</l>
<l>Care not for Him, who follows after, </l>
<l rend="indent">And wins at last the race.</l>
<l>Past pear and apple-orchards, </l>
<l rend="indent">The bramble and the rose,</l>
<l>And out across the swinging turf </l>
<l rend="indent">To where the sea-wind goes:</l>
<l>To horse! To horse! the time is short;</l>
<l rend="indent"> Soon will the day be done:</l>
<l>We'll gallop on the morning grass, </l>
<l rend="indent">And drink the rising sun:</l>
<l>And onward through the upland, </l>
<l rend="indent">To see the plains unfurled,</l>
<l>And armies of the stars go down </l>
<l rend="indent">Over the brink of the world.<pb n="43"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith21" type="poem" n="The Fairy Lover">
<head rend="center">THE FAIRY LOVER.</head>

<lg><l n="1"> SHE lay beneath an appletree,</l>
<l rend="indent">A marble maiden, free from care;</l>
<l>And round her was a canopy</l>
<l rend="indent">Of moonlit air.</l></lg>

<lg><l>He made his bed among the leaf,</l>
<l rend="indent">And on a petal softly blown, </l>
<l>He touched a vein upon her brow</l>
<l rend="indent">With grief unknown.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Then lightly, where the lashes fall,</l>
<l rend="indent">Entered the chamber of her soul;</l>
<l>And, finding there a silver bell,</l>
<l rend="indent">He made it toll.<pb n="44"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith22" type="poem" n="A Dedication">
<head rend="center">A DEDICATION</head>

<lg><l n="1"> FRIEND if all these verses die:</l>
<l>Soon will you, and soon will I</l>
<l>But, if any word should live, </l>
<l>Then that word to you I give.<pb n="45"/></l></lg></div>


<div id="asquith23" type="poem" n="Venice">
<head rend="center">VENICE</head>

<lg><l n="1"> IN domes of dim and ancient gold, </l>
<l rend="indent">In cloisters, where the lightning plays,</l>
<l>Where gleam the gorgeous saints of old </l>
<l rend="indent">In aisles of jade and chrysoprase, </l>
<l>In halls that wave like waving water,</l>
<l>Still moves the voice of Ocean's daughter.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Venice ! What siren music then </l>
<l rend="indent">Stirred on the shoals and shallow sea,</l>
<l>When that small band of wandering men </l>
<l rend="indent">First in their dreams imagined thee, </l>
<l>And hung thy lyric splendour high</l>
<l>Between the water and the sky!</l></lg>

<lg><l>What Triton strains in other days </l>
<l rend="indent">Were heard, when, on a sea of flame,</l>
<l>Thy battlefleet swung through the haze,</l>
<l rend="indent">And homeward in her glory came,</l>
<l>Bearing the beauty of the East</l>
<l>To make Thy happy saint a feast.<pb n="46"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>Now, though that sceptre-hand be cold,</l>
<l rend="indent">Those argent argosies no more</l>
<l>Their Tyrian-tinted wings unfold</l>
<l rend="indent">From Cyprus unto Elsinore;</l>
<l>With broken sword, and banner furled,</l>
<l>How dies the Siren of the world?</l></lg>

<lg><l>The cloud has lifted from the stars,</l>
<l rend="indent">And now again the starlight falls;</l>
<l>Now Venus calls again to Mars,</l>
<l rend="indent">And Bacchus reels about his halls</l>
<l>And, lovely in a thousand forms,</l>
<l>Our Lady drifts above the storms.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Among the moonlit marble lace,</l>
<l rend="indent">That wreathes this avenue forlorn,</l>
<l>Some God has made his dwelling place</l>
<l rend="indent">And takes his manna from the morn;</l>
<l>And every young and wandering soul,</l>
<l>That passes here, must pay its toll.<pb n="47"/></l></lg>

<lg><l>Far off the city fades away, </l>
<l rend="indent">Save where one tow'r of rosy light, </l>
<l>Like some dissolving shaft of day, </l>
<l rend="indent">Pierces the bosom of the night:</l>
<l>The distant lightning breaks its shroud:</l>
<l>Valhalla gleams beyond the cloud.</l></lg>

<lg><l>Alone we float through gulfs remote,</l>
<l rend="indent">The black canal no longer seen;</l>
<l>My boat it is a fairy boat, </l>
<l rend="indent">Above the ripple silver-green, </l>
<l>Upon the wavelet violet-crowned,</l>
<l>My boat and I are outward bound!</l></lg>
</div>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
