<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Postcard Description test</title>
            <author>Unknown Author</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
	   <p>[vacuous publication statement]</p>
	 </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>[vacuous source description]</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<p><figure entity="boy_soldier" ana="hf-c t-pre im-ph nat-brit">
<head>Off to the Front</head>
<figDesc>This postcard is a color picture of a young boy standing in the grass, wearing a hat and a shoulder harness with wooden weapons. Text at bottom right: "Off to the front". On reverse: a handwritten message.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure entity="Britain_needs" ana="nat-brit hf-p im-po">
<head>Britain Needs You at Once</head>
<figDesc>This color postcard depicts a knight on a white horse spearing a dragon. Text at top: "Britain &#x00B7; Needs". Text at bottom: "You  &#x00B7; At  &#x00B7; Once". Beneath the bottom text: "Published by the Parliamentary Recruiting Committee London Poster No 108 Printed by Spottiswoode L Co Ltd London EC". On reverse: "Dalkeith Classic Poster Card P79 Anonymous, Great Britain."</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="constant_love" ana="hf-ro nat-brit">
<head>Constant Love</head>
<figDesc>This postcard is a cartoon-like black and white picture of a soldier sitting at a writing desk and reading a letter. In the top right corner is an inset of a woman looking down at him. Text at top left: "Constant Love". Text centered at bottom: "Memories of the happy days,/Arise within my heart,/And my love is constant,/Although we're far apart." On reverse: "Entirely British Manufacture."</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="dear_mother1" ana="im-s nat-fr">
<head>To My Dear Mother</head>
<figDesc>This postcard has embossed flowers surrounding an embroidered picture of flowers and a sailboat. Embroidered text at bottom: "To My Dear Mother". On reverse: "Mod&#x00E8;le D&#x00E9;pos&#x00E9;", "Vise Paris" and "Fabrication Fran&#x00E7;aise"; a handwritten message.</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="dont_worry" ana="hf-w nat-us im-pa">
<head>"Don't Worry About Me"</head>
<figDesc>This postcard is a color drawing of a soldier standing with a woman who has grey hair. Text at bottom center: "'Don't worry about me'". Text next to soldier's feet: "Archie Gunn". On reverse: "Illustrated Postal Card &#x0026; Nov. Co. N.Y."; "Printed in the U.S.A."</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="Ecce_Homo" ana="nat-it hf-re t-wwi">
<head>Ecco L'Uomo (Ecce Homo!) 1915. Ecce Homo</head>
<figDesc>This postcard is a black and white drawing of a statue of a man which has fallen over into rubble. Text at top left: "Ecco L'Uomo (Ecce Homo!)"; "1915. Ecce Homo". Text at bottom left: "Noi, tedeschi, non temiamo che Dio." Text at bottom right: "Nous, Allemands, nous ne craignons que Dieu." On reverse: "Copyright di Societ&#x00E0; Editoriale Milanese - Milano/Reproduction interdite"; "Ufficio Rev. Stampa - Milano, 30-3-1917-N.162".</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure entity="feed_the_world" ana="nat-us con-v hf-p t-wwi">
<head>We Must Feed the World</head>
<p><text><body><l>It may not be that you'll be called </l>
<l>To go and carry arms,</l>
<l>But you can serve the Flag as well</l>
<l>At home upon the farms,</l>
<l>The service there is just as great</l>
<l>It's food the soldiers need,</l>
<l>And this great land of ours today</l>
<l>Has all the world to feed</l></body></text></p>
<figDesc>This postcard has a color drawing of a flag and a poem
entitled "We Must Feed the World." The poem speaks to the farmers who
are not fighting, but can contribute to the war effort with their
produce. At bottom right: "2194". On reverse: handwritten message.</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="flowerfield" ana="im-pa nat-us nat-bel t-wwi">
<figDesc>This postcard is a color picture of a flower field with children picking flowers in it. On reverse: "Flanders Field/'Where Soldiers Sleep/And Poppies Grow'/by Robert W. Vonnoh/58" x 104" Oil. Painted 1914./The Butler Institute of American Art/524 Wick Avenue/Youngstown, Ohio 44502"; "Kolorvue by Artvue Post Card Co., 160 Fifth Ave., New York, N.Y. 10010".</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="fond_memories" ana="nat-brit hf-w hf-p">
<head>Fond Memories</head>
<p><text><body><l>Though distance us may sever,</l>
<l>And keep us far apart</l>
<l>Sweet thoughts of you my loved one,</l>
<l>Arise within my heart.</l></body></text></p>
<figDesc>This postcard is a black and white picture of a soldier sitting at a desk and writing a letter. In the top right corner is an inset of a woman. Text at top left: "Fond Memories". Text at bottom center: "Though distance may us sever,/And keep us far apart,/Sweet thoughts of you my loved one,/Arise within my heart." On reverse: "Entirely British Manufacture".</figDesc>
</figure>


<figure entity="forget_not_anchor" ana="hf-h nat-us">
<head>Forget Me Not</head>
<figDesc>The face of this postcard is a brown, velvety material with a gold, lace border. In the middle of the card is a gold, plastic anchor. Text at bottom center in gold plastic: "Forget Me Not". On reverse: handwritten message; "Made in Cincinnati, O., by Vita Habib, 42 E. Fifth Street."</figDesc>
</figure>


<figure entity="gloria" ana="nat-fr hf-w hf-ro">
<figDesc>This postcard is a color-tinted, sepia-toned picture of a soldier with a bouquet looking up at a woman holding a bouquet. Text in middle left: "Vous avez pris ma fleur d'amour!/Gardez-l&#x00E0; jusqu'&#x00E0; mon retour!" In bottom left: "380". Text in bottom right: "Gloria". On reverse: "Fabrication Fran&#x00E7;aise". </figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="if_dreams" ana="hf-w hf-ro">
<head>If dreams would only just come true, Then, sweetheart dear, I'd be with you.</head>
<figDesc>This postcard has two color pictures. In the center is a picture of a soldier sleeping in a tent. To the left is a picture of him walking with a young woman. Text at bottom right: "If dreams would only/just come true,/Then, sweetheart dear,/I'd be with you." On reverse: "&#x00A9; Illustrated Postal Card &#x0026; Nov. Co., N. Y."</figDesc>
</figure>


<figure entity="in_memoriam" ana="nat-brit con-m">
<head>In Memoriam</head>
<p>To the memory of the brave sons of the British Empire who, in the
greatest hour of its destiny, laid down their lives for the future
welfare of humanity, and who, having made the supreme sacrifice, are
now assembled as God's happy warriors on the Plains of Peace.</p>
<figDesc>This postcard is a sepia-toned drawing of a soldier with a cannon in the background. Above the soldier is a text honoring the British soldiers who lost their lives in battle. The picture is bordered by a blue and green design. Text at top center: "In Memoriam". Text at bottom center: "Requiescant in Pace." On reverse: blank.</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="Jeder_Schuss" ana="im-ca nat-de t-wwi mil-p">
<figDesc>This postcard has several black and white cartoons. In the top left corner is a cartoon of a soldier shooting a Russian soldier. Text underneath: "Jeder Schuss ein Russ'." In the top right corner is a cartoon of a soldier stabbing a French soldier. Text underneath: "Jeder Stoss ein Franzos'." In the middle left is a cartoon of a sailor kicking a man from behind. Text underneath: "Der Englishmann kommtauch jetzt dran." In the middle right is a cartoon of a rooster and a man standing behind it with a knife. Text underneath: "Nach Japan kr&#x00E4;hf kein Hahn." In the bottom left is a cartoon of a soldier holding another man up by his collar. Text beneath: "Jhr in Belgien k&#x00F6;nntuns nicht behelligen." In the bottom center is a cartoon of a fat man and three roosters. Text underneath: "&#x00DC;ber die Montenegriner lachen selbst die H&#x00FC;hner". In the bottom right is a cartoon of a soldier stabbing a man on the ground. Text underneath: "Auch in Serbien soll'n se sterbien". On reverse: blank.</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="kaisers_dream" ana="nat-brit con-v con-h t-wwi">
<head>The Kaiser's Dream</head>
<p><text><body><l>There's a story now current, though strange it may seem,</l>
<l>Of the great Kaiser Bill and a wonderful dream.</l>
<l>Being tired of the Allies, he lay down in bed,</l>
<l>And amongst other things he dreamt he was dead.</l>
<l>On leaving the earth to Heaven, he went straight,</l>
<l>Arriving up there, he knocked at the gate,</l>
<l>But St. Peter looked out, and in voice loud and clear,</l>
<l>Said "Begone Kaiser Bill, we don't want you here."</l>
<l>Well, says the Kaiser, that's very uncivil,</l>
<l>I suppose after that, I must go to the Devil?</l>
<l>So he turned on his heel, and off he did go</l>
<l>At the top of his speed to the regions below,</l>
<l>And when he got there he was filled with dismay,</l>
<l>For, while waiting outside, he heard Old Nick say</l>
<l>To his imps: "Now look here, boys, I give you all warning,</l>
<l>I'm expecting the Kaiser down here in the morning;</l>
<l>But don't let him in, for to me its quite clear,</l>
<l>He's a very bad man, and we don't want him here.</l>
<l>If he ever gets in we'll have no end of quarrels,</l>
<l>In fact, I'm aftaid he'll corrupt our good morals."</l>
<l>"Oh, Satan, my dear friend," the Kaiser then cried,</l>
<l>"Excuse me for listening while waiting outside;</l>
<l>If you don't admit me, then where can I go,</l>
<l>Oh do let me in for I'm feeling quite cold.</l>
<l>And if you want money, I've got plenty of gold;</l>
<l>Let me sit in a corner, no matter how hot;"</l>
<l>"No, no," said Old Nickie, "most certainly not;</l>
<l>We do not admit folks for riches and wealth;</l>
<l>Here are sulphur and matches, make a Hell for yourself."</l>
<l>Then he kicked William out, and vanished in smoke,</l>
<l>and just at that moment the Kaiser awoke.</l>
<l>He jumped out of bed in a shivering sweat;</l>
<l>and said, "Well, that dream I shall never forget;</l>
<l>That I won't go to Heaven I know very well,</l>
<l>But it's really too bad to be kicked out of Hell."</l></body></text></p>
<figDesc>This postcard is a poem entitled "The Kaiser's Dream." It tells a story of "Kaiser Bill" having a dream that he is not admitted to heaven and kicked out of hell. On reverse: "E. Mack King Henry's Road, London N.W."; "Printed in England"; a handwritten message.</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="kriegsanleihe" ana="nat-de im-po t-wwi hf-p">
<head>Kriegsanleihe</head>
<figDesc>This postcard is colored drawing of people tearing down the British flag. Text at bottom center: "St&#x00FC;tzt Unsre Feldgrauen";"Zereisst Englands Macht Zeichnet"; "Kriegsanleihe". Text at bottom left: "Druck v. Wilh.Eisfeller-C&#x00F6;ln". Text at bottom right: "Otto Lehmann-C&#x00F6;ln". On reverse: "Dalkeith Classic Poster P83/Otto Lehmann, Germany/Translation: 'Support our field grey. Rend England's might. Subscribe to the war loan'". </figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="last_goodbyes" ana="hf-w hf-ro hf-p t-wwi">
<head>When the Last Goodbyes Are Whispered</head>
<figDesc>This postcard is a color drawing of a soldier and a woman embracing. Text beside picture: "Archie Gunn". Text at bottom center: "When the Last Goodbyes Are Whispered". On reverse: "1368 &#x00A9; Illustrated Postal Card &#x0026; Nov. Co. N. Y."; "Printed in the U.S.A."</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="loving_son" ana="im-s nat-fr t-wwi">
<head>From Your Loving Son</head>
<figDesc>This postcard has embroidered flowers and a butterfly; the
wings are flags; "From Your Loving Son" embroidered in the bottom right corner. On reverse: "Fabrication Fran&#x00E7;aise"; handwritten message.</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="loving_thoughts" ana="hf-h t-wwi con-v nat-us">
<head>Loving Thoughts</head>
<p><text><body><head>The Trail that Leads to Home</head><l>There's a
trail that calls me homeward night and day,</l>
<l>In my dreams the loved ones beckon far away;</l>
<l>Through the shadows and the sunshine some day I shall roam</l>
<l>Down that long, long trail a-winding&#x2014;the trail that leads
back to home.</l></body></text></p>
<figDesc>This postcard has an inset of a soldier in the top left
corner. To the right of the inset is "Loving Thoughts". Beneath the
inset are two flowers, an open book, and a poem entitled "The Trail
that Leads to Home". Text beneath poem: "Bamforth copyright. By kind
permission of West &#x0026; Co., Rathbone Place, London, W." On
reverse: "&#x00A9; 1918 Bamforth &#x0026; Co., 96 Warren St., New
York."; handwritten message; has mirror writing.</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure entity="loving_wishes" ana="hf-w hf-ro nat-brit">
<head>Loving Wishes</head>
<p><text><body><l>Only a wish deep and tender,</l>
<l>Only a greeting that's true,</l>
<l>Straight from the heart of the sender,</l>
<l>Memory's message to you.</l>
</body></text></p>
<figDesc>This postcard has a black and white picture of a soldier writing a letter at a desk. In the top right corner is an inset of a woman. Text at bottom left: "Only a wish deep and tender,/Only a greeting that's true,/Straight from the heart of the sender,/Memory's message to you." On reverse: "Entirely British Manufacture."</figDesc>
</figure>
</p></body>
<back>
<div>
<interpGrp type="nationality">
<interp id="nat-brit" value="Britain"/>
<interp id="nat-fr" value="France"/>
<interp id="nat-us" value="United States"/>
<interp id="nat-it" value="Italy"/>
<interp id="nat-de" value="Germany"/>
<interp id="nat-rus" value="Russia"/>
<interp id="nat-ee" value="Eastern Europe"/>
<interp id="nat-bel" value="Belgium"/>
<interp id="nat-ca" value="Canada"/>
<interp id="nat-jp" value="Japan"/>
<interp id="nat-nl" value="Netherlands"/>
</interpGrp>
<p></p><interpGrp type="military">
<interp id="mil-a" value="Army"/>
<interp id="mil-na" value="Navy"/>
<interp id="mil-i" value="Infantry"/>
<interp id="mil-p" value="propaganda"/>
<interp id="mil-f" value="battle front"/>
<interp id="mil-nur" value="nurse"/>
</interpGrp><p></p>
<interpGrp type="homefront">
<interp id="hf-w" value="women"/>
<interp id="hf-c" value="children"/>
<interp id="hf-p" value="propaganda"/>
<interp id="hf-re" value="religion"/>
<interp id="hf-ro" value="romance"/>
<interp id="hf-h" value="home"/>
</interpGrp><p></p>
<interpGrp type="content">
<interp id="con-v" value="verse"/>
<interp id="con-h" value="humor"/>
<interp id="con-p" value="person"/>
<interp id="con-m" value="memorial"/><!-- use with im-ph to indicate
photo of memorial -->
</interpGrp><p></p>
<interpGrp type="image">
<interp id="im-s" value="silks"/>
<interp id="im-ph" value="photo"/>
<interp id="im-pa" value="painting"/>
<interp id="im-ca" value="cartoon"/>
<interp id="im-en" value="engraving"/>
<interp id="im-po" value="poster"/>
</interpGrp><p></p>
<interpGrp type="time period">
<interp id="t-pre" value="pre Great War"/>
<interp id="t-wwi" value="during Great War"/>
<interp id="t-post" value="post Great War"/>
<interp id="t-ww2" value="World War II"/>
</interpGrp>
</div>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
